
ELECTION MANIFESTO—1996     Our Vision, Our Faith, Our Commitment It is out of the past that the future is moulded.
It is the past that becomes the future... —Swami Vivekananda Even as this century draws to a close and the millennium to ins, India stands at a critical crossroad of history.
Centuries’ old hopes and aspirations of our people yearn for a true expression.
The destiny of our land and its people cries for fulfilment.
At such crucial turns historical choices are made and instruments of change adopted.
That destined vehicle of change is the Bharatiya Janata Party.
Never before in the long history of our land has the country been governed by such a morally rudderless and financially corrupt regime.
Seldom have our trusting people been duped by a baser band.
With the people’s hopes belied and their aspirations thwarted, our ancient land stands today face to face with the option of a real change, a chance for a true departure from the last 50 years of Congress misrule, an alternative and an option: The Bharatiya Janata Party.
Our people are looking towards the BJP to become just this instrument of change.
The party is ready to shoulder this great duty and responsibility.
The task is nothing short of rekindling the lamp of our eternal ‘Dharma’, that Sanatan thought which our sages bequeathed to mankind — a social system based on compassion, cooperation, justice, freedom, equality and tolerance.
To reallse this goal, the BJP will launch a new social, economic and political order.
It will strive to transform the existing system of   2 , to make it responsive and answerable to the concerns of our citizens.
It will strive to make the economy cater to the largest demands of the largest number.
The party will endeavour to place in the service of the nation a political organisation that is conscientous and clean.
Above all, the BJP will secure for India a place in the comity of nations which befits its vast cultural, intellectual, economic, scientific and human wealth.
We realise that correcting the mistakes of the last 50 years of Congress misrule, of piecing together the shattered dreams of our citizens, of restructuring our polity which has been delivered a body blow by the present regime, of restoring 10 the state’s authority and reviving faith in the Government, is by no means an easy task.
But we also realise that only the BJP has the ideological commitment, moral conviction and political courage to shoulder this task and gently guide our nation into the next millennium.
The present millennium began with the subjugation of our ancient land; let a reinvigorated, proud, prosperous and strong India herald the next millennium.
In this noble mission, we shall be guided by our Manifesto — it contains our commitments to the nation and its citizens.
Our state governments in Uttar Pradesh, Himachal Pradesh, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Rajasthan, Gujarat and Delhi have demonstrated that for the BJP, these commitments constitute a sacred covenant with the people.
We do what we say.
This Manifesto shall be the covenant of our government.
With a BJP Government at the Centre, the next five years will be devoted to implementing our Manifesto based on the four concepts of Suraksha, Shuchita, Swadeshi and Samrasata.
Hindutva, or cultural nationalism, shall be the rainbow which will bridge our present to our glorious past and pave the way for an equally glorious future; it will guide the transition from Swarajya to Surajya.
Our Manifesto reflects the application of these four concepts in good governance and their role in moulding the nation we dreamt of on the dawn of Independence — a prosperous and strong India, a country where every citizen regards this land of ours, this Bharatbhoomi, that stretches from the Indus to the seas, as his sacred motherland.
The BJP believes in one nation, one people, and one culture.
We are, therefore, committed to promoting social reconciliation rather than conflict.
We are resolved to put an end to the politics of competitive communalism, of appeasement, and of casteism.
The politics of pitting caste against caste, community against community and class against class has torn asunder our social fabric.
The BJP will reweave this fabric into a harmonious pattern.
   2 Nation, Our State, Our Government A New Direction, A New Dispensation.
Nearly half a century of Congress misrule has all but shattered the internal polity of the country.
There is not one institution of the Republic left that can be said to now be in a state of total health.
The Legislature, the Executive, unfortunately the Judiciary, and even the media have been afflicted by the mindlessness of the Congress’ exploitation and loot of our country.
The Bharatiya Janata Party well recognises that to correct this great wrong of the past five decades requires the skill and commitment of a Vishwakarma.
With humility, we address ourselves to this task.
The first is to restore to our state its authority.
Perhaps never since the scourge of the Pindaries has the writ of our state been as enfeebled as by this Congress misrule.
The primary task, therefore, is to restore to the state, and to governance, its honour and its prestige — izzat and iqbal.
For this the BJP will institute a set of measures.
This is a challenge that is principally moral and only then functional.
The BJP commits itself, therefore, to: Addressing purposefully to the many challenges being posed to us in Jammu & Kashmir and in the North-East of India.
We are of the view that in both these strategically important border regions of the country, misgovernance, neglect and emotional separation from India lie at the root of the problems.
Terrorism and challenges to the state will be met forthrightly; changes in law where warranted will be brought about expeditiously; the approach will be firm   but always fair.
To translate this Manifesto into reality, to fulfil our destined role of leading India into the next millennium, the Bharatiya Janata Party seeks the support and cooperation of all our citizens.
Launching a major nationwide drive to identify influx of illicit arms and their possession.
Proliferation of small arms affects directly the law and order in the country as also the security of the nation.
We recognise that narcotics smuggling and narco-terrorism are linked.
The country must be rid of both.
The law in this regard will be made more effective and implemented.
Toning up the administration (as enumerated subsequently) and reforming its functioning, accountability and responsibilities.
Rationalising the number, structure, composition and role of paramilitary forces, including recent initiatives like National Security Guard (NSG), Rapid Action Force (RAF) and Special Protection Group (SPG).
We will review the personal security arrangments: We believe that the security of the high dignitaries of the country is the responsibility of the state.
This security, however, should neither be exaggerated nor intrusive.
It should not ever be at the cost of the collective convenience of the citizens of the country.
The BJP will reform this.
An Agenda for Change Constitutional Reforms The BJP believes that Centre-State relations, which have been on a downslide for the past 50 years, need to be improved.
We also believe that reforms are needed for a stronger Union and equal rights for all citizens.
The BJP will implement the main recommendations of the Sarkaria Commission, such as: (a) Restoring the balance of resources in favour of the States; (b) Ending the misuse of Art 356 to dismiss state governments and dissolve state assemblies.
We will   2 the possibility of making it mandatory for the Union Government to seek Parliament’s approval by two-thirds majority for dismissal of state governments and, (c) Consulting state governments before appointing Governors.
We promise to carve out Uttaranchal, Vananchal, Vidarbha and Chhattisgarh and give them full statehood.
We will further consider setting up a commission to examine the formation of smaller states.
Delhi will be given full statehood.
The BJP will provide Jammu, Kashmir and Ladakh in J&K state with regional development councils.
We will abrogate Article 370 of the Constitution, which puts Jammu & Kashmir on a separate and separatist pedestal, for the state’s full and final integration with the Union.
We will set up an inter-state council under Article 263 of the Constitution to settle all inter-State and Centre-state disputes to avoid ad hoc responses to issues like that of Cauvery waters.
The BJP is committed to Article 44 of the Constitution.
We will adopt a Uniform Civil Code which will be applicable to every community and foster a common Bharatiya identity, apart from ensuring gender equality.
Regressive personal laws will cease to have legal validity.
The manner of appointment of constitutional functionaries will be reviewed.
We will maintain a national register of citizens and introduce a multipurpose identity card.
Electoral Reforms The BJP carries a conviction that amongst the many causes that have brought the state of our polity to its present plight, a major factor is faulty elections.
We will, therefore, immediately on assuming office, implement various electoral reforms.
For free, fair and fearless elections, the BJP will: Update and adopt the Goswami Committee report; Grant statutory status to the Code of Conduct drawn up   by the Election Commission and give it teeth; Introduce a scheme of state-funding of candidates to all legislatures; Provide suitable incentives for open, official corporate funding to all recognised political parties; Undertake fresh delimitation of Lok Sabha and Assembly constituencies on the basis of the 1991 census; Make it mandatory for political parties to submit audited accounts for public scrutiny annually; Examine the feasibility of introducing the list system; Expedite the process of issuing identity cards to all voters and make it a mandatory requirement for voting; Scrutinise all voters’ lists to ensure that no legitimate voter is excluded; Take steps to curb expenditure on elections by imposing a ban on advertisements, cutouts, etc; Introduce electronic voting machines to hasten the process of counting; Examine the possibility of simultaneous elections to the Parliament, State Assemblies and Panchayats; Ensure speedy and exemplary punishment for those who indulge in booth-capturing; Officials found guilty of involvement in poll rigging will be given exemplary punishment; Amend the anti-defection law whereby a member of any Legislature who changes parties will lose his or her membership of the House; and, Prevent the misuse of Doordarshan and A.I.R.
by the ruling party.
Corruption & Its Cure The BJP treats this affliction as the single greatest wrong that the Congress misrule of the past 50 years has brought about on our land.
The corruption that now corrodes our country is of the spirit, it is moral, and it is also financial.
The challenge thus to governance is principally of setting an example — of impeccable probity and unimpeachable accountability of all public men and women.
This must not cover simply the elected representatives   2 the people but also the executive, the police and, indeed, even the judiciary, where the touch of corruption can easily be felt.
The BJP will address itself to this challenge and task, by adopting measures that are mentioned here.
We do not claim that this is either the ultimate blueprint for the reduction of corruption or the last word on it.
It is an expression of our commitment; a first step to setting right a very great wrong of many years’ malignancy; a beginning and that, too, with ourselves.
For a clean public life in which morality and ethics find due recognition, the BJP will: Make it obligatory on every elected representative to make, public his entire income and wealth within 90 days of election; Introduce extensive regulations and requirements upon those who hold public office so that no conflict of interest is ever permitted to influence a proper discharge of their duties; Appoint a Lok Pal to entertain complaints of corruption against anybody holding public office, including the Prime Minister; Take measures to modify and reform the methodology of government approval for contracts, schemes and large money value agreements so as to make them more transparent.
The powers of patronage, the right to say ‘Yes’ or ‘No’ to simple daily requirements of the citizens will be reduced drastically.
A government that intrudes the least, we hold, governs the best.
We will endeavour to combine this with open and transparent governance; Expeditiously deal with cases of corruption unresolved and in which no action has been taken in the past 10 years; Take steps to ensure that investigative and intelligence agencies like RAW, IB and CBI are not used to subserve the political designs of the ruling party.
Judicial Reforms For speedy, fair and inexpensive justice, the BJP will: Appoint special judges to clear the huge arrears at all levels of the judiciary; Fill the vacancies in the High Courts and the Supreme   Court without any further delay; Legislate to the effect that courts do not give unending adjournments and complete cases within one year.
Constantly review the salaries and pension benefits of all judges so as to attract the best legal talent to the judiciary; Expand and strengthen the existing legal aid facilities for economically weaker sections of the society; and, Set up a National Judicial Commission which will be responsible for making judicial appointments in the High Courts and the Supreme Court.
Panchayati Raj For better local self-governance at the village-level, the BJP will: In the light of recent experience, make changes in the Constitution 73rd and 74th amendments to further strengthen the Panchayati Raj system; and, Endeavour to make the panchayats financially self-sufficient.
Administrative Reforms For a caring, just and accountable administration, to provide high quality services the citizens value and for a new paradigm in public administration, the BJP will: Make the district administration accountable for any outbreak of violence; institute a time-bound inquiry; publish the findings; punish the guilty; and, compensate the victims; Update and implement the National Police Commission report in a time-bound manner; Ask each Ministry/Department to set clear performance standards, including cost consciousness, in quantifiable terms and monitor the adherence to these standards; Introduce a scheme of fixed minimum tenure for some identified posts at higher ranks, e.g.
Chief Secretaries, Secretaries to Government, DGPs, etc; Disfavour extensions to bureaucrats and police officers; Institute an annual Sardar Patel award for the best three district officers, as a beginning; Ensure uniform housing and other related facilities for   2 in the same grade and in the same station.
The system of allotment of houses will be made transparent; Introduce a system of allowing lateral entry of personnel from the private sector, NGOs, educational/research institutes into government; Identify areas from which government must withdraw so that departments can be wound up in a phased manner; Strengthen the department of administrative reforms at the Centre and in the States; and, Give the citizens what is their due.
A huge divide today separates the citizen, the society and the state.
This is principally on account of the state not treating the rights of the citizens as sacrosanct; not fulfilling its obligations towards the citizens sincerely; and, not providing to the citizens the services that are its bounden duty.
The BJP will, therefore, identify such areas as warrant immediate correction, as they affect the daily life of the ordinary citizen, and implement reforms in them within a given timeframe.
Shri Ram Mandir at Ayodhya The BJP is committed to the concept of one nation, one people, one culture — our nationalist vision is not merely bound by the geographical or political identity of India, but defined by our ancient cultural heritage.
From this belief flows our faith in ‘Cultural Nationalism’ which is the core of Hindutva.
That, we believe, is the identity of our ancient nation — Bharatvarsha.
Hindutva is a unifying principle which alone can preserve the unity and integrity of our nation.
It is a collective endeavour to protect and re-energise the soul of India, to take us into the next millennium as a strong and prosperous nation.
Hindutva is also the antidote to the shameful efforts of any section to benefit at the expense of others.
We hold that only by recognising the limitless strength of cultural nationalism, can the nation be moulded.
When the BJP joined the movement for the construction of the Shri Ram Mandir at Ayodhya, it was to strengthen just these foundations.
On coming to power, the BJP Government will facilitate the   construction of a magnificent Shri Ram Mandir at Janmasthan in Ayodhya which will be a tribute to Bharat Mata.
This dream moves millions of people in our land; the concept of Rama lies at the core of their consciousness.
   2 Economy, Action And Direction Economic Growth and Employment Through Swadeshi Four decades of Congress misrule have ruined the economic creativity of our country; these decades failed to place the country on a sound economic footing, befitting India’s stature as the largest democracy in the world.
The experiments of the Congress, with vastly divergent models, have brought the country, from time to time, to the brink of crisis.
The passive victim of all these experiments has been the long suffering citizen of our country; even as under- nourishment, malnutrition, illiteracy and deprivation afflict a large percentage of them; even as the quality of life gets fractured between India and Bharat.
We commit ourselves to bringing certainty in economic policy.
The Bharatiya Janata Party is proud of India’s heritage and has an abiding faith in the creative genius of every Indian.
We are committed to an economy that enables India to achieve its destiny in the forefront of the nations of the world.
In 1991, the present government claimed that it inherited an economy which had a slender foreign exchange reserves.
Accepting IMF conditionalities, it initiated a programme of deregulation of industry, trade and exchange rate policies, a radically different approach to foreign investment.
The consequential foreign exchange reserves that it will be leaving, as a legacy to the successor government, are, however, fragile, being composed mainly of quick-sand components of foreign institutional investments and FCNR deposits.
Foreign direct investment (FDI) is only a minor component of them.
An enormous $7 billion becomes ripe for debt servicing in 1996-97 itself.
In its zeal to contain fiscal deficits task in which it failed, the fiscal deficit continuing around 7% of GDP—it   pruned developmental expenditure beyond acceptable limits, in consequence constraining growth.
Despite the proclaimed deregulation, over the past five years, all earlier structures and institutions of the License Quota-Permit Raj remain intact.
Social infrastructure has been neglected and the lot of the poor and deprived has further deteriorated.
The country’s defence requirements were also neglected, thereby putting the nation’s security in jeopardy.
The neglect of infrastructure by this government has left a legacy of a fractured physical infrastructure—roads, railways, post, power, telecom—are grinding to near immobility, in the process constraining growth elsewhere in the economy.
In its methodology for containing the budget through limits on monetisation of the deficit, this government has compulsorily resorted to heavy borrowings, which in turn, has resulted in liquidity to the rest of the economy and a heating up of the interest rates.
Our domestic industry, starved of liquidity, is in danger of slipping into recession.
In totality, this government will leave an economy more fragile and shattered than what it inherited in 1991.
The challenges thus, to us in our bid at governance, are formidable.
Our Economic Thought In outlining our strategy, we recognise that the post Cold War world has adopted the market place for fast economic growth.
However, our thought is defined by the following: (i) Market may ensure growth, but it cannot ensure redistribute equity and justice.
The state continues to have a role to play; (ii) The poor and deprived have, therefore, to be helped by the state to cross the poverty line and to attain a sustainable minimum quality of life; (iii) On the economic front, the old order, based on comparative advantage of labour or resources, is giving way to a new order built on the basis of human resources, skills and technology.
A proper policy can make it India’s strength; and (iv) A society such as ours has to innovate its own strategy, to adapt itself to the high-tech challenges of a supposedly   2 world, without the attendant social stresses, economic instability and the abandonment either of its identity or of its own socio-cultural ethos.
This is the essence of our Swadeshi approach: A self-reliant India, asserting its national economic interests, not as autarchy, but as a pre-requisite to meeting the challenge of globalisation; of preserving our identity without compromising our sovereignty or self respect.
We reject unbridled consumerism and believe in adherence to sustainable consumption and growth.
Foreign investment will be required and encouraged for world class technology.
But when foreign savings have to supplement and assist the economy in circumstances where domestic savings are inadequate, we compromise with the nation’s long term interests.
While many countries which started late but arrived much earlier than India, managed their growth on savings levels around 35-40% of GDP, the Indian domestic savings rate has steadily declined to a low level of 20% of GDP during Congress rule.
This is grossly inadequate for even the current level of investment, let alone the levels required for a faster growth of the economy.
Not only have private savings declined, more worrisomely, governmental savings are now virtually nil.
We recognise two immediate priorities—first, providing the physical and economic infrastructure that is appropriate for the stipulated growth in our GDP; second, providing the required social infrastructure for a minimum sustainable quality of life.
To attain these and yet contain fiscal deficit requires a different approach.
The BJP will work towards pruning non-developmental expenditure; minimise the commercial activities of government; severely cutting back on bureaucracy; shedding the structures of controls and regulation; and re-equipping itself for its new role of providing a framework for free market operations for growth, accentuating programmes for poverty eradication and social Infrastructure.
Fiscal Reform and Taxation We believe that taxation alone cannot be the base for revenue.
A stable and fast growth is possible only through a high order of   investment matched by an appropriate level of domestic savings.
The present government has done a great disservice by encouraging avoidable consumerism and diverting the depleted savings into speculative rather than safe and productive channels.
• We will structure our fiscal reforms so that savings and contracted savings are augmented to levels that will take care of a higher order of investment needed for faster growth; • In taxation, we will ensure that not only levels and rates of taxation are such that growth is not constrained, but that the burden-sharing of taxes is equitably distributed among all affluent sections of society.
We will mitigate the undue rigours of indirect taxes—today indirect taxes constitute 71 % of tax revenue—so that productivity and growth are not hampered.
We will devise a suitably structured valued added tax (VAT) so as to ensure better burden-sharing among ‘goods and services’ that contribute to value addition.
• In tariffs we will ensure that the domestic sector gets a level playing field, and does not become uncompetitive; • We will also strive to lighten the debt burden on the nation.
This in turn will contribute to interest rate stabilisation; • We will not hike Excise Duties on items of mass consumption; • We will examine the aspect of sales tax reform and equalisation.
• We will ensure operational autonomy of the RBI; • We will adopt firm measures to prevent the generation of black money; • We will rationalise and simplify the present tax structure and raise the Income Tax exemption limit to ₹ 60,000; • We will provide weighted deductions taking number of dependents on earning member; • We will exempt all investments in approved organisations, private OR public, from the levy of Wealth Tax.
; • We will give tax reliefs to employment-oriented industries in non-municipal areas; • We will ensure minimum contribution to government   2 by all profit-earning business units.
The concept of ‘zero business units’ will be done away with; • We will give special tax concessions to writers, artists, academics and others engaged in intellectual and cultural pursuits.
Price Stability and Consumer Protection It is our firm belief that the price level can be controlled only through maximisation of production and a minimisation of costs of production.
This is to be achieved through technology upgradation, economics of scale and free competition.
Towards this end, the BJP will: • Ensure an efficient, low-cost, corruption-free PDS, so that there is a regular, assured, timely and adequate supply of commodities to the consumers in the rural, tribal, remote and backward areas of our country; • Supply better quality foodgrains through the PDS by enhancing the norms for quality standards rather than easing them as has been done by the Congress; • Make pulses, cooking oil and soap also available through PDS, in addition to food-grains, sugar and kerosene; • Improve the Consumer Protection Act of 1986, and ensure its application; and, • Encourage consumer movements.
Black Money and Corruption Starting from its Jana Sangh days, the BJP has been waging a relentless battle against the twin evils of corruption and black money.
We are committed to rooting out corruption, thus also the malignancy of black money.
• We will encourage capital creation through funds from such a parallel economy, retaining the right of government to tax the revenue flows from such created capital.
• The BJP will open up sectors such as social forestry, wasteland development and housing for rural and urban poor.
• We will also review the rationale of the Urban Land Ceiling Act, in this context.
Infrastructure We hold that power, telecommunications, transport (surface, sea and air) constitute the basic building blocks of our development.
With hardly 50% of the roads surfaced, about 40% of the traffic volume is handled by the National Highway System (NHS) which constitutes hardly 2% of the road network.
Our Railway network has grown only by 16% over five decades.
The ports have become the greatest constraint on our world trade.
The dimensions of the power and telecommunications situation cripple development.
• We need to actively develop a National Waterways network; • To meet our minimum needs, a staggering 10,000 MW have to be added annually for the next 15 years.
Irrigation needs press upon our resources.
All these call for large investments.
• We propose, therefore, to lay the foundations of a strong bond market in the country which can take care of the massive financial requirements.
We invite foreign capital in the field of infrastructure.
• We will initate a framework which will facilitate quick redressal of the acute infrastructure crisis based on international co-operation and partnership.
• We will strive to confine the role of the state to that of a facilitator, withdrawing in favour of suitably structured independent regulatory authorities.
Public Sector At present the policy relating to public sector is in disarray.
• The BJP believes in confining the public sector only to sensitive areas where the nation’s security is involved and to areas where the presence of public sector is necessary for providing a moderating or counter-poising role to the ill effects, if any, of an unchecked private sector.
• Public sector presence will continue in areas furthering social objectives.
• The remaining public sector that would continue will be managed with the least interference by government.
In the case of disinvestment from ailing, non-profitable or sick   2 sector undertakings, the BJP will constitute a Disinvestment Commission for taking care of disinvestment from the country’s public sector.
• While disinvesting, care will be taken so that the workers’ interests are not harmed.
• The National Renewal Fund will be realigned to take care of the constant requirements of retraining and redeployment of workers that may be necessary in a fast growing economy.
• Sales proceeds from PSU disinvestment will be utilised only on capital expenditure.
Foreign Trade and Capital Foreign Trade Policy has in the past degenerated into one of providing palliatives.
It has now become necessary to strengthen the interface between industry and trade.
• We will select core industries and a system of destinations and initiate an integrated production for export planning with selective intervention so that this sector, so vital to the economy, acquires dynamism.
• We will also strive to forge such alliances with or memberships of regional trading blocs that will give further impetus to our exports.
The BJP welcomes foreign investment, because we hold that it supplies knowledge, technology and know-how and sharpens the quality and competitive edge of our economy.
• We will, however, strive to minimise our dependence on foreign savings.
• We will prioritise foreign investment in sectors that will promote exports in preference to sectors that will cater solely or exclusively to the domestic market.
• Keeping in view that dissemination of world class technology is an objective of foreign investment, we will give preference to overseas investors who have domestic partners.
• We will encourage foreign investment in infrastructure, areas of high technology and R & D within India.
• As for MNCs in consumer non-durables, we do not consider   them as areas of priority.
Industrial Policy Industry in India has to be enabled to become more productive, more innovative.
Only then will it fulfil its main goal: Enhance the national wealth, provide greater employment in ever increasing numbers and thus assist the growth of other sectors, including agriculture.
For, we ecognise this inseperable interdependence.
Our exports must compete with the best in the world, add to our resources and fiscal health, and thus enable India to achieve the status that we believe is its destiny.
The BJP assures all about creating a healthy investment and industrial environment.
The BJP believes in the continued role and relevance of the small-scale sector.
This important segment of our national economy, which has been entirely ignored by the Congress and whose very existence is threatened by the present policy of economic liberalisation, will receive all encouragement and help from a BJP Government.
The following principles will guide the industrial policy of the BJP: A.
Economic Sovereignty The party regards the preservation of the nation’s economic interests as a component of our external economic relations.
Globalisation, to us, is not a synonym for the obliteration of national economic interests.
Indeed, in the ensuing global competition we need to be constantly mindful of preserving them.
B. Modernisation BJP stands for a mode 24 and progressive India, open to new ideas, new technology and fresh capital.
A modern India to the BJP is not a westernised India; a pale copy of the western economic models.
C. Decentralisation We stand for a decentralised economic order.
The BJP stands for political as well as economic democracy.
The role of the government   2 change from the restrictive to the supportive and encouraging.
The BJP will, therefore: • Debureaucratise industrial approvals and cut down the plethora of restrictive controls.
Industrial Development and Regulations Act will be replaced by Industrial Development Act; • Encourage research and development as part of the process of industrial growth and over-all modernisation; • Hazardous industries will be permitted only in specified areas.
Separate industrial satellites will be set up exclusively for such units; • Small-scale sector will be given all importance and encouragement.
We will establish agencies to help the small-scale sector in purchasing, marketing and selling their products; and, • Ensure a healthy capital market.
   Our Concept Of Employment And Labour’s Role Creating Jobs and Opportunities Apart from employment which will be created in the normal course by the growth of the economy, special employment schemes will be undertaken by the Bharatiya Janata Party to eradicate unemployment.
The BJP proposes to introduce a scheme of voluntary National Service to undertake the task of national reconstruction and also in order to instill a sense of discipline and nationalism among the youth of the country.
This service will aim at reclaiming wasteland for commercial use—for instance, after reclaiming the waste land, it will be used for horticulture, social forestry or any other purpose that will provide the youth involved in the reclamation with continued income.
Similarly, the National Service will be used for river management schemes.
Apart from this, the BJP proposes to: Increase employment opportunities in all sectors of the organised economy; Introduce policies and programmes to: (i) Develop agriculture, particularly in regions which are at present less developed and backward.
(ii) Promote industrial growth with special attention to village, cottage and small-scale sectors.
Special emphasis will be laid on agro-industry.
(iii) Undertake large-scale housing activity that will generate both jobs and additional shelter in both rural and urban areas.
2 (iv) Provide transport facilities with special emphasis in improving availability of transport in rural areas.
(v) Augment employment opportunities in villages through Schemes like Antyodaya, Gokul Gram, Gopal Gram, Saraswati Yojana as already being implemented by BJP governments in Rajasthan and Gujarat.
(vi) Provide and improve infrastructure, especially in rural areas, such as roads, small dams and water conservation projects.
(vii) Promote vocational training.
Labour BJP believes in healthy trade unionism.
It will: Rationalise and simplify Labour Laws; Recognise unions on the basis of secret ballot and have provisions for comprehensive bargaining; Introduce worker participation from the shop floor to the board room in all public sector projects, public limited companies and foreign companies operating in India; Protect workers against inflation; Evolve an effective mechanism and ensure better implementation of laws to protect labour from occupational health hazards arising from industries like asbestos, cement, slate, mica, chemicals, textiles, etc.
The workers will have the right to be informed about the possible health hazards they could be exposed to on the shop floor; and, Not allow an exit policy without fulfilling corresponding obligations towards labour.
Government Employees BJP will set up a permanent Employees Welfare Board with a view to resolving the long-standing problems related to: Time scale promotion; Revision of pay scales and award of bonus; Implementation of awards; Housing; and, Social welfare measures and travel concession for retired  personnel.
Our Scientific Talent, Our Technology Harnessing Nature For Human Welfare The BJP believes that science and technology must play its due role in transforming India into a prosperous and strong country.
The BJP will apply appropriate scientific and technological methods for increasing productivity, eradicating poverty, hunger and disease and providing meaningful employment along with the basic amenities of life.
We believe that science and technology need to be harnessed to improve the lot of the vast section of our population living below the poverty line.
We hold that science is not merely harnessing nature for material wealth but is as well for liberating and enriching the mind and enlarging the human spirit.
The BJP will use science in the service of the poor and develop technology that has a humane face.
Towards this end, we will: Foster a scientific temper among the people; Use science and technology for increasing productivity and generating employment; Implement a vigorous programme of science education and research for improving quality of life; Establish a network of centres for application of science and technology to rural areas, implement ‘lab-to-land’ programmes and develop a strong low-cost agro-Industrial base; Put new life into National Laboratories to develop them as centres of excellence in applied research; Direct these laboratories to evolve appropriate technology for Indian needs; Accelerate the production of scientific literature in regional languages and evolve a national terminology for science   2 technology; Create the right working conditions for our best brains to remain in India and serve the country and not migrate to other lands; Make a systematised effort to bring national laboratories and industry together by setting up ‘Technology Parks’ to be patronised by industry.
This will promote cooperation between industry’s resources and talent in laboratory; Safeguard national interests and our intellectual property rights by encouraging research and development; Undertake research in the field of drugs, micro-biology, bio-technology, bio-fertilisers etc.
; and, Strengthen research in indigenous systems of medicine.
   Our Foreign Policy India, the New Millennium, the World In a post-Cold War world India will be confronted by many new challenges and opportunities.
To meet them, to benefit from the opportunities, mindful of the existing global disequilibrium and in consonance with India’s national interests, our foreign policy in the emerging decades will be based on the human values of peace, equality and cooperation.
The BJP holds that as a departure from the recent past, Indian diplomacy should be conducted in tune with India’s position as a strong power and a major player in the world arena.
A billion people who do not depend upon anyone for feeding or clothing themselves are a power which cannot be ignored.
Our nation needs to regain its lost pride and the BJP alone can undertake this task.
While we believe in partnership with everyone, we reject the very thought of patronage by anybody.
The BJP’s foreign policy will be guided by the following agenda: Sovereign equality amongst nations; a rejection of political or economic hegemonism.
Promotion of Asian solidarity; development of South Asian Regional Cooperation; and, emphasis on improved relations with neighbouring countries.
The BJP does not accept outside interference in this region as being beneficial for it.
Pakistan continues to follow a policy of fomenting insurgency seeking to create instability and unrest in India.
The BJP stands committed to thwarting all these attempts.
In this context, we state: (a) The BJP affirms unequivocally India’s sovereignty over   2 whole of Jammu & Kashmir, including Pakistan occupied Kashmir; and, (b) The BJP declares that it will not accept any interference in our country’s internal affairs.
Our relations with the USA will be based on mutual respect and a congruence of interests.
We note, however, that US policy for this region continues to suffer from lack of vision and that it disregards India’s political and security interests.
India and Russia have a long tradition of good relations and have much to gain from the compatibility of their geopolitical interests in Asia.
The BJP will endeavour to further explore the avenues of bilateral cooperation in this direction.
Our relations with the People’s Republic of China offer an opportunity to now put them on a footing of friendship and cooperation.
For this we need to resolve the border question in a fair and equitable manner.
It cannot, however, be ignored that the People’s Republic of China continues to support Pakistan militarily and otherwise.
The BJP greatly regrets the continuing bloodshed in Sri Lanka, particularly as India all through its history has had warm fraternal ties with all sections of the population in that country.
The BJP is confident that within a united Sri Lanka it should be possible to fulfil the aspirations of the Tamil people.
The BJP pledges to maintain warm and friendly relations with Nepal, with which India has the closest cultural, religious and historical ties.
The BJP will work actively for resolving all outstanding issues.
We welcome the restoration of democracy in Nepal.
The BJP views with great sympathy the struggle for restoration of democracy in Myanmar.
It extends its support to the task of reconciliation and reconstruction in that country with which India has a long border and age-old religious, cultural and historicalties.
The BJP will try to consolidate further the close and friendly ties between India and Bhutan.
In our relations with Bangladesh, illegal immigration into India from that country has proved a major irritant.
This issue has cast its shadow on our bilateral ties and needs to be resolved early.
Millions of sons and daughters of Mother India, settled abroad as Overseas Indians, are considered by the BJP as an asset to the country.
Their emotional attachment to the motherland is still deep.
This must find due expression.
Schemes will be drawn up to attract substantial investments by non-resident Indians.
They will be welcome to set up industrial units and industrial parks, and invest in the infrastructure.
The BJP will examine afresh the issue of dual citizenship.
The BJP will launch a vigorous campaign for a permanent membership for India in the UN Security Council.
The BJP stands committed to peace amongst all nations; prosperity for all the peoples of the world; and, an international role for India that befits this great and ancient nation.
   2 Nation’s Security Protecting Our Country The BJP accords the highest importance to the security of our Nation, our Society and our Citizens.
We charge the present government with imperilling our security, internal and external, as never before.
Our defence expenditure has been cut steadily in real terms during the Narasimha Rao regime.
This has seriously compromised our combat effectiveness.
The present Congress government has been functioning without a full-time Defence Minister for over three years, and this negligence of India’s sword arm has begun to affect the morale of our gallant forces.
The BJP will correct this damaging imbalance.
We will accord due importance to all security related issues — the emerging global realities and regional complexities demand this as the very minimum response from our government.
Internal Security The nature of the state and its relationship with society has a direct bearing on the level of the citizens’ national commitment.
An insensitive and uncaring state erodes the citizens’ allegiance to the nation.
The BJP will restore national commitment to its rightful place by establishing a harmonious relationship between state and society.
We will: Defuse tension in long-festering trouble spots; Ensure protection of life and property from insurgents and foreign mercenaries; Provide our security apparatus with a free hand to deal with terrorism; Revitalise and reinforce law and order machinery;   Institute police reforms and upgrade the capability of the force; and, Legislate tough deterrent laws against terrorist and disruptive activities (TADA was repealed to pander to vote bank politics) while safeguarding democratic rights.
Jammu & Kashmir The absence of political far-sightedness and clarity of national objectives has resulted in our nation continuing to have to pay a price even 50 years after Jammu & Kashmir became a part of the Republic.
The failure of successive Congress Governments to formulate a Jammu & Kashmir policy that takes into account the State’s internal problems has led to a situation where this strategic border state has emerged as the principal challenge to Indian nationhood.
The BJP realises the magnitude of the challenge and dedicates itself to the task of not only solving the internal problems of the state but also reclaiming the portion of our territory which has been illegally held by Pakistan for nearly five decades.
Without repeating the mistakes of yesteryears and merely reacting to Pakistan’s moves, we will: Immediately strengthen the civil administration by inducting able and honest administrators; Provide a free hand to our security forces to deal with the menace of terrorism and induction of men and arms from Pakistan, while ensuring that democratic rights are not violated; Cleanse the local police and administration of malcontents who have aligned themselves with the terrorists or are pro-Pakistan; Declare Doda a disturbed area and invoke the Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act to prevent this district from becoming a haven for mercenaries and terrorists; Launch a massive welfare programme for all regions of the state and ensure that there is no seepage; Hold free and fair elections in the state after terrorism has been brought under control and every person, including the Pandits who have been forced out of the Valley, is provided with an opportunity to participate in the polls;   2 .
Rehabilitate all persons displaced from terrorism-afflicted areas of Jammu & Kashmir; and, Set up regional councils for Kashmir, Jammu and Ladakh.
North-East The north-eastern states of our country continue to suffer from the violence perpetrated by insurgency and ethnic strife.
Poor governance, a callous administration, seepage of development funds, and Congress’ politics of manipulation have contributed to the alienation of the people and the growth of insurgency.
In Assam, ULFA and Bodo militants have begun to strike with regularity; in Nagaland and Manipur the NSCN continues with its depredation; and, in Tripura, militant tribal outfits have once again reared their ugly heads.
The tide of illegal immigration from Bangladesh has only worsened the situation.
The BJP will address itself to the problems of our north-eastern States and institute a grievance redressal system monitored from Delhi.
It will also take the following steps to restore the rule of law in the troubled States: Check the inflow of foreign arms and terrorists from training camps across the border; Strengthen the security apparatus and intelligence network; Provide all citizens with identity cards on a priority basis; Check the narcotics trade and attendant ills in the region; and, Plan and execute an integrated and accelerated economic development programme.
Himalayas Over the past five decades, our Himalayan bastions have been strategically pierced.
Despite that, the attitude of successive Congress governments has remained unchanged.
Strategically, the government has failed to restore a balance there, leave alone regain the initiative.
In the process, we have also lost large national territories to the People’s Republic of China, thus demonstrating an absence of strategic thought about our Himalayan bastions.
The BJP will evolve a security policy for the Himalayas so that India’s national interests are fully safeguarded.
External Security We believe that pro-active diplomacy, especially defence diplomacy, coupled with adequate preparedness of our armed forces, is the key to securing our frontiers against aggression.
This requires both strategy and tactics.
The BJP will: Set up a National Security Council; Re-evaluate the country’s nuclear policy and exercise the option to induct nuclear weapons; Though the BJP stands committed to a nuclear-free world, we cannot accept a world of nuclear apartheid.
(i) The BJP will thus not agree to the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty (CTBT) unless there is a simultaneous agreement for a time-bound global elimination of nuclear weapons in their entirety.
(ii) The BJP will not agree to the Fissile Material Control Regime(FMCR).
(iii) The BJP will not agree to the Missile Technology Control Regime (MTCR).
Expedite the serial production of Prithvi and make Agni I operational for the deployment of these missiles.
In addition, hasten the development of Agni II; Immediately upgrade conventional weapons and weapons systems of the armed forces; Strengthen the intelligence-gathering system, inclusive of all intelligence agencies, initiate a Centre-State initiative on intelligence gathering and sharing, step up air surveillance of our territory, and acquire state-of-the-art electronic equipment; Strengthen the Air Force fleet with new generation aircraft; Make a qualitative and quantitative improvement in our naval capabilities; Invest in R&D in areas of defence and missile technology so that we become increasingly self-reliant; Peg defence-related expenditure to real requirements; and, Re-examine the role, structure and composition of the numerous para-military forces and reorganise and reform them.
2 Jawan The BJP is rightly proud of our valiant soldiers who have dedicated their lives to defend our nation from external aggressors and internal subversives.
We believe it is our duty to take care of our serving jawans and look after those who have retired from service, as well as their families.
To fulfil this duty, the BJP will adopt the following programmes and policies: The terms of service, including pay and allowance, housing, education for children and pension, of all ranks will be improved so as to attract men and women of high calibre.
The present shortage of men and officers does not have to be met by lowering standards of entry; Widows and dependents of jawans who die in action will receive higher benefits and compensation; Pension disparities will be solved and anomalies sorted out expeditiously; Hospitals for veterans will be set up throughout the country so that no ex-serviceman, irrespective of his rank, is denied medical care; Ex-servicemen’s welfare will be included in the concurrent list; The services of our retired soldiers will be used to the maximum extent possible, especially in insurgency- affected areas.
Wherever there is a stipulated percentage for employing ex-servicemen, it will be fulfilled; Necessary changes will be made in agricultural and urban tenancy laws to secure the proprietary rights of servicemen; and, District Sainik Boards will be strengthened.
Illegal Immigration: Demographic Invasion — A Threat to Our Security We believe that illegal immigration from our neighbouring countries, especially Bangladesh, has a direct impact on our nation’s security and has an unsettling effect on our demography.
Given the sheer dimension of numbers there are as many as 1.7 crore illegal immigrants, the bulk of them Bangladeshis, living in various parts of the country.
Illegal immigration is not only transforming   the geography, but the sociology, the economy, indeed even the politics of this country.
India is facing an explosive issue.
If our demographic balance is allowed to be disturbed by inept policies and political considerations, various demographic entities are bound to come in conflict, thus adversely affecting our security environment.
The invasion of illegal immigrants from Bangladesh has led to an alarming growth in a section of the population in our North-East, in Assam, in West Bengal, parts of Bihar and Delhi.
In certain areas, a section of the population has grown by almost 100 per cent.
The BJP proposes to: Complete barbed wire fencing along the India-Bangladesh border, beginning with the plains, to prevent infiltration; Detect illegal immigrants, delete their names from voters’ lists and arrange for their deportation without any further delay; Declare all property deals between Indians and illegal immigrants as null and void; Amend immigration rules and other laws to impose stringent checks on illegal entry into India; and, Expedite the issuance of identity cards to all citizens of the country.
   2 Villages, Our Farmers, Our Poor Towards a Revitalised Rural Economy Our country has an abundance of natural resources fertile lands, flowing rivers, rich mineral deposits and verdant forests.
More than anything else, we have a large army of farmers that shoulders the onerous task of feeding our people.
But the wrong priorities of the last 50 years of Congress misrule and the lopsided model of development pursued by policymakers have impoverished vast sections of our farmers, rendering agriculture economically non- viable.
Worse, bulk of the monies earmarked for infrastructural development, health, education and civic amenities has been canalised to the urban areas despite the fact that the majority of the population lives in villages.
Less than a quarter of the country’s population, 23.31 per cent, lives in urban areas, compared to the overwhelming 76.69 per cent which lives in villages.
As many as 71.4 per cent of our people are economically dependent on agriculture: This sector of our economy, therefore, generates the highest employment as well as provides the biggest market.
Yet, this sector continues to be neglected by Congress policy-makers.
The Bharatiya Janata Party believes that India cannot emerge as a powerful nation until the lot of our farmers is improved, adequate attention paid to the agricultural sector, an all-out war launched against poverty, and investments are made in agro-industry as well as small-scale and cottage industry catering to the requirements of our villages.
Our country’s progress is linked to the well-being of our villages, our farmers and our poor.
Congress’ Policy: Not to Have a Policy on Agriculture In the absence of any well thought out agricultural policy focussing on rural development and reconstruction, agriculture is fast becoming a losing proposition for our farmers.
While fixing agricultural prices, successive Congress governments have not taken into account the expenses incurred by our farmers on seeds, fertiliser, power, water, pesticides, machinery and labour.
No effort has ever been made to bring about parity in the prices of industrial and agricultural produce.
As a result, our farmers are forced to sell the fruit of their labour at low prices even while they have to pay ever-increasing prices for the necessary inputs.
Not surprisingly, this has contributed to the impoverishment and indebtedness of our farmers, pushing vast sections of them dangerously close to or even below the Poverty Line.
According to the Planning Commission’s own estimates, almost 42 per cent of our rural population lives below the Poverty Line.
No less alarming is the fact that the number of our villagers dependent on per acre of land has been steadily increasing, compared to other countries where this dependency has dramatically decreased with governments investing in agro-industry which offers alternative sources of employment.
No effort has been made to set up an adequate number of small-scale and cottage industries in our rural areas to absorb idle hands.
This has also contributed in no small measure to the impoverishment of our farmers.
In 1950-51, the ratio of the disparity between the per capita income in rural and urban areas was 1:2; in 1995-96 it stood at 1:4.
Similarly, while per family income has risen by 52 per cent in urban areas since 1952, it has increased by a mere 7.8 per cent in rural areas.
Ironically, these neglected villages form a vast market and from this market, as much as Rs 48,000 crores flow to our urban areas every year.
By killing our villages, we will be destroying this market.
Conversely, by developing our villages, we will be strengthening this market, which in turn will benefit our urban areas.
In other words, urban India cannot survive without rural India.
But this simple truth has been ignored for the last 50 years.
Today, three out of every four Indians live in villages, condemned to a life of exploitation and increasing social, political and economic marginalisation.
2 ’s Agenda For Our Farmers, Our Poor We pledge to reverse this trend of social, political and economic marginalisation of our rural population and empower our farmers.
We are committed to restoring agriculture to its rightful place and thus steering our people into an era of prosperity and social equality by the opening decade of the new century.
No country can be great if its people remain poor.
Our first task will be to wipe out the dark curse of poverty.
We will allocate greater resources for effective poverty alleviation programmes; we will invest in agriculture and small-scale industry; we will build from the bottom up, for that is the only way we can build an enduring edifice of development.
To develop rural India, the BJP will: Allocate 60 per cent of plan funds for agricultural and rural development; Treat villages as the basic unit of development and provide each village with basic facilities like roads, irrigation, drinking water, education, health and sanitation; Provide shelter to the homeless in our villages; Develop agriculture, enhance production and improve living standards in our villages by (a) Fixing agricultural prices after taking into account all expenses incurred by farmers; (b) Reducing the per acre cost of production; (c) Increasing the average per acre production; (d) Reducing the overall dependence on agriculture; (e) Providing alternative employment to displaced farmers; Give agriculture the same benefits as industry; Set up an Agricultural Costs and Prices Commission in which farmers and agricultural specialists will together comprise two-thirds of the members.
The Commission will be autonomous and its recommendations will be binding; Announce the total cost of inputs, the total expenditure incurred by farmers, and thereafter announce the support prices; Link support prices to the price index; Ensure parity between agricultural and industrial products   in respect of pricing; Conduct extensive research to evolve methods of dryland farming; Give priority to the farmers’ interests while determining the exim policy for agricultural produce; Enforce prompt payment for agricultural produce.
There will be automatic interest addition to payments delayed beyond two weeks; Extend crop and animal insurance to all agricultural produce.
Insurance schemes will also cover natural calamities; Establish a chain of warehouses with facilities for grant of advance payments of up to 80 per cent of the agricultural produce deposited; Encourage the use of fruit juice in the production of all beverages; Allow free movement of foodgrains throughout the country; Free sugar industry from licensing, and production of molasses from all restrictions on production and movement, as well as ensure that farmers receive an adequate share of the total prices; Maintain the subsidy on fertilisers; Improve the Public Distribution System; Establish farmers’ service centres; Give comprehensive documents to farmers which cover land records, ownership and all other relevant papers; Reform land acquisition laws and ensure that agricultural land acquired for any purpose receives prompt and full compensation at market rates; Free bonded labour and rehabilitate them; and, Launch employment guarantee schemes in rural India that will cover the largest possible number of people.
To revive village industry, the BJP will: Establish an extensive chain of tiny and small-scale industrial units; Give the greatest impetus to this sector.
To make agriculture- based sustainable, the BJP will sharpen the edge of agro   2 industries and food-processing; Provide all facilities, including easy access to credit and marketing to rural artisans and craftsmen; Set up a National Artisan Development Bank; Set up special institutes for skill upgradation; and, Give a thrust to wasteland development, social forestry and horticulture.
To provide irrigation facilities, the BJP will: Launch time-bound irrigation projects and complete ongoing projects; Give priority to small and minor irrigation projects; Remove disparities between districts within states; Encourage the use of alternative sources of irrigation through incentives and better water management; Ensure that farmers are made to pay only for the water they consume; and, Draw up a master plan for flood control and harnessing of flood waters for irrigation.
Offer prompt compensation for crops lost in floods.
To provide power for agriculture, the BJP will: Encourage rapid electrification of our villages so that no village is left without power by the turn of the century; Ensure adequate supply of power for agricultural activity; Set up small power stations and sub-stations in rural areas for supplying power exclusively to villages; and, Electricity Boards will be made to pay compensation to farmers if they fail to supply assured quantity of power.
Similarly, farmers will be required to pay their power bill on time, To strengthen the cooperative movement, the BJP will: Free cooperatives from political interference; Prevent the intrusion of vested interests; Simplify rules and regulations governing the functioning of cooperative societies; Make entry in passbooks mandatory for all money deposits;   Only those entirely dependent on agriculture will be allowed to become members of farmers cooperative societies; and, Ensure free and timely elections to cooperative bodies.
To implement land reforms, the BJP will: Enforce the implementation of Land Ceiling Laws in all States; Set up designated courts to expeditiously deal with all land ceiling disputes and monitor enforcement of verdicts; Expedite distribution of ceiling surplus land among landless farmers; Monitor the use of distributed land and prevent its alienation from beneficiaries;.
Reclaim cultivable land lying fallow; Time-bound registration of all lands; and, Decide ownership rights at the level of Gram Panchayats without any delay.
To alleviate poverty, the BJP will: Enhance public outlays for poverty alleviation and social infrastructure; Restructure the PDS, confining it only to the poor and the needy.
Burgeoning food stocks with a vastly reduced off take and a decline in the per capita consumption of cereals from PDS are powerful indicators of poverty rather than the misleading inflation indices.
PDS prices and the regulated intervals of offtake will be suitably adjusted so that the scheme becomes meaningful for fighting hunger and malnutrition.
PDS will also be dovetailed to provide ‘Food for Work’ in employment programmes linked with poverty eradication; Identify poverty through indexation reflecting not only the level of consumption of calories but also the minimal social infrastructure status such as literacy, housing, drinking water, health and sanitation; Implement ‘Antyodaya’ schemes throughout the country because we hold that sustainable employment is at the core   2 poverty eradication.
These Antyodaya schemes will be targeted at the poorest of the poor: Five crore families will be selected for immediate relief; Allocate more resources for food-for-work programmes so that they can be implemented round the year, as well as monitor their implementation; and, Introduce Langar Yojana and Annadan Yojana to ensure that no man, woman or child goes hungry.
To ensure cow protection, the BJP will: Impose a total ban on the slaughter of cows and cow progeny by amending Article 48 of the Constitution to cover bulls and bullocks, and prohibit all trading (state as well as private) in the slaughter of cows and cow progeny; Implement a policy for improved cattle-breeding; and, Provide tax exemption to the income of Goshalas and Pinjrapoles.
The BJP recognises the fact that from times immemorial, cow- protection has remained one of the basics of Indian culture and Indian agriculture, and it is on the patient back of the cow and its progeny that the entire structure of Indian agriculture rests.
Over 70 million animals are employed in farming operations in Indian villages, more than 80% rural transport needs are met by the bullock-cart.
Our livestock is also an effective protection against environmental degradation.
The BJP regretfully observes that millions of cows and cow progeny are slaughtered every year, most of them for export.
   Our Human Wealth Literacy and Health For All The Bharatiya Janata Party is committed to the creation of a Bharat whose citizens will not suffer from the dual affliction of illiteracy and malnutrition.
We believe that the state should invest in developing every citizen’s potential to contribute to the regeneration of our country.
To achieve that, we will stress on health and education, both of which are challenges that have to be met by the first decade of the 21st century.
India has to emerge as a powerful, self-reliant and proud nation.
True development will be possible only when we draw sustenance from our citizens; they are our true wealth.
Education The past five years have witnessed this core area of human resource development being increasingly deprived of state support.
As a result, quality education is fast becoming the preserve of the social and economic elite of the country.
The vast multitudes, who have been victims of inequity, continue to be denied the cherished ideal of literacy.
The BJP will stress on providing equal opportunity of education, literacy and information.
Towards this end, we will: Increase state spending on education progressively to at least six per cent of our Gross National Product; Spend more on primary education and enrol the help of non-government organisations in this area; Provide free education in order to universalise access to primary education; Offer incentives in the form of free text books, nutrition programmes and stipends to check dropout rate so that at   2 80 per cent children, both boys and girls, who enrol complete primary school education; Reduce learning period and introduce self-employment oriented vocational training programmes at high school level; Introduce an anti-cheating law which will be applicable to all States and whose abuse will be prevented through adequate safeguards; Launch community-level adult education programmes to provide functional literacy to at least 90 per cent of our adult illiterates in both villages and the cities; Set up a special monitoring authority to scrutinise the quality of education and remove gender disparity; Ensure autonomy to universities, encourage them to mobilise resources for research and higher education, and provide academic freedom to our scholars, especially in the social sciences; Improve the pay and emoluments of teachers at all levels and remove anomalies in college/university promotion rules; Enrol industry’s help to set up more technical and agro-industrial institutions that will provide affordable education; Abolish the system of capitation fees and monitor the functioning of private engineering and medical institutions; Launch a scheme for low interest bank loans for meritorious students who want to go in for higher education; and, Thwart attempts by foreign universities, colleges and institutes of dubious reputation to open branches in India and prevent the outflow of foreign exchange on studies abroad unless the course is relevant to our needs and requirements.
Health We believe in increasing state investment in health and nutrition programmes because this is the only path to the creation of a productive workforce by the beginning of the next century.
Our goal will be health for all.
Towards this end, we will strive for:   Ending the scourge of malnutrition; Drastically reducing our infant mortality rate and underfive mortality rate by spending more on pre-natal and pos-natal health care programmes; Immunising every child against killer diseases; Providing every panchayat with a free primary health care centre with facilities for mother and child care, as well as access to these centres; Canalising a substantial portion of the health care allocation on preventive rather than curative aspects; Promoting awareness on cleanliness and disease prevention; Re-evaluating existing programmes to tackle sexually transmitted diseases, with special focus on AIDS; Making the screening of blood at blood banks mandatory and provide for punitive punishment for any violation; Holding doctors, para-medical and non-medical staff at government hospitals and health care centres accountable and instituting a mechanism for swift disposal of all complaints; Revising pay and emoluments of staff at Government hospitals and health care centre to attract the best talent; Promoting alternative medical sciences with special emphasis on Ayurveda and Unani systems; Protecting traditional medicinal plants, trees and cures; Preventing drug prices from escalating to a point where they become non-affordable for the masses; Introducing health insurance schemes at a minimal cost to the subscriber; and, Instituting a mechanism to monitor and collate healthrelated information.
   2 Agenda For Women Nari Shakti: Towards Empowerment We hold that ‘Nari Shakti’ is not merely a phrase, it is the enunciation of our approach.
Towards this end, the BJP will empower women, ensure that their dignity and rights are not trampled upon and help develop their full potential.
We are also committed to protecting the rights of the girl child.
The BJP will: End discrimination in any form against women and encourage gender sensitivity.
All national policies will be subjected to gender analysis; Reserve 33 per cent seats in all elected bodies, including State Assemblies and Parliament, to make women real participants in a resurgent India of the 21st century; Actively promote the legal and economic rights of women which must be equal to those of men and not subject to the debilitating clauses of personal laws; Introduce a Uniform Civil Code that will: (i) Give women property rights; (ii) Ensure women’s right to adopt; (iii) Guarantee women equal guardianship rights; (iv) Remove discriminatory clauses in divorce laws; and, (v) Put an end to polygamy; Create conditions in society and workplace to ensure equal opportunities in employment and promotion, and end sexual harassment; Enforce the principle of equal wages for equal work whether in the organised or unorganised sector; Evolve a scheme for part-time jobs for women; Promote a health care system that will focus on the   nonreproductive health needs of women, especially in rural areas; Provide state support for single and working mothers through grants and subsidy, and formulate a forward looking housing policy to help women; Make women partners in the management of community assets and properties; Enrol the help of local self-governments to set up latrines for women in the rural areas; Set up a micro-credit system with the help of a national corpus to which both the Union and State governments, apart from banks, will contribute.
Encourage the setting up of cooperative societies in rural areas to be managed by women and to benefit women entrepreneurs; Introduce skill-based training programmes and employment schemes which are area-specific; Design a special programme to provide women who were denied education with functional literacy; Amend laws that deal with molestation, rape and dowry to provide for in-camera trial, swift justice and tough deterrent punishment as well as rehabilitation of the victims of these crimes; Amend the Prevention of Immoral Traffic Act to make clients as culpable as commercial sex workers; Rehabilitate commercial sex workers and set up a special fund to provide health care and education to their children; Enact a law that will make registration of marriages with foreigners mandatory; Make it compulsory for the mother’s name also to be mentioned in all government and non-government records, starting from a child’s birth certificate to a person’s death certificate.
Set up designated courts in every district for expeditious trial of civil and criminal complaints relating to women; Rapidly induct more women in the police force and appoint them in senior positions as well as set up a ‘Crimes Against Women Cell’ in every police station; Enact a special law to deal with the crime of domestic   2 against women; Promote a social agenda designed to discourage negative influences and end discrimination against the girl child in any form; Ruthlessly punish those who indulge in unethical practices like prenatal sex-determination test and female foeticide and infanticide; Invest in the girl child’s health, nutrition and education, from infancy through adolescence; Universalise primary and secondary education to narrow the gender gap and offer incentives for the girl child’s education in the form of free uniforms and books; Strictly enforce age of consent laws and end child prostitution; and, Have a fresh look at the UN convention for the elimination of discrimination against women (CEDAW) to determine whether the reservations expressed by the Government of India are justified.
   Our Population Policy Towards a Sustainable and Balanced Growth Our people are our primary concern - their basic needs of health, education and employment must precede everything else.
To ensure an equitable disbursement of resources so that the largest number of our people benefit from development policies, we must arrest the country’s runaway population and growth.
An increasing population can only mean a decreasing share of the fruits of development.
Successive Congress Governments have ignored this crucial area of development planning, often for petty political motives.
This has resulted in a steep rise in population and severe demographic imbalances.
The Bharatiya Janata Party believes that children are born — and have the right — to be happy, and not merely for existence.
We will, therefore, put population-related issues, especially family planning, firmly back on the national agenda, and launch a people’s movement against the impending population explosion through persuasive policies.
The BJP proposes to: Act on the reports of the National Development Council and the Swaminathan Committee to formulate a National Population Policy that will stabilise the population growth by the first decade of the new century; Enact a law that will debar those with more than two children from holding elected office, with 1996 as the cutoff year; Provide incentives to those among the economically weaker sections who opt for the ‘two-child’ norm in the form of special facilities for health, education, nutrition and employment opportunities.
At the same time, the BJP will also introduce disincentives like limiting subsidised   2 and maternity benefits to two children with 1996 as the cut-off year.
These disincentives will apply to all sections of society, irrespective of their social, economic or religious status to discourage large, unsustainable families; Ensure universal access to family planning information and quality facilities by involving non-government organisations, and promote awareness among the people, especially women, through counselling and educational programmes Introduce family planning methods and facilities that will allow women greater freedom of choice without imperilling their health; Launch a special campaign for women to seek about negative practices and encourage reproductive health services; Offer a special incentive in the form of a fixed deposit that will mature in 21 years for those couples who have only a girl child under a ‘Dattak Putri Yojana’.
Make family planning an integral part of policies to ensure widest applicability of these incentives and disincentives.
   Our Environment Only One Earth The BJP holds as a firm conviction that our ‘only one Earth’ is the endower of all our wealth and natural resources.
This, however, is not for endless exploitation.
Our environment has to be protected, not only to prevent the sanctity of Mother Earth from being profaned but also because our forests, our rivers and our skies sustain a multitude of lives.
No less important is the crucial role that environment plays in our nation’s security.
Environment must be protected by subscribing to the concept of ‘sustainable development’, a philosophical tenet that is integral to our civilisational and cultural consciousness.
The BJP will: Introduce a National Environment Policy incorporating a healthy balance between development needs and preservation of natural resources.
The interests of and consultation with states will be fully ensured.
To implement the policy, the Ministry of Environment and Forests will be recast as the Ministry for Ecological Security; Implement better management and harnessing of river waters as well as sources of ground water; Control land, air and water pollution by industry and urban centres.
Municipal sewage treatment plants will be made obligatory; Formulate a programme for developing sustainable cities, with special emphasis on waste management and use of natural resources like water; Make environment studies a part of school, college and university curriculum and make environment issues an integral part of the visual media so that our children   2 a caring and protective attitude towards the ecological system that sustains our lives; Protect the traditional and other rights of Vanvasis and Girijans over forest resources and produce; Involve local self-governments at all levels, both in villages and cities, in implementing the National Policy; Provide easy access to information on conservation and sustainable use of natural resources; Ban the import of hazardous chemical wastes for recycling by any industry or for dumping; Minimise the use of non-biodegradable material for packaging by the consumer non-durable products industry; It will the conversion of forests or grazing areas for other purposes; Adopt aforestation policies to be fulfilled within a given timeframe and prevent the degradation of forests by natural or manmade causes.
The cornerstone of the BJP’s forest policy will be a part of the total framework of land management, adoption of a dynamic programme of productive forestry and moving to private investment in forestry from total state management of forests.
A programme will also be drawn up for the conversion of degraded forests, wasteland and marginal land into quality forests; Deny exploitation of offshore resources, especially marine life, by big trawlers; Promote R&D in environment-related studies and eco- technology for application in agriculture, industry and the services sector; Provide incentives to manufacturers of eco-friendly products; Not sanction tourism-related projects that disturb the environment and cause degradation.
   Our Social Philosophy Harmony and Equality through Integral Humanism The Bharatiya Janata Party’s social philosophy, which is the bedrock of its social agenda, is rooted in integral humanism.
It rules out contradictions between society and its various components, as also between society and the individual, or, for that matter, between the family, the basic building brick of our social structure, and the individual.
From this stems the BJP’s commitment to the eradication of social and economic disparities that have prevented India from emerging as a modern, dynamic nation; to the creation of a socially integrated Bharatiya society which can proudly enter the new century.
The BJP will help all socially and economically weak and backward sections of society, through special welfare and other schemes, to reach their full potential, For us, it is a historic task which we are resolved to fulfil.
Equity and Equality The BJP will adhere to through its policies and programmes, to the ideals, principles and goals of equity and equality as enshrined in our country’s Constitution; The BJP will promote a casteless socio-economic order which will effectively provide access to equal opportunities to all citizens, irrespective of their caste, creed, religion or gender; The BJP will ensure that the place of an individual in society will not be determined on the basis of his birth; and The BJP will dismantle practices, customs, beliefs, usages and institutions which are divisive and discriminatory, and which in any manner hurt the dignity of the individual.
2 The BJP condemns unequivocally the practice of untouchability which is not only against the law of the land but runs counter to the very concept of integral humanism.
Not surprisingly, the first brick of the Ram temple at Ayodhya was laid by a member of the Scheduled Castes, Kameshwar Chaupal.
The BJP will endeavour to create an ethos of equality in social and inter-personal relationships.
Weaker Sections The BJP will make the existing institutions and Constitutional safeguards for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes operationally more effective.
The BJP views the provision of special facilities and special opportunities, including reservations, in the Constitution as practical steps to advance the deprived and under- privileged sections of society.
The BJP will continue with the existing policy on reservations till social and economic equity is achieved.
Our Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes The BJP’s goal is to achieve social equality for all Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes through political and economic empowerment.
To achieve this goal, the BJP will: Stringently enforce laws against untouchability; Inquire into all cases of atrocities, publish the findings, punish the guilty and rehabilitate the victims as expeditiously as possible; Lay stress on education, vocational training and skill upgradation; Take prompt action to fill up the backlog in jobs reserved for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes.
The reservations policy will be backed up with a statute; Set up a financial agency on the lines of NABARD to cater to the individual and institutional credit needs of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes; Provide more facilities for greater participation of Scheduled   Castes and Scheduled Tribes in small scale, cottage and rural industries, as well as in trade and commerce; End the pernicious practice of carrying night soil and accelerate the rehabilitation of those engaged in scavenging; Wipe out the evil of bonded and child labour and rehabilitate the victims; Launch a massive housing programme for the homeless in villages; Allot pattas for land, home site and homes in the name of wives/widows/daughters; Take necessary steps to protect tribals from exploitation, especially by contractors, and indebtedness; Amend the existing forest policy to restore to the Vanvasis their rightful share of forest wealth and produce, as well as provide viable marketing facilities; Expedite the processing of the claims of Vanvasis and Girijans for pattas in forest and hill areas; Disallow the diversion of monies from Plan and Tribal SubPlan funds meant for the welfare and development of Vanvasis and Girijans; Prevent land alienation through conversion of tribal lands for industrial and other purposes; Formulate and implement a National Policy for the rehabilitation of families displaced by development projects.
This rehabilitation policy will be multi-dimensional and not merely provide financial compensation or means of livelihood.
Governed by the principle of ‘total rehabilitation’, it will include social, economic, educational, environmental, occupational and cultural aspects.
Encourage the setting up of inter-state regional coordination councils to implement a common welfare programme for tribals living in contiguous areas of neighbouring states.
Erect a befitting memorial in honour of Maharishi Valmiki and Babasaheb Ambedkar in the national Capital.
Our Socially and Educationally Backwards The BJP is committed to providing both social and economic justice to the socially and educationally backward classes (Other Backward Classes) through the instrument of reservations.
At the   3 time, we hold that the path to progress of all sections of our people lies not through social divisions brought about by casteist politics but through social harmony.
The BJP advocates: Continuation of reservations for the Other Backward Classes till they are socially and educationally integrated with the rest of society; A uniform criterion for demarcating the ‘creamy layer’; Flow of reservation benefits in an ascending order so that the most backward sections of the OBCs get them first; Ten per cent reservation on the basis of economic criteria to all economically weaker sections of society, apart from the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes and the Other Backward Classes; and, Special programmes to provide education and vocational training as well as awareness campaigns.
Enabling Our Disabled As many as five crore of our people have been socially, politically and economically marginalised because of their physical and other disabilities.
Successive Congress governments have not only abdicated their responsibility towards these less fortunate of our citizens, but also resisted their empowerment and, therefore, their inclusion in the national mainstream.
The level of official apathy can be gauged from the fact that during the last year of its tenure, the Rao Government allocated Rs 42 crore for the welfare of the disabled, which works out to Rs 8 per person.
The BJP believes that those who have been excluded from playing a participatory role in the nation-building process by being stigmatised as ‘disabled’, should be empowered so that they become productive, proud citizens of our country.
Towards this end, we propose to: Order a special survey to collect data about the number of people who are physically and otherwise disabled and the nature of their disability; Use this data to formulate policies aimed at empowerment rather than merely welfare; Actively campaign to remove social prejudices; Sensitise the bureaucracy to the needs and aspirations of   the disabled people; Provide employment in all suitable categories of government service through a policy of equal opportunity; Give incentives to the private sector to provide disabled people with job opportunities; Offer medical, counselling and rehabilitation facilities at health care centres by increasing budgetary allocation and encouraging state governments to make a matching contribution; and, Ensure that disabled people have access to public utilities and services.
Our Minorities Wherever and whenever the Bharatiya Janata Party has been in power, it has ensured peace and security for all sections of society, irrespective of their religious identity.
The BJP is committed to further strengthen this achievement.
This is in stark contrast to the insecurity faced by minority communities under Congress rule.
We have been steadfastly opposed to appeasement as state policy since it benefits only those sections which profess regressive and retrograde social norms in the guise of protecting their religious beliefs.
The BJP will be guided by its policy of ‘justice for all, appeasement of none’.
A resurgent India will enter the 21st century with the resolve of one nation, one people and one culture.
To achieve this goal, we will: Guarantee all minority communities equal opportunity for economic development; Lay stress on education and vocational training; Provide incentives to those who are self-employed, especially artisans, and those who want to set up their own business enterprise; Launch community programmes to create awareness among women members of minority communities; Ensure equality for all and discrimination against none on grounds of religion in matters of education by amending Article 30; Disband the Minorities Commission and entrust its responsibilities to the National Human Rights Commission;   3 .
Set up special courts for speedy trial of those accused of participating in communal riots; Protect wakf property from being usurped and misused by unscrupulous individuals and organisations and help wakf boards to become self-sustaining bodies so that they do not have to be dependent on government doles; Set up trusts along the line of the Tirupati Temple Trust with official nominees for managing the affairs of dargahs; Ensure that no religious property is misused or usurped; Ban all foreign funds irrespective of the organisation which is the recipient; Make fraudulent conversions, including those done by holding out the promise of economic or social benefits, to punishable offence and introduce a system of registering all conversions; Ban the publication of job advertisements that mention religious identity as a criterion; and, Set up a Commission of Inquiry (similar to the Neogi Commission) to inquire into the activities of foreign missionaries and other organisations that have been receiving foreign funds.
Human Rights The BJP subscribes to the view that human dignity, justice for all and protection of the individual from the tyranny of the state are among the basic tenets of Hindutva.
We are committed to upholding the human, democratic and civil rights of every individual, irrespective of the person’s caste, creed, religion or gender.
But, we will not allow this commitment to be used as a shield by those who commit inhuman atrocities and thus forsake their claim to human rights.
The BJP believes that the state should be fair to all citizens, but firm while dealing with those who militate against civil society.
The BJP will not allow any foreign interference in our country’s internal affairs on the pretext of monitoring human rights violations.
We will: Strengthen the existing National Human Rights Commission through more powers, additional resources and better infrastructural support;   Disband the Minorities Commission, which has only succeeded in feeding separatist sentiments and giving rise to imagined grievances, and entrust its responsibilities to the National Human Rights Commission; Take swift action on the basis of the Commission’s findings and punish the guilty; and, Include the study of human, democratic and civil rights in school curricula.
Displaced Communities: Protecting their Rights Separatist violence and Islamic fundamentalism/terrorism in Jammu and Kashmir has forced more than 300,000 people, including 250,000 Kashmiri Pandits and Punjabi and Dogra Hindus, apart from thousands of Sikhs and even some Muslims, to flee their homes and hearths.
Most of the displaced Pandits are living in abysmal conditions in refugee camps in Jammu and other parts of the country.
Together, they perhaps form the largest internally displaced community in the world, forced to live as refugees in their own motherland, condemned to the mercy of an uncaring and callous Congress government at the Centre and its puppet administration in Jammu and Kashmir.
The Bharatiya Janata Party has mobilised its own resources, men and material to provide succour to these unfortunate victims of government apathy and terrorist violence.
But a lot more needs to be done.
Similarly, thousands of Buddhist Chakmas have fled the Chittagong Hill Tracts in Bangladesh in the face of persecution by Muslim settlers from the plains and the Bangladesh Rifles.
Most of them are at present living in camps in Tripura.
Regardless of the grim future that awaits them back home, the Government of India has shown unnecessary haste in trying to repatriate them—an action that is largely motivated by the petty politics of the Congress.
The BJP is opposed to such forced repatriation in the absence of foolproof security guarantees from the Government of Bangladesh.
The escalating conflict in Sri Lanka between Sinhalese and Tamils is posing a demographic threat to South India with a large number of Tamil refugees beginning to pour into this region.
Such a movement is bound to increase the influence of the LTTE which may, in turn, promote separatist tendencies.
3 must also address ourselves to the concerns of nonresident Indians, especially those who had settled in Hong Kong and now find the future uncertain with Britain handing over this territory to China in 1997.
The BJP proposes: For Kashmiri Pandits As urged by them for social cohesion and cultural preservation, designate the Pandits who have been forced out of Kashmir Valley as an internally displaced community.
Provide adequate financial relief, proper health, housing, education and employment facilities on a priority basis to all displaced families.
Take adequate steps to protect their assets and properties in Kashmir Valley till such time they are able to return home.
Elections in the Valley should be held only after the displaced people are able to return to their homes.
Ensure proper documentation of the displaced Pandits and their assets.
For Chakma refugees Resettle Chakma refugees, the bulk of whom are at present in Tripura, in camps in other contiguous States and provide financial support to their governments so that they do not have to take on the economic burden.
Provide full citizenship to those Chakmas who do not want to return to Bangladesh and whose children were born in India.
Negotiate with Bangladesh for the phased repatriation of those Chakmas who want to return, provided Dhaka guarantees their safety and well-being.
Ensure full security for the Chakmas who live in refugee camps so that they are not harassed or threatened.
Maintain an official register of Chakma refugees and their whereabouts.
For Sri Lankan Tamil refugees House them in refugee camps and monitor their movements.
Prevent their association with local organisations or opening local chapters of Sri Lankan organisations.
Screen the antecedents of the Tamil refugees and disallow asylum to those who have or had links with Tamil terrorists.
Maintain a register of all such refugees.
Repatriate Tamil refugees as soon as the situation is conducive for their safe-being.
For non-resident Indians Provide citizenship to those Hong Kong based Indians who wish to return to their motherland.
Help rehabilitate the returning Hong Kong based Indians.
Examine afresh difficulties in granting dual citizenship to non-resident Indians all over the world.
   3 Identity, Our Culture The Cornerstone of Bharatiyata The Bharatiya Janata Party believes that modernisation does not mean the mechanical imitation of a particular way of life.
It will redefine the concept of development to accommodate the Bharatiya way of living, belief system and values to reach the ultimate goal of Bharatiyata.
We hold that it is necessary to emphasise the linkage of development elements to cultural elements, including local relevance, relevance to geographical and environmental factors, historical traditions, traditional knowledge and skills.
We believe that cultural factors play an important role in energising a nation.
For a resurgent India whose people can proudly flaunt their Bharatiyata, the BJP will: Strengthen and revitalise our cultural institutions; Revive and rejuvenate our positive cultural traditions and values; Include Indian cultural studies and ‘Naitik Siksha’ as part of school curriculum; Establish a Bharatiya Sanskriti Kendra in each district; Declare all places of pilgrimage as national heritage centres; Encourage the study of Sanskrit and strictly enforce the three-language formula in schools; Promote Bharatiya classical music and performing arts through state support; and, Discourage indecent representation of women in advertisements and publications; young minds.
Sex and violence on the silver screen are beginning to gnaw at the moorings of our cultural ethos.
To check this abuse of popular cinema, the BJP will:   Provide film-making the status of industry so that producers can be made accountable for their resources and expenses; Enable film-makers through suitable provisions in law to raise resources from financial institutions to curb the influence of underworld financiers and mafia dons; Analogous to the concept of the Customs ‘green channel’, provide automatic certification for films which do not contain explicit scenes and dialogues of violence and sexproducers and exhibitors of such films will not have to wait in the queue for Censor Board clearance.
Deterrent punishment will be meted out to any producer who abuses the facility; theatre owners who screen such films will also be penalised; Exempt quality films, which will be certified as ‘Q’ from entertainment tax; Encourage viewers to form local Darshak Sanghs—on the lines of consumer organisations—to monitor the quality of films being screened in their area; Set up special theatres at district headquarters and metropolitan cities for screening art and quality films; Appoint 50 per cent women on the Censor Board and Censor Panels; Create a special fund for promoting regional cinema; and, Introduce legislation to ensure minimum wages and retirement benefits for film extras and crew members.
   3 Youth — Our Future In the Vanguard of Change Our youth form the backbone of our vibrant nation and they alone can shape the destiny of this country.
The BJP has a tryst with the youth of India and will harness their creative energy for bringing about social, cultural and political change.
We will aim at transforming Yuva Sankalpa into Yuva Shakti, which, in turn, will be the catalyst for reinvigorating India.
We will inculcate in the country’s youth a sense of pride in our ancient traditions and heritage.
We will instil in them a sense of self-confidence so that they can take their rightful place in the vanguard of change.
Towards this end, through its policies and programmes, the BJP will: Inculcate in the youth a sense of being indebted to society at large and thus prepare them to repay this debt by involving themselves in development programmes and social, cultural and economic activities; Initiate schemes both at Government and Non-Government levels to achieve overall development of young talent; Mobilise the youth to fight regressive and retrograde social practices and customs by making community service a compulsory and integral component of college and university curricula; Set up a National Youth Commission and a Youth Development Bank to design and implement comprehensive employment oriented education policies as well channelise youth power for the purpose of nation-building; Encourage the youth to form ‘Yuva Sena’ and ‘Dharti   Raksha Vahini’ for voluntary community service with the ultimate aim of generating employment; Launch a massive self-enterprise programme to provide employment opportunities to the educated unemployed; Allocate adequate time for youth programmes on Doordarshan; Promote sports through enhanced expenditure on training and rehabilitate sportsmen after they retire from the field; Establish a network of youth hostels throughout the country and provide travel concessions; and, Encourage the study of yoga and promote our cultural heritage by incorporating them in educational curriculum.
   3 Achievements Peace, Progress and Prosperity Wherever and whenever the Bharatiya Janata Party has formed a state government, it has provided the people with a caring, fair, clean and strong administration.
The emphasis of our state governments, be it in Rajasthan, Gujarat, Delhi or Maharashtra (where it shares power with the Shiv Sena), or earlier in Uttar Pradesh, Himachal Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh, has been on ensuring peace, progress and prosperity.
The distinctive feature of our State Governments is their singular achievement in curbing communal and caste conflict.
This is in stark contrast to the situation that prevails in States ruled by the Congress or the Janata Dal where the law and order machinery has virtually collapsed.
A shining example of our achievement on this front is the communal peace that prevails in Maharashtra which till recently was wracked by riots and social conflict.
Similarly, the BJP government in Gujarat has ensured peace.
This has been achieved by cracking down on anti-social and anti-national activity.
The underworld mafia, which flourished under Congress rule, has been brought to book.
The criminal-politician nexus has been broken.
Blackmarketeers, and other criminals, who survived because of Congress patronage, have been put behind bars or are facing prosecution.
The emphasis on enforcing law and order is not without reason.
For, unless there is peace, there cannot be progress and prosperity.
In the field of development, our state governments have focused their attention on the rural sector, because the majority of our people live in the villages.
Not only have effective steps been taken to solve the problems of our farmers, but innovative   schemes have been introduced to generate employment and fight the scourge of poverty.
For instance, the BJP government in Rajasthan has earmarked more than 60 % of Plan allocation for rural areas.
As many as 12.86 lakh farmers and artisans have benefited from the state government’s decision to write off loans amounting to more than Rs 300 crores.
The state government has also written off irrigation loans amounting to Rs 124 crores and introduced more effective means of irrigation.
Tax relief on seeds, a wide range of agricultural produce and equipment has further helped the farmers.
Similarly, the state government has reduced sales tax on fertlizers and made a five-fold increase in agricultural loans.
On the social front, the government has introduced innovative schemes like Gopal Gram Yojana and Saraswati Yojana.
The first scheme not only aims at improving the quality of livestock but also providing people with a sustained income.
Similarly, Saraswati Yojana has a two-fold purpose: Universalising primary education and providing employment to the educated youth of the villages.
Schemes like Shiksha Karmi Project and Guru-Mitra Yojana have also contributed immensely to increasing literacy levels.
Vikalp, a specially designed family planning programme based on incentives and which protects the girl child, has been immensely successful.
The Rajasthan Government has also introduced a new industrial policy to attract both Indian and foreign investors.
The policy has already begun to pay rich dividends.
The government has signed MOUs for the setting up of new power plants.
Soon, the state shall have the largest solar power plant.
In Gujarat, the BJP government has maintained communal harmony in the trouble-prone areas.
Latif, a notorious criminal involved in bootlegging and anti-social activities, has been put behind bars.
His underworld activities in the border areas of Kutch and Saurashtra have come to a grinding halt.
Those involved in adulteration of petrol with solvents, which had become an extremely profitable crime during Congress rule, are facing prosecution.
With law and order restored, the state government has turned its attention on development activity.
Work on the Sardar Sarovar Project is progressing at a remarkable speed.
Bonds worth Rs 300 crores were issued and the amount obtained in seven days from   3 cooperative sector.
Simultaneously, those displaced because of the project have been rehabilitated, On the industrial front, the state government has adopted an investor-friendly policy which has evoked a tremendous response.
An increasing number of Non-Resident Indians have begun to show keen interest in investing in Gujarat.
At the same time, the interests of the agricultural sector are not being ignored.
For instance, 42 % of the power generated in the state is channelised for agricultural use, compared to 34 % for industry.
New power plants are being commissioned to meet future requirements.
In the last three years of Congress rule, not a single MW was added to the installed capacity.
On the social front, the state government has reduced bus fares by 20%, a move which has brought tremendous relief to millions of people.
Poor families are being provided with wheat at Rs 2 per kg.
More than 40 lakh families have already been covered by this poverty alleviation scheme.
The biggest success of the Gujarat Government has been the Gokul Gram Yojana, a scheme to develop the villages and provide a better quality of life to villagers.
The aim is to make the 18,090 villages of the State self-reliant and provide them with basic facilities ranging from roads to drinking water to schools and proper sanitation.
Since this is a participatory model of development, the government has sought the people’s participation.
The response has been tremendous: Even NRIs have come forward to contribute to the scheme.
To empower women, the state government has introduced schemes like Kuvarbai-nu-Mameru and Ghar Divda.
Daughters of poor families receive financial support at the time of their marriage.
Tribal girls have been provided with bicycles so that they can attend school.
The Daridra Naray a Yojana has encouraged children from poor families to attend school.
Under this scheme, children get free uniforms and books in addition to monetary incentives.
On the agricultural front, farmers are now allowed to buy land in any part of the state.
New insurance policies have been introduced to provide extensive cover.
The quality of seeds, pesticides and fertilizers has been improved and there has been a three-fold increase in the allocation for drip irrigation.
Farmers   today get adequate power supply.
In Maharashtra, the Shiv Sena-BJP Government has spared no effort to break the vicious grip which the mafia had established over the administration.
The law and order machinery has been strengthened and the police made accountable.
In Maharashtra, too, the emphasis has been on restoring law and order and implementing schemes aimed at providing a better quality of life for the people.
This is most obvious in the rural areas where even small farmers today are provided with power for their pumps and insurance cover for their crops.
The government has undertaken a massive programme to provide drinking water to every village.
To protect the poor from inflation, the state government has frozen the prices of five essential commodities.
The poorest of the poor are covered by the jhunka-bhakar scheme: For a rupee, a person can have a meal.
Those who cannot afford to pay for health care, have been provided with free health services.
Meritorious students from poor families are being provided with all incentives to ensure that they do not drop out of schools.
A programme has been adopted to provide free housing to 40 lakh slum-dwellers in Mumbai.
The state government has initiated steps to ensure that those who perpetrate crimes against women are punished immediately.
Kamdhenu Yojana provides women with sustained employment.
For the girl child, a special scheme has been introduced to ensure that her education and health care needs are taken care of.
The Maharashtra Government has taken the first bold step to dismantle the practice of polygamy.
Above all the state government has restored probity in public life: They have provided the people with a clean and transparent administration.
The Enron deal was scrapped because the cost was inflated.
A committee of experts renegotiated the deal with Enron and the new agreement has resulted in savings worth Rs 25,000 crores.
The cost per unit of power has also been brought down by 54 paise The biggest gain is that by bringing down the project cost, the Maharashtra Government has set new parameters for power projects elsewhere in the country.
The BJP Government in Delhi has achieved the unique   3 of fulfilling 94 of the 100 promises which the party had made within two years.
This despite the fact that the state government is hamstrung by restrictions imposed by the Union Government.
The focus has been on improving the quality of life of a common man.
The BJP had promised that if voted to power, it would pursue the prosecution of those involved in the November 1984 anti-Sikh riots.
We are proud of the fact that our government has successfully reopened the investigations which were suppressed by the Congress.
Some of the guilty people have been brought to book.
The others will also be brought to justice.
The BJP Government has provided Delhi with a corruption-free administration.
Several steps have been taken to end ‘inspector raj’ and simplify rules and regulations.
Schemes have bean introduced for employment generation and to encourage entrepreneurs.
Those living in slums have been provided with basic amenities.
These are only some of our achievements, the highlights of our governments’ performance.
Much more remains to be done and we are committed to completing the task we have set for ourselves.
   Let’s Commence A New Chapter This then is the blueprint which the Bharatiya Janata Party will implement on coming to power.
The task will be undertaken by the party’s inspiring team of leaders, each one of whom has an unmblemished record of self-less service to the nation.
It is through this blueprint that the BJP will bring about radical change in the country’s polity, society and economy.
It is this blueprint which will be the bedrock of a new India where every citizen shall be free from fear, hunger and discrimination.
This blueprint will pave the way to the next century and the new millennium.
But to implement our commitments we need your support.
The sweeping change that has become so necessary to save the nation can be brought about only with your help.
To begin with, you have to change the leadership at the helm of the country’s affairs and vote out the Congress.
The time has arrived for a nationalist government which will lead India from the dark curse of poverty to prosperity; which will free the administration from the clutches of criminals and restore probity in public life; which will reinvest the state with authority and strengthen our security forces; and, which will secure our country’s frontiers so that we do not have to suffer once again the humiliations of this millennium.
Such a government can be provided only by the BJP.
The past five decades have been a tragic story of missed opportunities and self-serving opportunist politics.
The Congress has abused power and authority for the benefit of few and to the detriment of millions of Indians.
The leaders of the Janata Dal have demonstrated their inability to think beyond themselves.
The Left parties, orphaned by the passing away of Communism all over the world, are struggling to come to terms with an ideological vacuum.
3 of these parties can boast of ideological commitment, moral courage and political conviction.
On the other hand, the BJP has emerged as the only national alternative, a party that stands apart for its ideology, commitment and courage.
We are standing at an important crossroad of our nation’s history.
The BJP appeals to all patriotic Indians to join the noble mission of national reconstruction the task of creating a strong and prosperous India.
Let us be partners in a new era of equality, peace and progress.
Vande Mataram!