
MANIFESTO Lok Sabha Elections, 1989 Central Office 11, Ashok Road, New Delhi 110 001 Phone Nos: 383349, 386586   3 -9 356 11/7/2016 11:08:30 PM Introduction The Bharatiya Janata Party is wedded to the Unity and Integrity of India.
It stands for Law and Order–for Justice, Social and Economic and for Security, Internal and External.
It is committed to the uplift of the poor and the downtrodden.
But BJP is sorry to note that the Rajiv Government has disappointed the country on all these counts.
India today is in the grip of a serious multidimensional crisis of unprecedented proportions.
The national mood is not just of cynicism but of mounting disgust and rage, not unmixed with sorrow, at the steady deterioration in public morality at the topmost leadership level.
The people feel sad that through an accident of history this great country should have been saddled with a coterie of small men who are not only incompetent and corrupt, but who lack a sense of commitment to the nation, its democratic institutions and cultural traditions.
Evidence ‘is mounting that the Prime Minister, whose personal probity is now in serious doubt, has not only been bending words but telling lies, distorting facts, changing versions, elbowing ——— ministers of integrity and unabashedly misleading the Parliament and the Nation even on crucial issues of national defence and security.
The men at the top are not only without integrity but also without shame.
In any other country, such a government would have resigned long ago.
But it is continuing in office and trying to subvert the democratic process by resorting to fascist methods, including mugging of the press, instigation of communal riots and subversion of the judiciary.
Stark failure faces the country on all fronts.
Accords have ended up in bloody discords.
The Rajiv regime is bathed in blood and muck from head to foot, from Punjab to, Assam and from Kashmir   3 Sri Lanka.
Everything Rajiv Gandhi touches ends up in a bloody mess.
A man who waded to his office through the blood-soaked streets of Delhi will be leaving behind a gory legacy.
This country is not safe in the hands of such a man or such a party.
How can men who lack integrity themselves, and are not above looting the country, defend the country and protect its integrity and honour?
The power and prestige of great institutions like the Parliament, the Army and the Judiciary have been eroded; the press has been repeatedly threatened and harassed; and the electronic media have been prostituted.
The directive principles of state policy have been forgotten; the Mandal Report on the welfare of backward classes has been pigeonholed; and never before has Indian womanhood suffered insult and assault as during the last five years.
By negativing the Supreme Court judgment in the Shahabano case, the government has put a premium on communalism and obscurantism.
And by recognising Urdu as second official language in Uttar Pradesh on election eve, it has shown more interest in Muslim votes than in Urdu language.
In the process it has only given the country so many corpses.
By not allowing the rebuilding of the Ram Janma Mandir in Ayodhya, on the lines of Somnath Mandir built by the Government of India in 1948, it has allowed tensions to rise, and gravely strained social harmony.
About the situation on the economic front, the less said the better.
During the last five years, prices have doubled and in many cases trebled; unemployment has soared by leaps and bounds and national debt increased three times.
And all this while the country has been thrown open for plunder by foreign interests who are taking out more from the country than they ever put in.
The country has paid out more to foreigners in the last five years than the entire debt of farmers which the government refuses to write off.
In this enveloping darkness, the Bharatiya Janata Party stands as a beacon of light.
It is wedded to Desh and Dharma, Samata and Samanvay.
It stands for justice–social and economic–for all, for the Kisan and the Jawan, for the young and the old, for the poor and the downtrodden, for women and children, irrespective of class, creed or gender.
It also stands for law and order particularly moral order, for without such an order, the country cannot endure and flourish.
BJP rejects both exploitative capitalism and suppressive communism.
Its approach to life and society, as expounded by our late Pt.
Deendayal Upadhyay, is integrative and holistic.
It looks upon the farmer in the field and the worker in the factory as two mighty wheels of our modern Rashtra-rath.
It believes that the nation cannot progress until those who have remained at the bottom of the social pile for centuries are helped to elevate themselves and join the mainstream on a footing of equality.
BJP believes in positive secularism which, according to our constitution-makers, meant Sarva-Dharma-Sama-Bhava and which does not connote an irreligious state.
It certainly does not mean rejection of our history and cultural heritage, the very foundations of this great nation.
The BJP stands for ‘Justice for All and Appeasement of None’.
This is what we are and this is what we aim to do.
Come and join us in the great enterprise of nation-building, in taking this country to great heights of prosperity and glory.
Following is the programme which the BJP offers to the people for taking India to its destiny-a modern, peaceful and prosperous nation on the road to an exciting future.
   3 Unity and National Integration India is one country, and all Indians irrespective of caste, creed or language are one people, one nation.
The idea of a theocratic state is an anathema to Indian mind and the BJP believes that State in India has always been a civil institution which respects all religions equally and makes no discrimination between one citizen and the other on the grounds of language, gender, caste or religion.
It is the duty of the State to guarantee justice and security to all minorities–linguistic, religious or ethnic.
The BJP considers that it is also imperative for national integration that minorities do not develop a minority complex.
Indian Constitution is quasi-federal.
It envisages strong States with a strong Centre.
The BJP believes in maintaining a balance between the two as visualised in our Constitution.
The BJP also recognises that regional imbalances have developed in some States because of their size.
The party stands for the formation of smaller states which are economically and administratively viable.
The BJP will Support and strengthen State Governments and not destabilise and topple them; Give the states a fairer share of Central revenues and increase the financial powers of the states; Constitute an Inter-State Council under Article 263 to settle all Inter-State and State-Centre disputes; Appoint State Governors in consultation with State Governments; Limit the number of ministers to 10 per cent of legislators; Guarantee to all minorities, linguistic and religious, peace   and security, and full opportunities for progress and development; Delete the temporary Article 370 of the Constitution and scrap the 59th Amendment of the Constitution:, Appoint a Commission to examine the various personal laws in vogue in the country–Hindu Law, Muslim Law, Christian Law, Parsi Law, Civil Law etc.
and to identify the fair and equitable ingredients in these laws, prepare a draft with a view to evolve a consensus for a uniform Civil Code; Appoint a Commission to examine the Constitution of India for making it an effective instrument for containing centrifugal tendencies; Grant statehood to the Union Territory of Delhi, create Separate States of Uttaranchal in U.P.
and Vananchal in Bihar, give the status of Union Territory to Laddakh; and Maintain a National Register of Citizens.
Human Rights Commission BJP will widen the scope of the present Minorities Commission and convert it into a Human Rights Commission to take care of the just rights of all individuals, groups and communities.
Fair Elections Free and fair elections are sine qua non of a democratic polity.
The BJP believes that elections must be held regularly and very fairly.
The BJP will Introduce compulsory voting for all citizens; Arrange for public funding of elections; Ban the company donations; Introduce Identity Cards for voters; Use electronic voting machines in all elections; Give the right of Postal Ballot to Indian citizens living abroad; Strengthen the independence of the Election Commission by making expenditure incurred on the Commission as a charge on the Consolidated Fund of India, as is provided in the case of Comptroller and Auditor General and   3 Court and High Court judges, and by providing the Commission with an independent infrastructure; Hold State and Central elections simultaneously every five years; Examine the feasibility of introducing the List system to elections; Have party accounts publicly audited; To prevent abuse of governmental power by the ruling party give legal teeth to the Code of Conduct framed by the Election Commission; violation of the Code shall be made a corrupt practice under the Law; Empower Election Commission to monitor all political and election coverage by the Doordarshan and the Akashvani and ensure that these media are not abused; and Include in the limitative ceiling of election expenses all expenditure incurred by the candidate, his election agent, his party and supporters.
Clean Public Life Cleansing of the public life will receive BJP’s top priority.
The party holds that the roots of all corruption lie in political corruption.
The party recognises the urgency of evolving effective mechanism to break the unholy nexus between the corrupt bureaucrat, corrupt businessmen and the corrupt politician.
The BJP is determined to fight corruption at all levels and will specifically adopt the following measures— It will enquire into all cases of corruption in the foreign deals (including the defence deals) by various ministries and departments of the Government and punish the guilty.
It will enact a law, and create institutions of Lokpal and Lokayukta bringing the P.M. and the Chief Minister also under its purview.
Streamline procedures and rules relating to purchase, awarding contracts etc.
in government and public sector undertakings, and also the discretionary powers of political authorities.
Rationalise and streamline the tax structure, providing for sufficient incentives to savings and avoiding harassment   to honest tax-payers and to avoid generation of black money.
Require all Ministers to make an annual declaration of assets.
Review and update the existing laws, administrative procedures and powers for detecting the corrupt practices and for speedily punishing the guilty.
Create an atmosphere of austerity and simplicity by enforcing strictly the norms of expenditure in government departments.
The North East The entire North Eastern region is in ferment.
The BJP holds, the Central Government squarely responsible for the neglect of the North Eastern Region and its unsatisfactory economic development and consequent exploitation by the foreign Missionaries.
The BJP would take following steps to meet the alarming situation in the North East— Setting up of the barbed wire fencing along the Indo- Bangladesh border; Detection of infiltrators and deletion of their names from the voters list on a war footing.
Steps will be taken for their deportation; Issue identity cards to all citizens in border states; Creating a special cell for identification of the landed properties acquired by infiltrators, such property will be confiscated; Repealing the Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act.
Foreign –contributions will be totally banned.
No private organisation, religious, social or any other will be allowed to receive any foreign contributions–in cash or kind; Abolishing the Innerline permit system in all the North Eastern States; Safeguarding the interests of refugees; Taking effective steps for an honourable return of the Chakmas to Bangladesh; Ensuring no further division of Assam; and Implementing a sub-plan for the economic development   3 the Tribals.
Punjab The BJP holds the Congress (I) squarely responsible for what is happening in Punjab.
Punjab situation continues to deteriorate not because of any lack of power with the government.
The government is possessing enormous powers but lacks a policy and a will to act.
The BJP has always been striving for maintaining social harmony in Punjab.
Several party leaders including the State BJP President and other colleagues have laid down their lives in this cause.
The BJP would strive for a fair and peaceful solution of the Punjab problem.
It would adopt the following approach for containing terrorism in Punjab— Creation of a security belt all along the Western borders with Pakistan without delay; Secure the assistance of Army to help the civil administration in the Mand area, if need be; Strengthen the intelligence apparatus; Punishing those who were responsible for the killings of innocents in Delhi and elsewhere after the assassination of Mrs Gandhi; Adequately compensating the victims of violence; and Review the structural changes in the economy of Punjab and to remove the distortions.
Jammu And Kashmir And The Western The BJP views with concern the recent developments in the State of Jammu and Kashmir and the continued discrimination against the people of Jammu.
The rabid communal and pro-Pakistan elements are spearheading a massive hate India campaign in Kashmir valley and the entire region is engulfed by widespread terrorism.
The unabated infiltration and smuggling all along the western border needs to be effectively curbed.
The BJP suggests that— Effective and immediate measures to weed out the foreigners from Jammu and Kashmir, Rajasthan and Gujarat be taken; Border with Pakistan should be effectively guarded by   creating a security belt to stop infiltration of trained terrorists and smuggling of arms and ammunition, narcotics and other contraband commodities; and A Regional Council for Jammu be formed so that regional 12 imbalances in development be removed.
Law And Order And Protection Of Weaker Sections The BJP views with alarm the rise of social violence in the country.
This includes communal violence, atrocities on Scheduled Castes and Tribals, and criminal assaults on women.
The BJP believes that the weaker sections need an effective protection from atrocities and the Party is committed to the security of life, limb, property and honour of all citizens.
In case of a serious eruption of violence, the BJP commends that— A judicial inquiry will always be held; The inquiry report will be published; Those guilty of incitement to violence or dereliction of duty will be punished; All not sufferers will be suitably compensated and rehabilitated; An indepth socio-economic study of riot-prone areas to take effective steps for riot-prevention will be conducted; The Police Force be transformed into an efficient and impartial instrument of law and order, through modernisation programme and better service conditions; and Political meddling in police work be stopped and a machinery for redressal of Police/ People’s griveances be created.
Justice And Judicial Reforms The BJP believes that without an independent judiciary, it is impossible to have the Rule of Law.
Also the judicial system should be speedy, inexpensive and just.
The BJP would under-take the following measures to restore the independence, integrity and efficiency of the judicial system— Take effective measures to provide free legal aid to the poor and specially the Scheduled Castes and Tribes and   3 abolition of the Court-fees; Simplify the legal procedures and increase the number of judges so that majority of the cases are disposed of within one year; Provide mobile courts for the rural areas and set up Nyaya Panchayats with judicial powers; Offer better service conditions and emoluments to judges at all levels; The Chief Justice of India should have the final say in the appointment of the High Court and Supreme Court Judges to be recommended by an independent body; Raise the retirement age of judges to 65, give them full pension equal to their salary, prohibit them from holding any office after retirement; Appoint a Commission for suggesting an overhaul of the Judicial System which is under serious stress; Appoint special courts for different categories of cases so that pending cases in various High Courts and Supreme Court are cleared within one year; and Introduce social security measures like provident fund and group insurance schemes for the advocates.
Decentralisation Of Power And Panchayati Raj The Panchayat System formed the bedrock of the democratic functioning of the Indian Social System since the Vedic period.
Mahatma Gandhi and Jay Prakash Narayan were strong votaries of local self-government.
The Jana Sangh under the leadership of Pt.
Deendayal Upadhyay had always canvassed for the Constitutional status of the Panchayats and Municipal boards.
The BJP believes in decentralisation of power and strengthening of democracy at the grass roots.
The party ensures a Constitutional status to the Panchayats and other local self institution and assured share of resources so that they do not depend upon discretionary grants.
The BJP will neither impose Panchayats from above nor will  use them to bypass the State Governments.
National Economy The Indian economy is presently going through an acute crisis.
In fact it has been stagnating since the last ten years and more so since 1985.
The per capita availability of the items of staple diet of the nation, in these years has gone down.
The nation is more undernourished today than it was few years ago.
As a result of wrong plan priorities, the country is producing more colour TV sets, but not enough steel, more computers but not enough power, more fancy cars but not enough buses, more superfine fabrics but not enough cheaper varieties of dhoties and saries.
The result of this lopsided elitist sense of priorities, combined with corruption and profligacy, is that today there are more people looking for jobs than ever before, more landless farmers than ever before, more illiterates than ever before.
The consumer is groaning under the burden of back-breaking prices.
There is more sorrow than happiness, more poverty than wealth.
The BJP hold the ruling party squarely responsible for deliberately neglecting the agriculture sector in pursuit of mythical modernisation.
Forty years ago, the disparity between the farmer and his counterpart in other sectors was not very large.
Today it is one to three; soon, it will be one to four.
A country that treats its farmers with contempt is bound to remain mired in poverty, as India is.
The Country is again resorting to imports of foodgrains after so many years, which in itself is a tell-tale commentary on the mess that has been made on the farm front, in fact, in respect of the entire economy.
Thanks to the wrong policies of our rulers over the years, thousands of crores of rupees from the rural poor have been transferred to the urban rich, resulting in a colossal rural   3 .
The BJP will reverse all these ugly trends and give the country a humane economy.
It will take all steps necessary to achieve full employment, maximise production, stabilise prices and eradicate poverty and rural indebtedness.
For this BJP offers the following programme: Agriculture In the opinion of the BJP the speedy development of the agriculture and rural sector is the key to India’s prosperity.
The party recognises that more than 65 per cent of Indian farmers are poor, they need capital and subsidised inputs for their rapid growth.
The Kisan will continue to flaunder in poverty unless the burden of people depending upon agriculture is reduced.
A network of agro-industrial complexes in the rural areas is the real answer to the problems of poverty of the Indian peasantry.
The party is committed to implement its Charter of Rights of Kisan.
The BJP offers a new deal to the farmers and it will— Write off the debts of the farmers, agricultural labourers and rural artisans; Allocate sixty percent of the plan money, both Central and State, for rural development, agricultural and allied services; Ensure remunerative prices to the farmers, computed after taking into consideration all the parameters like cost of inputs and living index etc; Ensure minimum wages to farm labour; Maintain parity of prices between agricultural and industrial produce; Remove all restrictions on the movement of agricultural produce throughout the country; Arrange abundant and regular supply of water and energy; Introduce crop and cattle insurance schemes which would guarantee adequate compensation in case of crop failure, damage or loss due to natural calamities or outbreak of epidemics in cattle; also update the age old famine code; Provide market value compensation in one instalment in case of land acquisition and rehabilitation of the uprooted in the process;   Issue Pass Books to Kisans and implement the land laws; Reclaim all wasteland and give special attention to dry farming; Speedily complete the on-going big irrigation projects, take up thousands of small and minor irrigation projects, organise efficient flood management and relief; Encourage the cultivation of pulses, oil-seeds, fruits, nuts, and other cash crops; Protect the traditional rights on village forests and Nistar Land; Speedily provide the minimum civic facilities like drinking water, roads and other means of communication, public health and hygiene; Organise the purchase operations through a wide and efficient network so as to ensure that all farmers and particularly the small farmers realise the guaranteed price and are not forced to make a distress sale; and Restructuring the Agriculture Cost and Price Commission so that two-thirds of its members are drawn from those engaged in farming.
Cow Protection And Animal Standard The BJP notes with concern that in spite of the clear provision of the Constitution in Article 48 and the Supreme Court’s emphasis that cow protection is a constitutional mandate and slaughter of cows is not enjoined in any religion including Muslim religion, complete prohibition of cow slaughter has yet not been introduced in various States of India, specially in West Bengal and Kerala.
The BJP recognises the fact that from times immemorial Cow protection has remained one of the basic tenets of Indian culture and it is on the patient back of the cow and its progeny that the entire structure of the Indian agriculture rests.
Over seventy million animals are employed in the farming operations in Indian villages, more than eighty percent rural transport requirements are met by the bullocks.
Cow and its progeny continue to be the major source of power, manure and fuel including bio-gas.
Cow is also an effective protection against environmental degradations.
The BJP regretfully observes that about three million cows   3 slaughtered every year and most of them for export.
The party would put a total ban on the slaughter of the cows.
It will Amend the Article 48 of the Constitution to include bulls, and bullocks, and to prohibit State-trading in slaughter of cows; to ensure that no-one has a fundamental right of trade or business to slaughter cows; and to incorporate the subject of Cow-protection in the concurrent list; Implement a policy of Go-Samvardhan or development of cow and cattle breeding including the improvement of Sheep and Goat breeds to bring about a white revolution in the country; and Provide tax exemption to the income of Gashalas and Pinjarapoles.
Industry The BJP’s industrial policy flows from the following principles— Self-reliance: The Party’s industrial policy would be strongly nationalistic in approach and content.
The party, would like to keep multinationals out of the field of consumer industries.
The party regards self-reliance as an overriding component in our external economic relations, including the import of technology and capital.
Decentralisation: The party stands for political as well as economic democracy, so that the benefits of economic development go to the smallest man.
The party believes that for this decentralisation of economic power, presently concentrated in the hands of the state or of big business, is necessary.
Primacy for agriculture and Agro-based industries, Swadeshi and importance to the small and medium scale sector in industry are commitments that flow from this.
Modernisation: BJP will harness new technologies to the changing requirements of the country, and build India as a modern and progressive nation.
But it will not allow technology to degrade man as just another input in Gross National Product.
Man will be the main focus of our developmental policies.
Daridra Narayan Sewa: Consistent with the above three elements, the party will aim at securing to every Indian citizen minimum conditions of material welfare in terms of food, raiment, shelter, health and education.
The party will leave no stone unturned in carrying jobs to the people.
Generation of employment will be a major component of BJP’s industrial policy.
BJP will encourage and improve industry all-round.
We will— Make the public sector productive and profitable; its management will be professionalised and a Central service called the ‘Indian Management Service’ will be formed to select, train and allocate the professional managers to these units; Demarcate the spheres of multi-national corporations, big- scale industry, small-scale industry and cottage industry; Ensure that the existing patent laws safeguarding Indian national interests remain intact under external pressure; Cut down the plethora of controls which presently exist, and which breed corruption and dampen enterprises, and maintain only such of these restrictions as are necessary for social justice; Foster the spirit of Swadeshi; Reserve more and more consumer items to small-scale and cottage sectors; Make credit more cheaply available to small-scale industry; Modernise industrial plants; and ensure fuller utilization of capacity; Promote agro-based industries; Encourage Research and Development to play a live role in industrial growth; Require businessmen to consider themselves as trustees of the public good; Publicly honour excellence in industry and commerce; and Provide tax and non-tax incentives to companies for making permanent workers share-holders out of a part of their gross profit.
3 Textile Policy The BJP recognises the need to have an integrated textile policy and would ensure protection to handloom and cottage sectors of textile industry.
To this end the party will demarcate the role of each of the Sectors viz.
organised sector or mills, powerloom and handloom sectors, and Khadi and cottage industries.
The Party would ensure cheap clothing to the poor and national and international market to various sectors.
The handloom sector would receive adequate protection.
The interests of cotton growers would also be duly safeguarded.
Taxation BJP would adopt firm and bold measures to prevent generation of black-money.
Rationalise and simplify the entire tax structure.
The highest rate of income tax shall be 40 per cent; Raise the present exemption limit of income tax to ₹ 30,000/-; and introduce differential slab system and lower rates for fixed income groups; Abolish octroi duty and require the State Governments to make good the loss of Municipalities; Abolish Sales Tax and require the Centre to make good the loss of State Governments; Exempt all savings and investments in approved organisations (including non-government institutions) from Wealth tax and Estate duty; Share Corporation tax revenues with the States; Take stringent measures against the smugglers and other economic offenders; and Keep a strict watch on the operations of foreign banks.
Foreign Assets The BJP will enact and strictly enforce a suitable legislation so as to require all Indian citizens to disclose their foreign assets including secret and undeclared bank accounts.
The Party will take all measures including signing treaties for unearthing Indian unaccounted money in foreign countries.
Encourage the growth of small local banks, duly supervised and guaranteed by the Reserve Bank of India.
Take drastic action against tax-evasion.
Motivate people for savings and Protect the honest tax-payer from harassment.
Pursue a policy of balanced-budget for the country and will discontinue the present practice of huge deficits in the national budget.
Impose statutory ceilings on deficits in budget and debts of the government.
Convert RBI into an autonomous institution, responsible to the Parliament for regulating the monetary policies of the government.
Prices BJP will maintain price stability by efficient management of production and supplies, and by rooting out corruption, – which is a major contributory factor for price rise.
With this view the party will evolve a well coordinated wages, prices and profits policy.
The BJP will Appoint a Price Commission to regulate the prices of manufactured goods both in private and public sector; Fully and promptly neutralise any rise in prices by increased DA in both private and public sectors and in private and Government service, including Central, State and local government; Open more fair price shops in towns and villages, existing arrangements will be streamlined; and Make not only grains, sugar and kerosene, but also pulses, cooking oil and soap and such sundry articles of every day use available at these shops.
Consumer Protection The BJP is of the opinion that there must be a co-relation between cost of production, price and profit.
Nobody should be permitted to pocket super-profits.
The party also recognises the need to enforce strict measures of quality control and price regulation.
With this view the BJP will Build a powerful consumer movement and formulate a price and profit policy for industrially manufactured goods;   3 .
Make statutory provision for declaring cost of production of industrially manufactured items; Ensure a reasonable rate of interest on the deposits by a consumer for registering his demand for cars, scooters, installation of telephones, gas, electric connections, etc; and Enforce the Consumer Protection Act, 1986, specially by constituting consumers’ courts in all the districts.
Labour BJP believes in healthy trade unionism.
It will Rationalise and simplify Labour Laws; Recognise unions on the basis of secret ballot; Introduce worker participation from the Shop Floor to the Board Room in all public sector projects, public limited companies and foreign companies operating in India; Protect workers against inflation; and Make laws and evolve an effective mechanism to protect the labour from occupational health hazards arising from industries like asbestos, cement, slate, mica, chemicals, textiles.
Full Employment And Right To Work BJP recognises the citizen’s Fundamental Right to work and will incorporate it in the Constitution.
All our economic policies whether it is small dams or cottage industry, house construction or road building–will boost employment.
In addition we will Introduce Employment Guarantee Scheme throughout the country; Provide Pensions for the aged poor; Establish techno-economic project formulation bureaus in all districts and blocks for speedy launching of various full employment schemes with a special emphasis to cover the poor under-employed; and Announce a work guarantee scheme as soon as the full employment plan for the block is approved.
Energy There is acute energy crisis in India particularly in the villages, which have remained without any dependable sources of energy   even after forty-two years of Independence.
This situation will have to be tackled on a war-footing.
BJP will Intensify efforts to find more oil, coal and natural gas reserves; Improve the working of power plants which are now functioning at less than 50 per cent of capacity; Stop the massive theft of electric power; Introduce power-efficient, energy-saving devices in homes and factories; Increase forest cover from the present 19 per cent of land to the desired 33 per cent; and Encourage wind, water, bio-gas and solar power generation.
Justice To The Poor For accelerating the process of distributive justice the following policy measures will be undertaken— 1 .
The surplus land already identified (about 5.5 million acres) shall be distributed to the landless within a maximum period of 3 years; All tillers of the land shall be given title deeds, on the basis of quick, on-the-spot inquiries by competent authorities.
The report regarding the progress made in this connection would be placed on the floor of the Assembly every year for approval; Block level committees and tribunals with 50 per cent representation from tenants and landless labour would be appointed to implement land ceiling and tenancy reforms; Legislative measures for the protection of unorganised rural worker would be introduced; The share of small and marginal farmers landless workers and artisans in institutional credit will be raised upto 50 per cent under a time-bound programme; Antyodaya Schemes covering every development block would be launched; and The big industrial houses will be required to spend a portion of their wealth for the rural welfare every year.
3 People The Indian people are nation’s greatest assets.
They are the real instruments of transforming the country and building its future.
The BJP is fully conscious of their manifold problems and is committed to redress their sufferings.
It offers the following programme for different sections of Indian citizens.
Rural Folk The BJP recognises that rural poor has to be provided or subsidised a set of social services and an infrastructure for their speedy development.
The BJP will Launch Schemes to supply ample and clean drinking water to each village, all problem villages to be covered in five years; Energise every village; Connect the villages through all-weather pucca roads; Provide comfortable mass transit; Implement schemes to offer health and family planning knowledge, supplies and services; Undertake a massive drive for literacy and continuous non-formal education to transmit professional knowledge, and to raise the consciousness of the poor about current injustices, and their rights; Provide sanitation (with increasingly mechanised and covered waste and sewage haulage, disposal and recycling; and Implement Housing Schemes for the poor.
Salariat The BJP fully appreciates the problems of the government employees and the salaried class, now crushed between fixed income and rising prices.
It will Link salaries in private services also to cost of living index; include minimum housing standard in computing minimum wages; Provide residential accommodation to all government employees and encourage employers to build houses for staff; Progressively introduce triple benefit schemes in private services, private sector and public sector; Lower Life Insurance premia; and Increase the return on Provident Fund deposits.
Senior Citizens And Pensioners The Party recognises the need to have a National Policy for Senior Citizens.
In the opinion of the BJP the pensioners are the most hard-pressed in the fixed income group.
BJP will Have a National Pension Policy to secure social and economic justice to all citizens including senior citizens; Replace the 1971 Pension Act by a new law, more in tune with the changed social security concepts; Launch Schemes to utilise the talents and expertise of the Senior Citizens; Grant pensioners DA relief on the same scale as to serving employees; Introduce lower income tax rates for pensioners and ensure higher rates of interest to Senior Citizens on investment in certain approved schemes; Re-fix pensions as and when pay scales are revised; and Grant travel concessions to pensioners and Senior Citizens.
Ex-servicemen The BJP holds that the plight of the ex-servicemen has suffered at the hands of the Rajiv Government.
The BJP would work towards a purposeful resolution of their problems and is committed to implementing the following   3 — One rank, one pension; Guaranteed avenues of employment upto the age of 58; Necessary changes in the agricultural and urban land tenancy laws so as to ensure proprietory rights of servicemen; To bring the welfare of ex-servicemen on the Concurrent List in the Constitution; and Strengthen District Sainik Boards.
Sindhi Speaking People The BJP recognises the valuable contributions made by the Sindhi speaking people for enriching the Indian society.
The party also assures the Sindhi Community of protection and promotion of their identity, culture, language, and literature and fulfilment of constitutional guarantees enshrined in Article 350A and 350B of the Constitution of India.
The Party would also give them due representation in various spheres of social and political life.
Women The BJP will Take measures to remove gender discrimination and give equal status to the women in society; ban the determination of sex of a child in embryonic stage; Make registration of marriages compulsory–like births and deaths to prevent child marriages; Make the wife equal co-sharer in the husband’s wealth and income; Initiate schemes to provide economic opportunities for women, provide more facilities in technical and vocational training by starting ITIs and Polytechnics specially for women; Take stringent measures against employers who discriminate against women workers on the ground of marital status, age or family responsibility, in order to save themselves from the responsibility of providing maternity benefit, creche facilities etc;   Launch a special drive to improve the educational status for women.
More women’s universities will be opened; Reserve upto 30 per cent certain categories of jobs for women; Treat burning injuries as attempt to murder and dowry deaths as murder under section 302 IPC; Provide smokeless Chulhas at concessional rates to village women; and Build hostels for single women working in the cities.
Youths The BJP has a special appeal to the youth of India.
The Party recognises the tremendous potential in them and calls upon them to join great endeavour of national reconstruction.
The BJP in accordance with a National Youth Policy, will Device mechanism for the participation of youths in the complementation of the poverty alleviation programes; Ensure participation of youths in literacy drive, conservation of environment, Land Army etc; Mobilise youths for fighting social evils like untouchability, dowry, superstitions, casteism, etc.
and develop a scientific outlook in them; Encourage the spirit of adventurism in the youths; and Inculcate in them a sense of pride for their glorious heritage and a will to transform India into a modern, progressive, prosperous and front rank nation.
Scheduled Castes And Scheduled Tribes The BJP stands for all such measures which will bring the SC and ST people on par with the rest of the society, not in terms of economic status alone but on broad spectrum of social life giving them a rightful place of honour to live with a sense of belonging.
The BJP will Enforce laws against untouchability and atrocities very stringently and set up mobile or special courts to try cases of atrocities against SC and ST; Atrocity prone villages will be identified and steps will be taken to safeguard the life, honour and property of the   3 Castes and Tribes; A massive campaign to eradicate untouchability will be launched; Full allocation and utilisation of funds under special component plan in proportion to SC population will be ensured; A national level financial agency on the lines of NABARD to cater the credit needs of SC/ST will be set up; Ensure greater participation of SC/ST in small, cottage and rural industries; Launch vigorous schemes during VIII Five Year Plan coinciding with Dr. Ambedkar’s centenary to raise SCs and STs families above poverty line; Implement the reservation policy for SC and ST by resorting to special recruitment drives so as to fill their quota within the shortest possible time; Put an end to the carrying of night soil as headload and introduce modern technique for disposal.
Also take steps for effective rehabilitation; Separate heads of account for SC/ST expenditure will be maintained by the Central and the State Governments; A befitting memorial to Dr. B.R.
Ambedkar will be established in Delhi during his centenary year; Evolve a new forest policy based on a partnership between the forest tribals and the forest authorities Frame policies which protect tribals from exploitation, and indebtedness, and enable them to grow in accordance with their own genius; Remove the impediments in the speedy development of Tribal and Hill areas and settle the pending claims for grant of permanent pattas to the tribals by amending the Forest Conservation ACT (1986); Amend the laws relating to the collection and marketing of the minor forest produce to protect the economic interests of the ST; Convert all forest villages into revenue villages; and Formulate a sub-plan for the economic development of the Scheduled Tribes.
Reservation Policy In the opinion of the BJP the question of reservation has to be viewed with an open mind free from all prejudices of any kind.
For this BJP commends: Reservation should be continued for the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes as before; Reservation should also be made for other backward classes broadly on the basis of the Mandal Commission Report, with preference to be given to the poor among these very classes; and As poverty is an important contributory factor for backwardness, reservation should also be provided for members of the other castes on the basis of their economic condition.
Physically Handicapped The BJP accepts the rehabilitation of the physically handicapped persons as a component of Social Welfare.
The party will Make a detailed survey and prepare a register of disabled persons in each district; Open centres to train the disabled for appropriate vocations; Give tax benefits to those industries, firms, and organisations who either absorb the disabled or provide limbs and other artefacts for their use; Provide marketing and other infrastructural facilities for the items manufactured by the disabled; and Will pay cash awards and other incentives to those handicapped who excel in any field of life; Destitutes The BJP recognises the need for providing the destitute homes and orphanages and this would form an important component of Social Welfare Schemes.
Institutions providing such facilities would be given tax relief.
   3 of Life Man does not live by bread alone.
He must also have health and housing, education and sports, and above all a happy environment.
Housing And Town Development The BJP recognises the right to shelter by all citizens of India.
The party would evolve a National Housing Policy based on the minimum housing standards for the urban and the rural poors.
In this direction the Party will Take measures for providing minimum area of land for housing to each family at cheaper rates; Expand and strengthen housing co-operatives, and encourage trusts and other establishments for building houses to be rented or sold; Improve the basic civic amenities in towns and pay special attention to the problems of slums to improve their habitats; Develop small and medium townships to prevent overcrowding of metropolitian towns; Progressively develop all urban centres as garden cities; Rationalise Housing and Rent Control laws; and Double the number of houses now built annually by various State Housing Boards.
Education The party views with concern that with the rising cost of education, the existing socio-economic disparities will be perpetuated in the field of education.
The BJP belives in equalisation of educational opportunities and build up a system worthy of the genius of our heritage and the undoubted capacities of our youth.
Towards this end, we will Implement Articles 45 of the Constitution to give free education to all children in the 6-14 age group, evolve a new strategy for a teacher oriented expansion programme for this; Launch an Adult Literacy Programme; Give education a vocational and technical content, establish a complex of agro-industrial polytechnics in each district;, Introduce compulsory moral instruction, that will be nondenominational but character-building; Supply subsidised text books and writing materials, develop book-banks in the educational institutions; Ensure academic freedom and the autonomy of universities, raise the emoluments and status of teachers; Make the Universities and colleges adopt localities and villages and help them in their overall development; Delink jobs from degrees; Progressively increase the allocation for education till it reaches the six per cent of the GNP; and Associate students’ unions with the management of student welfare programmes.
Language The BJP supports the principle that people have a right to be educated and run their administration in their own language.
The BJP will Impement the three language formula and make adequate arrangements for language teaching so that persons knowing different Indian languages are available in each region; Speedily implement the recommendations of the Parliamentary Committee on Official language; Take necessary administrative steps that candidates can appear with Hindi medium in all Competitive Examinations and/or interviews for recruitment in all central services, and admissions to national institutions like IlTs and AIIMS; Remove all impediments in pursuing higher education and research through Hindi or other Indian languages;   3 .
Promote the study of Sanskrit language as the storehouse of ancient Indian wisdom and restore its position in the three languages formula; Assist the development of those Indian languages which are neither State languages nor regional languages, but have contributed to the enrichment of Indian culture; and Include Nepali in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution.
Health And Nutrition Health care to all citizens is the primary duty of the State.
A majority of children born in families below poverty line are undernourished and show sign of mental retardation chiefly due to protein deficiency.
BJP, therefore, considers hygiene, sanitation and nutrition as more important than medicines and hospitals.
We will Along with Allopathy, recognise and promote Ayurveda and Siddha, Unani and Homoeopathy, Chromopathy and Nature Cure and in general encourage holistic healing; Supply free milk and nutrition to children in primary schools, and give every child an annual physical check-up; Improve the present district civil hospitals, and set up similar hospitals at taluka level; Give every village a Health Care Centre to take particular care of expectant mothers and provide them with adequate nourishment; Have a Mobile Dispensary in each taluka; Build more and better public latrines, particularly for women in villages; Organise Eye Camps, and camps for other serious ailments in various areas; Implement Hathi Committee Report on Pharmaceuticals and make essential medicines available cheap to the people; Implement a programme to control and eradicate the communicable diseases; and Take effective measures against drug addiction and alcoholism.
Science And Technology The BJP believes that Science and Technology (ST) should be allowed to play its due role to transform India into a prosperous, modern and enlightened society.
The party would unhesitatingly apply appropriate scientific and technological methods for increasing productivity, eradicating poverty, hunger and disease and to provide meaningful employment along with ‘the basic amenities of life to the vast percentage of population living below the poverty line.
The party holds that science is not merely harnessing nature for material wealth but is as well liberating and enriching mind and enlarging the human spirit.
The BJP would use science in the service of the poor and would develop technology with a human face.
The party is equally concerned about the rising trends of brain drain.
The BJP will Foster a scientific temper among the people; Use Science and Technology for increasing productivity and generating employment; Implement a vigorous programme of science education and research for improving quality of life; Establish a network of Centres for Application of Science and Technology to Rural Areas, implement lab to land programmes and develop a strong low cost agro-industrial base; Put new life in National Laboratories, develop them as centres of excellence in applied research; Direct these laboratories to evolve Appropriate Technology for Indian needs; Accelerate the production of scientific literature in regional languages and evolve a national terminology for science and technology; and Create the right working conditions, for our best brains to remain here and serve the country and not migrate to other lands.
Sports The BJP will give all encouragement to sports and put India on the Olympic map of the world.
We will Evolve a new dynamic national sports policy aiming at bringing 10 per cent population on the playgrounds   3 winning medals in Olympic and other international competitions; Provide play fields in schools, colleges, Universities, rural areas and open sports complexes in all districts with modern equipments under a time bound programme; Sports persons at par with those available to the sports persons of advanced countries; Ensure job security for sportsmen and admission to the colleges and technical courses; and Respect the Olympic charter and autonomy of the sports bodies and will prohibit governmentalisation of sports.
Family Welfare And Population Policy The BJP recognises the growing concern of the people about the dangers of a demographic explosion and distortions created by the mishandling of the population control programmes by the Congress(I) government.
The BJP is committed to the policy of responsible parenthood and believes that population control programme should be given top priority while formulating national plans.
It expects all sections of Indian community to fully participate in these programmes.
The BJP will Strive for creating a national consensus for adopting a National Population Policy and if necessary to take suitable legislative measures for it; Make Family Planning information and facilities available to the people.
Involve all voluntary, social and cultural organisations in creating an awareness for adopting family planning as a way of life; Perform Vasectomy and Tubectomy operations free, and encourage all methods including herbal and biorhythmic; Help childless couples with medical assistance to have a child; Integrate the family planning programme with other community welfare programmes; and Pursue vigorously for the voluntary adoption of the ‘two children’ norm and evolve a system of incentives and disincentives for achieving the long term demographic goals.
Environment The BJP attaches high priority to stop the degradation of environment.
In the opinion of the BJP, the rapid depletion of natural resources, risks of green house effect, the destruction of tropical rain-forests, and the hazards of dumping of industrial waste and discharge of highly toxic materials in air and water are matters of global concern and world opinion has to be alerted against them.
International efforts are needed to save the planet.
Preservation of environment has been an integral part of Indian way of life.
We look upon India as Bharat Mata and a holy land.
Our land, air, waters, our hills, forests, flora and fauna are all sacred to us.
We will keep them neat, clean and intact.
We will Formulate a National Resources Management Policy and adopt a holistic approach in planning; Require anti-pollution devices to be installed to process and clean up industrial and Municipal effluents before the same are discharged into our rivers; Keep a strict watch on chemical fertilizers and insecticides for any poisoning of the soil; Improve auto exhausts to prevent the fouling of the air; Curb the aggression of noise in the cities; Undertake a massive afforestation programme; While protecting the traditional rights of Vanavasis, we will require the planting of three trees for every single tree that is cut by anybody for any reason; Make environmental concerns an integral part of education; and Take special care in import of technology and promote research for developing indigenous pollution free technology.
Culture The BJP believes in preserving and propagating the cultural values which have kept India united through the ages.
It will Conserve the ancient heritage of India and make people feel proud about it; Promote Indian values of life through cultural centres;   3 .
Acquaint people with the glorious traditions and achievements of ancient Indian genius in the fields of science, technology, medicine, agriculture, etc; Wage a relentless war against superstitions and outmoded customs; and Emphasise on culture as a dynamic and synthetic process.
Arts Arts is the essence of life.
BJP will encourage all art forms.
It will make the various arts, part of Education, Production and Life.
To promote theatre, BJP will, as a rule, exempt all theatrical performances from entertainment tax.
The BJP will encourage folk art in various fields.
Films BJP recognises the great role of cinema in entertainment, education and national integration.
BJP will Have, in addition to ‘A’ and ‘U’ Films, ‘Q’ that is Quality films, which will be exempt from entertainment taxes; Have special theatres in metropolitan centres to screen art films and other Quality films; and Implement the recommendations of the Karanth Committee on National Film Policy.
Tourism The BJP recognises the importance of tourism as an instrument of national integration, international understanding and employment generation.
India abounds in natural beauty and charming tourist centres, which have fascinated people from far distant quarters.
It will Promote tourism both national and international as an industry and give incentives to those who take it as a profession; Will evolve a policy of integrating tourism and marketing of handicrafts and other art works; Take a scheme of training tourist guides and opening tourist homes and information centres; and Provide infrastructural facilities like sites for building   dormitories at subsidised rates and network of communication channels.
Mass Media The BJP reaffirms its commitments to the freedom of thought and expression.
We will Make freedom of the Press an explicit Fundamental Right, and not just an implied one derived from the citizen’s right to Freedom of Expression; Encourage the growth of the Press by abolishing the duty irk on newsprint and the tax on newspaper advertising; Revive the ‘Prasar Bharati Bill’ of 1979, which sought to convert AIR and Doordarshan into an autonomous corporation.
The Corporation would have greater autonomy than that enjoyed by BBC today; Review the Official Secrets Act in so far as it obstructs the Right to Know and enact a Freedom of Information Law; and Implement the P.C.
Joshi Report on TV software to improve the quality of TV programmes.
   3 Security The BJP holds that National security is a primary responsibility of State.
Security of the nation is an integrated whole: an amalgam of the internal, the economic, the social, the political, the military and the diplomatic.
The BJP will, therefore, resolve the social and political turmoil in strategically sensitive border states like Jammu & Kashmir, Punjab, North East and Assam.
Indian diplomacy can assist in the protection of our national interests only if it is guided by a purposeful foreign policy.
Foreign Policy The conduct of diplomacy by the Rajiv Government has left India’s foreign policy in tatters.
Never has the country faced so much animosity from so many of our neighbours, as today.
It is BJP’s view that the challenges, we face in the field of external relations, arise from a re-assertion of the altered importance of non-alignment, as a concept, in a rapidly transforming world.
It is our view that increasingly, we should give emphasis to foreign economic policy under the time-proved concept of non-alignment.
It is vital to move the world towards a greater and more effective North-South and South-South Co-operation.
The BJP has stood for, and is committed to mutually beneficial aim of good bilaterial relation with all our neighbours and a strengthening of SAARC.
We stand for a normalisation of relations with China, with due safeguards for Tibet, proper recognition of India’s national interests and honourable solution of the border dispute.
We would work for a comprehensive package of settlement of all outstanding matters with Pakistan and a widening of the people-to-people relations between our two countries.
We would   work for an early withdrawal of the IPKF from Sri Lanka.
With Nepal BJP would seek the re-establishment of harmonious relations based on the concept of interdependent growth.
The BJP stands for a foreign policy committed to world peace, disarmament and a non-exploitative new international economic order.
The Party will Work towards re-imparting dynamism to the non-aligned movement; Pursue a policy of peace, friendship and co-operation with neighbouring countries; Reject the domination of super-power interest in South Asia and the Indian Ocean; Work towards the establishment of a regional common market by strengthening South Asian Regional Conference; Work for the establishment of a new international economic order, take initiative for trade and monetary reform, North- South dialogue with emphasis on enhanced South-South Co-operation; Continued efforts for the world-wide rejection of apartheid; and Continuously work towards the solution of problems of people of Indian origin living abroad.
Defence Defence preparedness has suffered grievously in the hands of Rajiv Government gripped as it is, by ad-hocism and by corruption surrounding defence procurements.
This has brought to a standstill all policy-making and implementation within the Defence Ministry.
The other great harm that Rajiv Government has caused to the country is excessive misemployment in an adventurous manner, of the Indian Armed Forces on Political roles or on militarily unattainable tasks.
This has caused a very serious lowering of the morale of our Armed Forces, and hence of its total combat effectiveness.
BJP wishes to caution the nation against the extremely harmful consequences if such a situation is permitted to continue.
The BJP would work actively towards reviving the morale of the Armed Forces, giving a solemn assurance that the Indian Armed Forces, the Army, the Navy and the Air Force, would not   3 either in equipment or in the necessary where withals to execute their responsibilities.
The BJP will exert for— Optimum defence preparedness including production of nuclear bombs and delivery systems; Diversification of sources of suply of defence hardware, continued emphasis on maximising indigenous production, self-reliance and Defence Research and Development; Greater public accountability of defence expenditure; Enhancement of Indian Navy’s capability; Identification, and elimination of, foreign lobbies associated with defence weapons procurement and contracts; and Improve service conditions in the Armed Forces so as to make careers in the Army, Navy and Air Force more attractive to the best talent in the country.
This then is the programme which the BJP pledges to implement under the inspiring leadership of Shri A.B.
Vajpayee and Shri L.K.
Advani.
The dedicated cadres of the party, headed by these brilliant leaders of impeccable record of clean public life and selfless service to the nation, are committed to usher in a new political culture.
In the opinion of the BJP a critical moment of history has arrived for India.
The country can not afford to miss this moment of history, this opportunity to throw out the last vestige of the dynastic rule mainly responsible for this country’s ruination.
The BJP on its part has left no stone unturned in its efforts to put up a determined and united electoral battle and has unhesitatingly sacrificed its party interests whenever national interests so demanded.
The Bharatiya Janata Party calls upon the people to join in its struggle for a value based polity and throw out this corrupt and incompetent government.
