
ELECTION MANIFESTO 1991     This We Believe The country stands today on a major cross-roads of history.
A right turn – and the country would be well on its way to fulfilment.
A wrong turn – and the country would be in serious trouble.
The electoral contests so far have been mainly bouts between various shades of Congressmen.
Today for the first time Bharatiya Janata Party the Party of Independent India, offers itself as an independent and complete alternative to the current confusions.
The country has been advancing at snail’s pace when it has not actually been declining.
Prices are rising and employment generation rate is falling.
The foreign debt trap is closing on us.
Communal violence has rocked several States.
For the first time in history we had immolations by the frustrated flower of Indian youth.
State-Centre relations are seriously strained.
Opportunistic alliances have brought Democracy itself into disrepute.
Secessionism has raided its ugly head in Punjab, Kashmir and Assam.
And what is worse, there is sinister cooperation between these separatist terrorists and the people’s war group in Andhra and LTTE in Tamil Nadu.
In the face of this challenge, other parties have gone casteist communalist or both.
Different Political Parties exploited even the tragic Gulf War to carve out and comer communal Vote banks.
The leaders of these parties have conclusively proved themselves non-leaders.
Taking advantage of this confusion, communists are making attempts to gain some respectability. .
The Bharatiya Janata Party as the party of Nationalism, Holism and Integral Humanism, offers a complete, new and higher alternative to the current dismal scene.
As the party of Swadesh and Swa-dharma, it is wedded to our country, our people and   3 culture.
It believes in consensus and cooperation, and not in contrariety and conflict.
It would uplift the poor and the down- trodden, without pitting caste against caste, without inciting class against class.
As the party of law, order and justice, it would ensure the security of life, limb and honour of all citizens.
It seeks the restoration of Ram Janmabhoomi in Ayodhya only by way of a symbolic righting of historic wrongs, so that the old unhappy chapter of acrimony could be ended, and a Grand National Reconciliation effected.
Hindus and Muslims are blood-brothers.
But on account of historical reasons their relationship has not been harmonious.
It shall be the endeavor of BJP to make all Indians fraternal and friendly once again.
BJP is no prisoner of any dogmas.
We will debureaucratise the Economy to maximise production.
We will make even the Sarkari Sector productive and profitable by throwing open some of the public sector units to people’s participation.
The BJP will modernise the country on the basis of Science and Technology, even while strengthening the cultural roots of our national life.
We want to do a thousand things to uplift the people and upgrade the country.
And we have the first Principles, the sound policies, the wise leadership and the dedicated cadres to do them and do them well.
Towards A Clean Political System From the Himalaya to Kanya Kumari, this country has always been one.
We have had many States, but we were always one people.
We always looked upon our country as Matribhoomi, Punyabhoomi.
The Atharva Veda says ‘Janarn bibhrati bahuda vivachasam’ -Nana Dharmanam Prithvi yathou kasam.’ (This our motherland gives equal protection to people speaking different languages and professing different faiths).
We have never had a theocracy, with a State Religion, in India.
In fact, it is not possible in India because of its inherent magnanimous cultural heritage.
This being our tradition there is no room for discrimination against anybody on grounds of caste, creed, language or region.
It is the duty of the state to ensure justice for all citizens and for all sections of society.
The Bharatiya Janata   Party is wedded to National Unity and National Integrity and a balanced development of all regions and all sections.
To these ends we will have, politically, not only a strong centre but also strong autonomous States.
Law And Constitution The polity will accordingly, be reformed along the following lines: BJP favours restructuring of Centre-State relations in view of the quick economic development and decentralisation.
BJP will implement the Sarkaria Committee Report on Centre-State relations; Article 356 permitting dissolution of a State Government by the Centre, will invoke only when the Constitutional machinery has in fact broken down and not to promote any partisan interest; The BJP recognises that regional imbalances have developed in some states because of their size.
The party would appoint a commission to report on formation of smaller states which are economically and democratically viable.
Initially BJP will have Uttranchal, Vananchal and Union Territory of Delhi as three new states of the Indian Union; Certain regions in some States have an acute sense of neglect.
These regions e.g.
Ladakh and Jammu in J & K State, and Marathwada and Vidarbha in Maharashtra – will be given Regional Development Councils; The States will be given a fairer share of Central revenues; We will appoint an Inter-state Council under Article 263 to settle all inter-state and State-centre disputes; We will delete the ‘temporary’ Article 370 from the Constitution, which more than anything else, psychologically separates J & K state from the rest of the country; Article 30 permits minorities to run their own schools.
It will be rationalised and suitably amended to ensure justice & equality to all irrespective of religions; We will guarantee to all minorities, whether religious or linguistic, peace and security and full opportunities for   3 and development; We will set up a commission to study and report whether the Presidential system of Government will give us a more stable Government than the present Parliamentary system; BJP will examine the feasibility of introducing list system; We will appoint a Law Commission to study various Civil Laws.
ancient, medieval and modern, to evolve a Common Civil Law for the whole country to give our citizens a feeling of unity and brotherhood; We will maintain a National Register of citizens; In place of the minorities commission and which entertains complaints of discrimination only from minority sections.
We will have a Human Rights Commission to look into complaints of injustice against any section of society.
Fair Elections Free and fair elections are the life-breath of democracy.
From time to time there are reports of doctored electoral rolls, booth- capturing, physical violence.
Money power and muscle power have assumed sinister proportions.
To restore health to our electoral system we will: Arrange for public funding of elections; Introduce identity cards with photographs for all voters; Replace ballot boxes by electronic voting machines, to prevent rigging and booth-capturing; Give the right of vote by postal ballot to Indian citizens living abroad; Permit company donations to parties – until State funding is introduced, to keep black money out of the political process; Strengthen the independence of the Election Commission by making its expenditure a charge on the Consolidated Fund of India – as is the case with the Comptroller and Auditor General and the Supreme Court and various High Courts; Hold State Assembly and Lok Sabha Elections simultaneously and regularly every five years, avoiding, as far as possible, any mid-term polls;   Give legal teeth to the Election Commission’s Code of Conduct by making violation of the same a corrupt practice under the Election Law; Empower the Election Commission to, monitor Akashvani and Doordarshan broadcasts and ensure that the same are not misused for any partisan purposes; Fix a realistic limit on a candidate’s election expenses and then include in it not only the money spent by him but also by his party and friends; and Introduce public auditing of party funds.
Shri Ram Mandir At Janamsthan BJP firmly believes that construction of Shri Ram Mandir at Jamnasthan is a symbol of the vindication of our cultural heritage and national self respect.
For BJP it is purely a national issue and it will not allow any vested interests to give it a sectarian and communal colour.
Hence party is committed to build Shri Ram Mandir at Janmasthan by relocating super imposed Babri structure with due respect.
Clean Public Life BJP attaches the greatest importance to the probity and quality of public life.
To this end we will Inquire into all cases of serious corruption in high places; Require all those holding public office to make an annual declaration of their own and their dependents’ assets; Set an example in simple living, to give a new, higher tone to public life.
North-east We have long had many problems in the North-East beginning with Naga insurgency.
And now we have a Bodo problem and also the ULFA problem in Assam proper.
BJP will examine outstanding regional and sectional problems, redress all legitimate grievances and, for the rest maintain law and order with a firm hand.
To this end we will Have electrified barbed wiring all along the Indo- Bangladesh border, to keep infiltrators out;   3 .
Check and identify infiltrators, strike out their names from the electoral rolls and arrange to send them back to Bangladesh; Declare all property deals between locals and infiltrators as null and void; Give all adult citizens in the North-East identity cards with photographs, on a priority basis; To monitor and keep watch on receipt of foreign funds so that it is not used for conversion in the garb of religious activities; Abolish the Inner Line Permit System in all the seven North Eastern States; Safeguard the interests of bonafide refugees fleeing because of religious or political persecution in Bangladesh; Secure the honourable return of Chakmas to Chittagong Hills, Bangladesh; Plan and organise an integrated and accelerated economic development of the North-East; and Incorporate Manipur and Nepali in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution.
Punjab The BJP holds Cong.
(I) wholly responsible for the Punjab problem.
Had the Congress Govt.
not toppled the duly elected Govermnents, of Prakash Singh Badal, not once, not twice, but three times, there would have been no Bindaranwale, no -Blue Star’, no ‘Black Thunder’.
Later, it was the loot and murder of thousands of innocent Sikhs in Delhi and else-where in 1984 that has angered the Sikhs, given a handle to Pakistan and encouraged terrorism.
However, the fact that not all the machinations of Pakistan and not all the provocations of their terrorist agents, has soured Hindu-Sikh relations, is proof positive that the heart of the Punjab is sound.
To mend matters in the Punjab, we will Create a kilometer-deep Security Belt all along the Indo- Pak border – as has already been done by Pakistan on its own side – to prevent all movement of terrorists, smugglers and their lethal cargo; Post Army Units in the acutely disturbed border areas to   maintain order and restore confidence; Give relief and provide rehabilitation to the widows and orphans of 1984 outrages; Punish the guilty men of the 1984 terror; and Have the various grievances of the people of Punjab examined in depth by experts, including social scientists and redress them suitably.
Jammu, Kashmir And Ladakh The BJP views with concern the recent developments in the Kashmir valley.
Widespread violence in the State has led to an anarchical situation.
This has paralysed tourism, the backbone of the Kashmir economy.
The Pakistan – inspired violence against Hindus has caused those Kashmiris to become refugees in their own land.
The BJP will Weed out Pakistani elements from the valley; Hold free and fair elections in the State as soon as conditions stabilise there; Have separate Regional Development Councils for Jammu and Ladakh; Make relief and rehabilitation facilities available to Kashmiri refugees, settling them particularly in the hills of Pir Panjal Range; and End all uncertainty about the future status of the State by deleting Article 370 of the Constitution.
Telangana Ever since the Razakar excesses in 1947-48 and the Communist rebellion in 1948-50, the Telangana area of Andhra Pradesh has been more or less disturbed.
In the last few years, People’s War Group, a Naxalite outfit, has been virtually running a state within a state there.
The Congress (I) and T.D.P.
have been competing for the support of P.W.G., which has been holding people to ransom and killing scores of BJP men, and anybody else who would stand up to them.
BJP will go to the root of the Telangana land problem and, for the rest, crush the lawless elements and restore law and order.
3 Under Congress (I) mismanagement, even a peaceful State like Assam has produced a terrorist outfit like ULFA.
Here again, BJP will redress legitimate grievances and for the rest, discipline unruly elements and restore order.
Law and Order The BJP views with concern the alarming rise in social violence, involving different castes and communities.
All this violence is mainly due to exciting feelings to carve out certain Vote Banks and then cornering them.
The party expects the District Administration to take all steps necessary to maintain Law and Order.
Should there still be any serious eruption of violence, BJP will Institute an inquiry; Publish the findings of such an inquiry; Punish the guilty; Compensate the victims; and Transform the Police Machinery into an efficient and dependable instrument of Law and Order.
Justice And Judicial Reform In a situation of rapid social change, the judiciary holds a pivotal place.
It can ease social tensions by dispensing quick, inexpensive and impartial justice.
We are sorry to note that on all these counts the Judiciary’s performance has been less than exemplary, particularly since the Congress (I) came up with the ploy of a committed judiciary, that is a Judiciary committed to the ruling party.
To stop further erosion of this hallowed institution, and restore it to its earlier state, the BJP will Take suitable measures to clear the arrears; Through suitable measures BJP will ensure the cases, by the large, are decided within one year; Discourage interminable adjournment of cases for years on end; Improve the emoluments of judges to attract better talent; Raise the retirement age of High Court Judges to 65 – that of the lower judiciary to 60; Give attractive pensions to judges;   Enhance judicial powers of Nyaya Panchayats to ensure speedy justice and to carry to the doorstep of the people; Provide mobile courts for the rural areas; To provide free legal aid to SC and ST to enable them to procure their rights and position as SC and ST; and The role of executive in judicial appointment will be rationalised to keep it within the framework of spirit of the Constitution.
Panchayati Raj And People’s Power The Panchayat system formed the bedrock of the democratic, social and political set-up in India since Vedic times.
It was this democratic set-up that absorbed the shock of invasions and protected the integrity of Indian life.
In modern times Gandhiji commended ‘Power to the People’ in a ‘structure composed of innumerable villages’ in which there will be ‘ever-widening, never-ending circles.
Life will not be a pyramid with apex sustained by the bottom but it will be an oceanic circle whose centre will be the individual.’ Lok Nayak Jaya Prakash Narayan also worked for Panchayati Raj and Deendayalji pleaded for a statutory status for the village Panchayat and the city municipality – in the Constitution.
The BJP will Effectively decentralise power; Give a constitutional status to local bodies from Village Panchayats to Metropolitan City Corporations; and Involve the Panchayats in all rural development work and make 10 per cent of the Development Budget directly available to them.
Economic Growth With Social Justice The Indian economy has reached a point of total collapse as a result of the knock-out blows it has been dealt, by a succession of profligate and irresponsible governments led by Congressmen and ex-Congressmen.
These people have literally robbed the country and left its hapless citizens high and dry, staggering from one crisis to another and trapped in a rising vortex of high prices, murderous taxes and soaring debts.
The nation is on the verge of bankruptcy and has been reduced to begging for hand-outs from all and sundry.
Indian ambassadors go abroad to beg for loans and even the Prime Minister has to genuflect   3 heads of foreign nations.
As a result India’s international rating has sunk to a new low.
India is one of the few countries in the world without a proper government, without a proper budget and without a proper economic policy.
The net result is an upside-down economy in which farmers who produce cotton cannot afford to buy cloth; and masons who put up five-star hotels, have no roofs over their heads.
For certain consumer durable there is no dearth of demand.
It is estimated that 60 per cent of the consumer durables are purchased by less than 40 cent of the population.
In other words, the Developmental effort during the past four decades has resulted in a Socio-Economic dualism.
All these trends have to be reversed, and the Bharatiya Janata Party will reverse them.
BJP government will ‘ bring out White paper on State of the Economy soon after assuming power.
The core sector of our economy will be MAN.
State should retreat from commercial activities and instead, concentrate on basic functions such as maintaining law and order, justice, welfare programme, infrastructure etc.
We will make our Economy truly Swadeshi by promoting native initiatives.
It will be an Economy of the People, by the People and for the People.
Through our pragmatic Economic strategy we promise to: Hold the Price Line; Liberate the Economy from the clutches of the bureaucratic controls; Not to hike Excise Duties on items of mass consumption for five years and indeed, rationalise the whole tax structure; Reduce non-plan expenditure drastically.
Balance the Revenue Budget (Zero budgetary deficit under Revenue Account) and reduce the overall debt burden; Ensure development of Rural Economy with remunerative prices to the farmer and network of agro-based industries; Make Public Sector productive and profitable, invite equity participation in some of the public sector units with adequate safeguards; Use Science, Technology and native wisdom to raise annual growth rate of Economy from around 5 per cent at present to 7.5 per cent;   Create a full fledged Ministry for Handicrafts and Village Industries; Implement Antyodaya scheme throughout the country; and Launch a nation-wide Employment Guarantee Scheme.
Agriculture: Integrated Rural Development Agriculture is our First Priority.
The Indian peasant is the salt of the earth and he is the backbone of the country’s economy.
When he prospers, India prospers.
We have waived the loam of poor agriculturists in Madhya Pradesh, Himachal Pradesh and Rajasthan.
But the Kisan win continue to flounder in poverty unless the burden of people depending on agriculture is reduced.
A countrywide network of agro-industrial complexes in rural areas should relieve the burden and provide the real answer to the problem of poverty of the peasantry.
BJP aims at rural development where farmer will not be forced to borrow.
The party has offered a new deal to the farmers in terms of its Charter of Rights of Kisan.
The party will Ensure remunerative prices-to farmers; Ensure minimum wages to the farm labour; Ensure abundant supply of water and energy, the farmers have a natural right on these basic inputs; Remove all restrictions on the movement of farm produce throughout the country; Maintain parity of prices between agricultural and industrial products; Issue Pass Books to Kisans and Implement the land laws; Allocate 60 per cent of the plan money, both central and state, for rural development; Encourage cultivation of pulses, oil-seeds, course grains, fruits, vegetables and other cash crops; Speedily complete on-going irrigation projects, organise efficient flood management and relief; Launch a million small, labour-intensive rural projects.
Cluster of agro-centers would be promoted which would take up activities directly relating to agriculture and also meet other requirements of villagers.
This would help to   3 employment to rural youths who are not actually required in agricultural activities.
e.g.
Scientific storage facilities, food processing units, cottage industries etc.
Investment in rural industries will be given appropriate fiscal incentives; Introduce cattle and crop insurance schemes and also update the old Famine Code; Improve roads and other means of communication to facilitate quick transportation of agricultural and horticultural produce to towns; Provide market value compensation in case of land acquisition in one installment, and provide jobs to those uprooted in the process; Protect the traditional rights of villagers in Gochar Bhoomi and Nistar land; Make Water, Power, a School and a Health Centre available in all villages; and Restructure the Agriculture Cost and Price Commission and make it more broad-based, with adequate representation to those engaged in farming.
Cow Protection And Cattle Wealth The BJP recognises the fact that from times immemorial, cow- protection has remained one of the basics of Indian culture and Indian agriculture, and it is on the patient back of the cow and its progeny that the entire structure of Indian agriculture rests.
Over seventy million animals are employed in farming operations in Indian villages, more than eighty percent rural transport needs are met by the bullock-cart.
Cow and its progeny continue to be the major source of power, manure and fuel, including bio-gas.
Cow is also an effective protection against environmental degradation.
The BJP regretfully observes that about three million cows are slaughtered every year, most of them for export.
The party would put a total ban on the slaughter of cows.
It will Amend article 48 of Constitution to cover bulls and bullocks, and prohibit all trading (state as well as private) in the slaughter of cows; Implement a policy of Go-Samvardhan or development   of cow and cattle-breeding, including the improvement of sheep and goat breeds, to bring about a White Revolution in the country; and Provide tax exemption to the income of Goshalas and Pinjarapoles.
Industrial Policy Industry in India has to be much more productive and innovative to be able to fulfill its main role viz provide employment in increasing numbers and inputs to other sectors, including agriculture.
It has also to earn foreign exchange competition with the rest of the world and create resources for overall growth.
The BJP promises healthy investment environment so that entrepreneurs find domestic market as more attractive and challenging.
The following four main principles will characterise the industrial policy of the BJP— A. Self-reliance: The party regards self-reliance as an over-riding component in our external economic relations, including the import of capital and technology.
We will keep multinationals out of consumer industries.
B. Modernisation: BJP believes in a modern and progressive India.
Open to new ideas, no matter where they come from provided they suit our requirements and ethos.
We will not allow technology to degrade man.
Our people with their intelligence, industry and character are the true and abiding wealth of India.
C. Decentralisation: There is far too much power concentrated in the Government, and it must be decentralised.
The party stands for political as well as economic democrac, as also for an open society, where the government has only an indicative and not a commanding role.
It will not be necessary for people to come to Delhi and waste time and money over licences and other clearances.
3 .
Daridra Narayan Sewa: Consistent with the above three principles, the party will aim at securing to every Indian citizen a minimum of material welfare in terms of food, clothing.
shelter health and education.
The BJP pledges to: Debureaucratise the industry, cut down the plethora of controls which have mushroomed over the years, and which breed corruption and dampen enterp rise.
We will clear projects promptly and quickly.
Industrial Development and regulations Act will be replaced by Industrial Development Act; Reconsider the role of the public sector in the light of its contribution to development and society and draw up firm guidelines for its re-organisation into a more efficient, productive, profitable and people-oriented sector; Improve the efficiency and profitability of crucial Public Sector Units like Railways, oil and gas production, ports, Nuclear Energy, Defence, etc.
through better management; Encourage people’s initiative in Public Sector Units involving trading, hotels, tourism, consumer goods, etc., by offering them to the public in capital market with appropriate safeguards; Foster Swadeshi spirit in every economic and industrial activity and reduce the country’s dependence on foreign countries and foreign agencies.
Foreign capital will be encouraged in high-tech, import substitution and strictly export oriented areas.
Within the set guidelines clearance will be given with minimum paperwork.
Promote agro-based industries; Apply MRTP to business houses with assets value crossing ₹ 1,000 crore and more; or with more than one-third of the market share; Encourage research and development as part of the process of industrial growth and over-all modernisation; Encourage business men to function as trustees of the public good; Hazardous industries will be allowed to set up at safe distance.
Separate industrial satellites would be set up   exclusively for such units; Protect our Economic Sovereignty and ensure that the existing Patent laws, which safeguard Indian national interest, remain intact under any external pressure; Small-scale sector will be given due importance and encouragement.
We shall set up agencies to help small- scale industry which will help in purchasing raw materials and selling finished goods; BJP government will evolve national management cadre.
Both public sector as well as private sector will draw their requirements from this cadre; and While conducive environment will be created to strengthen capital market adequate measures will be taken to safe- guard interests of small equity holders.
Handicrafts & Village Industries: To Play Pivotal Role BJP firmly believes that national goals such as employment generation, export earnings could be met through our ancient craftmanship such as handloom & handicrafts, gems & jewelry etc.
For instance, investment of ₹ one crore in village industries creates job opportunities for 202 persons while the same investment in organised industrial sector can provide job to only 48 persons.
Besides, more than 40 per cent of our export earnings comes from these so called smaller initiatives.
BJP pledges to recognise their importance in the national economy and look at them with enhanced expectations.
A separate ministry will be set up to look after interests of Handicrafts and village industries.
To preserve and promote native Craftmanship ‘National Artisan Development Bank’ would be set up.
Government would contribute the necessary initial capital of this bank.
These native artisans will be made to feel proud of themselves with due recognition in the society.
Attempt will be made to bring them together under cluster of artisans.
Native Artisans such a weavers, goldsmiths, blacksmiths, carpenters, shoemakers, potters etc.
Will be provided with basic amenities such as housing.
3 .
Processing units, marketing facilities, marketing consultancy etc.
will be provided so that native artisans will get remunerative returns for their special skill, which at present is exploited by middlemen.
Similarly skill of tribal people will receive special attention.
In government media such as T.V.
native of artisans will get adequate coverage without fees.
Fiscal Reform The current economic mess is a direct consequence of the mismanagement of the economy by the government.
While the government controls everyone and everything, nobody seems to control the government.
BJP believes that the government too must function within the limits of strict financial discipline—on the following lines (i) The Government must live within its means.
Revenue Budgetary Deficits will be reduced to Zero and fiscal deficits will be brought down from 9 per cent to 5 per cent of Gross Domestic Product.
BJP believes in imposing a statutory ceiling on budget deficits in order to restrain government spending; (ii) At present the Reserve Bank has structural autonomy.
BJP Govt.
will ensure operational autonomy of RBI: BJP will adopt firm and bold measures to prevent the generation of black money.
It will also appoint a Taxation Inquiry Commission to suggest guidelines for taxation over a long-term period in line with future developments; Rationalise and simplify, the present tax structure, and bring down the highest rate of income tax to 40 per cent; Raise the income Tax exemption limit to ₹ 48,000; Weighted deductions will be provided taking number of dependents on earning member; Exempt all investments in approved organisations, private or public from the levy of Wealth tax; Exempt employment-oriented industries in non- municipal areas from income tax;   Abolish octroi duty and persuade state governments to make good the loss of municipalities; Arrange uniform sales tax rates throughout the country.
Loss in revenue will be compensated by the Centre; Impose Estate Duty on property and assets worth more than ₹ One Crore; Share Corporation Tax with the states; Give special tax concessions to writers, artists, and others engaged in intellectual and cultural pursuits; Non-developmental expenditure will be curtailed drastically; and Take stringent measures against smugglers and other economic offenders.
Make smuggling a non-bailable offence and appoint special courts to try such cases.
Price Stability And Consumer Protection It is our firm belief that price level could be controlled only through minimisation of production and minimisation of cost of production through technology upgradation.
Besides, by abolishing deficits on Revenue account and cutting capital account deficits to half, the BJP will end inflation and stabilise prices.
Additionally we will Public distribution system would be streamlined so that needy sections of the society would have access to essential commodities at nominal prices.
Under the present system, poorest section is forced o buy essential items on open market.
Poor daily wage earners who have to make their purchases at the end of the day cannot afford purchases once in a fortnight or so.
Public distribution system will be overhauled to help these sections; Make not only grains, sugar and kerosene, but also pulses, cooking oil and soap available in these shops; Enforce the Consumer Protection Act of 1986, specially by constituting Consumers’ Courts in all districts; and Build a powerful consumer movement and formulate a price and profit policy for industrially manufactured goods.
3 Policy The BJP recognises the citizen’s Right to Work in principle.
We shall make every endeavour to accomplish its objectives.
Our many developmental policies that will nearly double the Growth Rate, will take good care of unemployment— Launch Employment Guarantee Scheme throughout the country in a phased manner; Introduce a contributory Family Pension Scheme to cover particularly the daily wage earner; and Implement Antyodaya Scheme to serve the poorest in the land.
Labour BJP believes in healthy trade unionism.
It will Rationalise and simplify Labour Laws; Recognise unions on the basis of secret ballot; Introduce worker participation from the Shop Floor to the Board Room in all public sector projects, public limited companies and foreign companies operating in India; Protect workers against inflation; and Make laws, and evolve an effective mechanism, to protect labour from occupational health hazards arising from industries like asbestos, cement, slate, mica chemicals, textiles, etc.
Government Employees BJP will set up a permanent Employees Welfare Board with a view to resolving the long-standing problems related to— Time Scale Promotion; Implementation of Awards; Recruitment avenues; Housing; Revision of Pay Scales and award of bonus; and Social welfare measures and travel concession for retired personnel.
Energy Policy There is acute energy crisis in India, particularly in villages which have remained without any dependable source of energy even after forty four years of Independence.
This situation will have to be tackled on a war footing.
BJP will Intensify efforts to find more oil, coal and natural gas reserves, and economies on their use; Improve the working of power plants which are now functioning at less than 50 per cent of capacity; Stop the massive theft of electric power; Introduce power-efficient, energy-saving devices in homes and factories; Increase forest cover from the present 19 per cent of land to the desired 33 per cent; Encourage Private Sector’s participation in power generation; and Encourage alternative sources of energy such as wind, water, biogas, solar power and ocean thermal energy conversion.
Transport Policy Speedy movement of goods and people will receive utmost attention.
In this regard, the whole country will be considered as a single zone.
Metropolitan cities like Delhi will be provided with better transport system; Public Transport system will be improved so as to attract marginal personal vehicle owners.
This will help to reduce demand for energy.
Simultaneously, environmental pollution could be controlled; Utmost attention will be paid towards development of Inter modal Transport System.
This would mean integrated development of all modes of transport such as roads and road transport, railways, ports and shipping; Inland water transport system will be fully tapped; and Air transport system will be overhauled not only to improve operational efficiency but also to take care of safety elements.
Entrepreneurs will be encouraged to come   3 in air transport.
Foreign Made And Balance Of Payments Under the current balance of payments crisis foreign trade plays an important role.
Export promotion and Import rationalisation receive due attention of BJP government— Thrust would be given to promotion of exports and intensive effort would be made to identify alternative markets and also thrust commodities; Required infrastructural support would be provided on priority basis to export oriented units; At the same time import would be rationalised and restricted to those items which are absolutely essential; Corporate sector would have to fulfill its export obligation specially if its production is import intensive; Balance of trade would have to be maintained on unit by unit basis.
Right now, performance of the corporate sector is not satisfactory in this respect; Under-invoicing of exports and over-invoicing of imports will be strictly dealt with; Excellency in export performance will receive special recognition; It is estimated that 12 million Indians settled in over 100 countries save around 100 billion U.S. dollars a year.
Scheme would be drawn to attract substantial portion of these savings; NRIs would be welcome to set up Industrial units.
‘Science Based Industrial Parks’ would be set up which would cater of the NRIs not only with regard to infrastructural facilities required for their industrial units but would also be complete with basic amenities such as education, housing, health care and entertainment.
This would help us to raise resources as well as reversing the brain-drain; The present principle of linking Indian rupee to basket of currencies will be re-examined; and Tourism will get special attention.
Science And Technology The BJP believes that Science and Technology (S & T) should be allowed to play its due role to transform India into a prosperous, modern and enlightened society.
The party would unhesitatingly apply appropriate scientific and technological methods for increasing productivity, eradicating poverty, hunger and disease and to provide meaningful employment along with the basic amenities of life to the vast percentage of population living below the poverty line.
The party holds that science is not merely harnessing nature for material wealth but is as well liberating and enriching mind and enlarging the human spirit.
The BJP would use science in the service of the poor and would develop technology with a human face— Foster a scientific temper among the people; Use Science and Technology for increasing productivity and generating employment; Implement a vigorous programme of science education and research for improving quality of life; Establish a network of Centres for Application of Science and Technology to rural areas, implement lab to land programmes and develop a strong low cost agro-industrial base; Put new life in National Laboratories.
develop them as centres of excellence in applied research; Direct these laboratories to evolve Appropriate Technology for Indian needs; Accelerate the production of scientific literature in regional languages and evolve a national terminology for science and technology; and Create the right working conditions, for our best brains to remain here and serve the country and not migrate to other lands.
A systematised effort would be made to bring national laboratories and industry together by setting up of ‘Technology Parks’ which would be maintained by the industry.
They would help to bridge the gap between talents and commercial needs and promotes co-operation between industry’s resources and expertise in labs.
3 A Vibrant Social Order The Bharatiya Janata Party looks upon people of India’s true wealth and strength of the country.
Since the majority of people of India live in the cluster of Villages BJP will give special attention to their welfare and progress.
To this end we will Carry water and electricity to every village; Connect all villages to national centres of activities by road transport; Upgrade village health and educational centres; Train and equip village artisans; Recognise People’s traditional rights in Gochar Bhoomi grazing, local forests and forest products, and fishing in local water resources; and Make living conditions in the countryside, more attractive and honourable to check huge influx of villages towards cities.
Salaried People The salarised people find themselves pressed hard between fixed incomes and rising prices.
We will; Encourage all employees – private and public – to provide housing for their staff; Exempt salaried incomes of upto ₹ 4000 a month, from income tax; and Increase the return on General Provident Fund deposits.
Senior Citizens Elderly people who have served the country all their lives, will be taken good care of.
We will Require the private sector also to introduce pension schemes; Grant pensioners the same DA relief as available to serving staff; and Build Homes for old aged people.
Jai Jawan Jawans must be assured of service upto 58 years of age;   Implement the policy of one pension for one rank under a time bound programme; Make necessary changes in agricultural and urban Tenancy Laws to secure the proprietary rights of servicemen; Include ex-servicemen’s welfare in the concurrent list; Strengthen District Sainik Boards; and Start more Sainik schools.
Sindhis Sindhis are the only community in India to have lost their entire territory as a result of Partition.
The Party assures the Sindhi Community of protection and promotion of their identity, culture, language and literature and fulfillment of constitutional guarantees enshrined in Article 350A and 350B of the Constitution of India.
Women BJP looks upon womankind as Matri-Shakti.
It will take several steps to improve their socio-economic status.
We will Give preferences to women as primary school teachers; Make women equal share-holders in the husband’s wealth and income; Strengthen family courts, presided over by Women-judges to try all family-related cases; Get women equal pay for equal work; Start more and more Hostels for single working women; Provide Smoke-less chulhas at concessional rates to village women; Put up public latrines for village women as well as for women living in slum areas; Appoint a Commission to study problems of women, particularly women labourers and suggest suitable remedial measures; and Promote ₹ 100 crore a year cottage industry to employ rural women.
Youth The BJP has a tryst with the Youth of India.
They will be the fly-wheel of national progress.
Apart from organising their   3 and full employment, BJP will Utilise their energies to transform society; Associate them in all developmental activities; Mobilise them to fight social evils like child marriage, dowry, untouchability, drug-addiction; Build more Youth hostels; and Inculcate in them a sense of pride in our traditions and heritage and confidence in our future.
Scheduled Castes And Scheduled Tribes The BJP sincerely believes with all its heart in the upliftment of SC and ST. To this end we will Energetically enforce anti-untouchability laws; Make free legal aid available to SC in cases under these laws; Make all village wells available to all castes and communities; Set up a financial agency on the line of NABARD to cater to the credit needs of SC & ST; Promptly fill up the shortfall in jobs reserved for SC and ST; A befitting memorial would be constructed in honour of Dr. Ambedkar; Evolve a new forest policy based on a partnership between the forest tribals and the forest authorities; Protect SC and ST for exploitation and indebtedness; Formulate a sub-plan for the economic development of Scheduled Tribes; and Remove all impediments in the speedy development of hill and forest tribal areas.
Other Backward Castes The BJP is pledged to the socio-economic uplift of Other Backward Castes particularly the more backward among them.
BJP in its 1985 resolution and subsequently in its 1989 Election Manifesto commended the following reservation policy: Reservation should be continued for the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes as before;   Reservation should also be made for other backward classes broadly on the basis of the Mandal Commission Report, with preference to be given to the poor among these very classes; and As poverty is an important contributory factor for backwardness, reservation should also be provided for members of the other castes on the basis of their economy condition.
In view of the shocking manner in which the National Front government implemented the Mandal Commission Report which resulted in self-immolation of youths and pitted caste against caste and community against community.
BJP feels that the reservation policy should be introduced taking into consideration socio-economic ethos.
Reservation policy should be used as an instrument of social justice and promoting social harmony as well.
The question of reservation has to be viewed with open mind free from all prejudices of any kind.
In addition BJP Will start a chain of first class residential schools where the really bright children of really poor families of all castes and communities will be admitted, educated and otherwise looked after, to come into their own and enter Services, Business and Professions in open competition; Most of the non-agricultural OBCs are artisans.
Foreign and metropolitan competition has hurt these people badly.
BJP will train and equip them, so that they can find a place of honour in the new social economy.
The Destitute And Handicapped BJP will not forget the destitute and the handicapped.
It will not allow anybody to starve.
Antyodaya Scheme will take care of destitutes.
We will encourage people to set up institutions for the care of the physically handicapped and mentally retarded and make certain jobs available for them.
3 Policy The Bharatiya Janata Party believes in a stable growth of the Population — and the quality, physcial and mental, of that Population.
We will, therefore: Adopt a National Population Policy, if necessary through legislative measures; Make Family Planning information and facilities available to the people.
Involve all voluntary, social and cultural organisations in creating an awareness for adopting family planning as a way of life; Integrate the family planning programme with other community welfare programmes; and Pursue vigorously the voluntary adaptation of the ‘two children’ norm through adequate incentives and disincentives for achieving the long term demographic goals.
Environment The Bharatiya Janata Party takes serious note of the degradation of the environment and disturbance of the eco-system.
The pollution of air, water and soil are a serious menace to health.
The denudation of forests, the warming up of the earth, acid rain and the ‘hole in the sky’ are a threat to the whole life-system itself.
We in India have always looked upon the earth as Divine Mother.
Our land air and waters, our hills, forests flora and fauna, are all sacred to us.
We will keep them neat, clean and intact.
We will Formulate a National Resources Management Policy and adopt a holistic approach in planning; Require anti-pollution devices to be installed to process and clean up industrial and Municipal effluents before the same are discharged into our rivers; Keep a strict watch on chemical fertilizers and insecticides for any poisoning of the soil, and ban DDT etc; Improve auto exhaust to prevent the fouling of the air; Curb noise pollution especially in the cities; Undertake a massive afforestation programme; While protecting the traditional rights of Vanavas is, we will require the planting of three trees for every single   tree that is cut by anybody for any reason; Make environmental concerns an integral part of education; and Take special care in the import of technology, and promote research, for developing indigenous pollution-free technology.
Culture The BJP believes in protecting, preserving and promoting the cultural heritage of India that has given us an identity, an integrity and an aura all our own.
We will Conserve the ancient heritage of lndia and make people feel proud of it; We shall set up cultural heritage centres at District levels; Acquaint people with the glorious traditions and achievements of ancient Indian genius in the fields of art, science, technology, medicine, agriculture, etc; Wage a relentless war against superstition; Emphasise culture as a dynamic and synthetic process; and Not ban any publication without a prior judicial review.
Arts Art is the essence of life.
BJP will encourage all forms of art.
It will make the various arts a part of Education, Production and Life.
To promote the theatre BJP will repeal the restrictive Dramatic Performance Act of 1876; and Exempt all theatrical performances from entertainment tax; Encourage folk art in various fields; Lift the AIR and TV ban on the use of classical symbols like Om, Swastika, Sri chakra, etc.
Films BJP recognises the great role of cinema in entertainment, education and national integration.
BJP will: Have, in addition to’A’ and ‘U’ Films, ‘Q’ that is Quality films, which will be exempt from entertainment tax; Have special theatres in metropolitan centres to screen art   3 and other quality films; Implement the recommendation of the Karanth Committee on National Film Policy; and Have 50 per cent women on Film Censor Board – to keep violence and vulgarity out of films.
Tourism The BJP recognises the importance of tourism as an instrument of national integration, international understanding and employment generation.
India abounds in natural beauty and charming tourist spots, which have fascinated people from far and wide.
We will Promote tourism, both national and international, as an industry; Evolve a policy of integrating tourism and marketing of handicrafts and other art works; Take up a scheme of training tourist guides and opening tourist information centres; and Build Holiday Homes in the hills, on sea beaches and at pilgrim centres.
Mass Media The BJP re-affirms its commitment to the freedom of thought and expression.
We will Make freedom of the Press an explicit Fundamental Right, and not just an implied one, derived from the citizen’s right to Freedom of Speech; Encourage the healthy growth of the Press and abolish duty on newsprint and the tax on newspaper advertising; Review the Official Secrets Act as to remove obstruction in Right to know, and enact a Freedom of Information Law; Implement the P.C.
Joshi Report on TV software to improve the quality of TV programmes; Implement the Prasar Bharati Act to make Akashvani and Dor Darshan autonomous and credible and; make second channels available to public trusts as well as programmes by non-governmental agencies so as to promote competition; and Screen Ramayana, Mahabharat, Bhagwat and other Epics   and classics in various Indian languages.
The Quality Of Life Man does not live by bread alone.
He must also have health and faith, housing and education, sport and a wholesome environment.
Housing BJP will adopt all policies necessary to make it possible for every family to own a house.
To this end it will Make land available to cooperative group housing societies; Encourage employers, private and public, to build houses for their employees; Build low-cost model houses in villages; Clear slum areas and build multi-storey buildings on the spot to house their present residents; Rationalise Rent Control Laws.
to encourage housing construction and house renting; Stamp duties and such other formalities will be rationalised so as to encourage low and middle income classes to own dwelling units; and Progressively develop all urban centres as Garden Cities.
Education The party view with concern that with the rising cost of education, the existing socio-economic disparities will be perpetuated in the field of education.
The BJP believes in equalisation of educational opportunities and build up a system worthy of the genius of our heritage and the undoubted capacities of our youth.
Towards this end, we will Implement Article 45 of the Constitution to give free education to all children in the 6-14 age group to enforce the principle of universal primary education; Give education a vocational and technical content, establish a complex of agro-industrial polytechnics in each districts; Ensure academic freedom and the autonomy of universities, raise the emoluments and status of teachers; and Progressively increase the allocation for education till it reaches the six percent of the GNP.
3 The BJP supports the principle that people have a right to be educated and run their administration in their own language.
The BJP will Engage adequate number of linguists all over the country to translate standard literature of other languages into Indian languages; Strictly implement three languages formula; Give credit – in the matter of admission to institutions of higher education and in job recruitment – to persons knowing more than three languages, Indian or Foreign; and Encourage study of Sanskrit.
Health And Nutrition Every citizen must be helped to have a healthy body and a healthy mind.
The BJP will Integrate Ayurveda, Siddha, Unani, Homeopathy, Chromopathy, Flower Remedies and Nature Cure with Allopathy, to give the country an Integrated and Holistic Medical system; Retrieve, compile and publish ancient wisdom about health, herbs and other remedies; Encourage Yogasanas in every school; Give an annual medical check-up to all students; Increase production of proteinous foods, in view of the under-nourishment of our own people; Increase milk production – to give the country a White Revolution; Give every village a Health Care Centre with particular emphasis on mother-and-child care and ratify the U.N. convention on the Rights of the children; Have a Mobile Dispensary in each Taluka; Organise Eye Camps and Camps for other serious ailments in various areas; Take adequate measures to promote production of poor man’s grains like Jowar, Bajra and Ragi; Replace the 60,000 brand-name drugs by 250 generic   formulations; and Ban amniocentesis – sex determination tests – often leading to female foeticide.
Sports BJP will encourage sports as the way of health, strength and the sheer joy of living.
We will put India on the Olympic map of the world.
We will Create a Ministry of Health, Nutrition and Sports Help every school to have a playground; Provide coaching, training, diet and other facilities of international standards to our Sportmen; Encourage Tribal Youth living close to Nature, to participate and shine in the field of sports; Ensure college admission and job security to our athletics; and Respect the Olympic Charter and autonomy of the Sports bodies and prevent the governmentalisation or politicisation of Sports.
   3 World Fraternity In four decades of Freedom, India has had to face as many as four aggressions against our territory.
This is, in all conscience, a high degree of challenge to our territorial integrity and national sovereignty, with its consequential strains on the Indian Economy, the Indian Polity and the Indian society.
Diplomacy Like India, the world is also at cross roads.
With the sudden disappearance of bipolar divide of 45 years, the USSR and the US are no longer adversaries but partners.
Curtain has finally been drawn over the cold war that has dominated the world for most of the current century.
International equations are changing fast.
In the post cold war period, neither the USA needs the third world countries to contain communism nor does the USSR has any use now for its ‘natural allies’ in the developing world.
As a result.
non-alignment movement which was created against the backdrop of a bipolar world, has lost its relevance.
The new situation is a challenging one and at the same time pregnant with several fresh opportunities to enlarge India’s role in global affairs.
But only economically healthy, militarily strong and progressive India can carve out a niche for itself.
As long as India goes around with a begging bowl around the world, her voice in the international affairs will not be heard with respect.
Prevention is always better than cure.
That Defence is best that does not need to be invoked too often to defend our legitimate national interests.
And that, in turn calls for wise and integrated Domestic,, Economic and Foreign Polices.
In the past, our foreign   policy has suffered from inconsistencies.
At times we have treated it as an exercise in verbal gymnastics and used it as a, feather in a Prime Minister’s cap.
At other times we have treated it – as was the case only recently with the Gulf War — as a football, for irresponsible parties to kick it around.
We are sorry to note that Foreign Policy discussion and formulation has not been institutionalised in India.
As a result the performance of our diplomacy has been spotty at best.
Pakistan and China continue to occupy territories lawfully ours.
Thousands of Tibetans continue to live in India as refugees.
The Pakistan Establishment is hostile, and even the Bangladesh Establishment has been less than friendly.
The situation in Afghanistan has fortunately stabilised.
But the situation in Sri Lanka is as disturbed as ever, with serious violence erupting on both sides of the Palk straits.
Burmans next door continue to suffer dictatorship.
And Indians abroad continue to suffer discrimination in many lands.
The BJP is wedded to National interest and World Peace.
To these ends we will Set up a Policy Planning Committee of experts to formulate a long-term Foreign Policy for India; Forge a national Consensus on Foreign Policy issues; Work for a stronger SAARC in view of the old bipolar world giving place to a uni-polar World; Invite Pakistan to come forward to resolve out disputes in terms of the Shimla Pact and meanwhile develop cooperative economic and media relations; Promote the idea of a Common Market of all SAARC states; Constitute a South Asian Environmental Protection Authority, with representation from non-governmental environmentalists from all concerned countries; Continue the North-South Dialogue and promote South- South cooperation; Develop friendly and cordial relations with the countries of South-East Asia, with whom we have ancient bonds of blood and culture; Stand by persons of Indian origin abroad in defence of their legitimate rights; Give Dual Citizenship to Indian citizens abroad; and   3 .
Strive to strengthen United Nations in view of the fact in the changed situation the world powers are more inclined to work-through the UN than unilaterally or even through older groups and factions.
Strive to make India an autonomous power centre in the world with a permanent seat in the U.N. Security Council.
Defence Diplomacy and Defence are two sides of the same coin, that is a country’s relation with the outside world.
A sound Foreign Policy will give us a secure base for a sound Defence policy.
However, recent events have shown that international relations continue to be governed by the law of the jungle.
The way Iraq occupied Kuwait and USA exceeded the UN resolutions to bring death and destruction to both Kuwait and Iraq is a warning that we cannot afford to neglect our Defence.
The BJP will Encourage an educated debate on national strategy as a route to national security strategy; Set up a National Security Council to institutionalize forward planning; Give our Defence Forces Nuclear Teeth; Give ourselves a Blue Water Navy that will be the first Navy in the Indian Ocean from Singapore to Aden; Encourage Research and further Development on Arjun battle tank, Light Combat Aircraft, Army Radio Engineering Network (AREN) and Prithvi and other missiles developed by Dr. Abdul Kalam; Identify and eliminate foreign lobbies engaged in arms trade; Effect economic even while improving Defence capability; Avoid unnecessary duplication and merge paramilitary forces like BSF, Assam Rifles, Indo-Tibetan Border Police with the Army and the Coast Guard with the Navy; and Liberalise the Official Secret Act to facilitate an intelligent debate on defence.
Invite This then is the programme which the BJP pledges to implement under a team of inspiring and brilliant leaders and dedicated cadres of the party of impeccable record of clean public life and   selfless service to the nation.
The party is committed to usher in a new political culture.
India today is in the grip of a serious multi-dimensional crisis of unprecedented proportions.
The national mood is not just of cynicism but of mounting disgust and rage, not unmixed with sorrow at the steady deterioration in public morality at the topmost leadership level.
The people feel sad that through an accident of history this great country should have been saddled with a coterie of small men who are not only incompetent and corrupt, but who lack a sense of commitment to the nation, its democratic institutions and cultural traditions.
In the opinion of the BJP a critical moment of history has arrived for India.
The country cannot afford to miss this moment of history, this opportunity to throw out the rulers mainly responsible for this country’s ruination.
The BJP on its part has left no stone unturned in its efforts to put up a determined and united electoral battle and has unhesitatingly sacrificed its party interests whenever national interests so demanded.
The Bharatiya Janata Party calls upon the people to join in its struggle for ushering in a new era of hope and prosperity, a value based polity and throw out this corrupt and incompetent Congressmen.
