
1 .The Key Issue 3 Overview of 45 Years of Congress Achievements 4 Why Congress Again?
6 The BJP/NDA's Monumental Failures 8 The Congress Party's Priorities, Plans and Programmes 12 • Rozgar 14 • Kisans and Khet Mazdoors 16 • Women and Children 18 • Education and Health 19 • Minorities 20 • Dalits and Adivasis 21 • Food and Nutrition Security 22 • Panchayati Raj 23 • Informal and Unorganised Sector 24 • Social and Physical Infrastructure 24 • Defence, National Security and Foreign Policy 26 • Regional Development 27 • Administrative, Police, Judicial and Electoral Reforms 28 • Industry 29 • Fiscal Policy 31 • Implementation of Manifesto 31 An Appeal 32 This is the time for Back to Basics, basics that have formed the essence of our culture, basics that provided the impetus to our Independence Movement, basics that have built a modern, self-reliant and self-confident India over the past half century.
A time to reestablish the core values that have made India unique.
A time to rejoice in our diversities and reiterate our unities.
A time to reestablish the rule of law and repair our secular fabric.
A time to revive economic growth.
A time to reinforce social justice and equity.
A time to reinvigorate agriculture.
« A time to recharge the aspirations of our youth and women.
A time to reinject clarity and consistency in governance.
A time to rekindle the flame of all-inclusive, composite, pluralistic nationalism.
A time to reject the forces of bigotry and divisiveness.
A time to reinvent the politics as an instrument f c^anSe based on conscience, competence, compassion and commitment.
The 2004 Lok Sahha elections is no ordinary election.
It is not just an election between one party and another.
It is a clash of sharply competing values, of diametrically opposite ideologies.
It is a contest between the Congress that has always celebrated India's glorious past and drawn from its traditions to build modern India, and the BJP that is systematically undermining the very essence ot Indian civilization and destroying the very idea of India.
The Congress recognises that this is not a moment for a narrow pursuit ot partisan power.
This is the moment to consolidate all forces subscribing to the fundamental THE KEY ISSUE values of our Constitution.
The Congress's goal is to defeat the forces ot obscurantism and bigotry who contributed nothing to the Freedom Movement or the making ot our Constitution and whose sole objective is to subvert our millennial heritage and composite nationhood.
In this sacred endeavour, the Congress has joined hands with like-minded political parties in different states.
The Congress and its various allies are united in their determination to defeat the BJP, which threatens to rewrite our past and wreck our future.
In the process, we will present the national alternative to bring India back on the path ot economic growth with social harmony.
x -r. , Ihi tiding one nf the wtnLI's largest tcxtik Industrie*.
14 t T r' ' Bp ■ • ■ -., - -».
> mt‘pufiient r^„2 he achievements of successive (Congress governments are indelibly marked on rhe contemporary face of our country.
The RSS-RJP ci'mfmc has never missed an opportunity to develop backward regions and provide and adivasis.
ridicule, distort and misinterpret everything that the Congress party has done.
It is rhe Congress that abolished ramindan and ushered in land reforms, [r is rhe Congress rhar launched the Green Revolution and engendered rhe White Revolution bringing new prosperity to our kisans and khet mazdoors and making Indi- the largest milk producerm the world.
1 h is the Congress that fought for and won India's freedom.
It was the forebears of rhe R|P in the I I indu Mahasahha and the RSS rejected Mahatma ^ Hi 1111 S 4 Jill, kflTPTljKf Marengc” with he launched the Quit India Movement It is Congress leaders like t iandhiji, Indiraji and Rajivji who h; • a % sacrificed their lives in t he service c >1 thesounrt y.
It is rhe ( iuigrvss that was a n d nurturing OF CONGRESS responsible for establishing parliamentary denim racy vs as the Congress that It made out Constitution possible, a national charter for radical hut peaceful rhe Congress • f ’ r m. f • - ^ ^ that spearheaded s,n.ial reforms to give dignity to re discriminated tor centimes.
It t t hose who preserves I m ilittv al unity ansi sow reign tv s>f India.
|, ,f the ( ungrevs that t reated the public sector to 11 it) tea 11, tit sc 11 ul la and make it selt-adiant, to take it to new height* of technological progress, to It ts the Congress that promoted the scientific spirit ansi establishes!
the infrastructure and institutions that have made Irislia a major nuclear, spate and missile power, and a global lead Information Technology (IT).
India could test its nuclear weapons in May 1998 only because of the foundations laitl by the i single v*.
Missiles like Agnt are the Congress.
Satellites like INSAT are rhs legacA of the Congress.
I itaWiifini* toaliin m<u >u J 111i unJ 11 Ms tmiiiuhs A fh.iU'y told* kite I • ^ - '■ t/u I dliu.)
o/ liu N'aium If is the Congress that launched extensive anti- development through grassroots democracy in our poverty and rural development programmes that villages and mohallas.
It is the Congress that have helped alleviate the distress of the most conceived and pushed through the Constitutional disadvantaged and deprived sections of our society and made a massive dent on rural poverty.
A nation which had two-thirds of its people under the poverty-- line at Independence is now a nation with two-thirds ot its population above the poverty line in the halt century since Independence.
The middle class of India is the proud creation amendments relating to Panchayati Raj and the Municipalities.
It is the Congress that introduced and enacted extensive labour legislation to give workers in the organised sector and contract labour fair and remunerative wages and job security.
It is the Congress that began the process of extending social security to the 93 per cent work force that subsists in the unorganized sector.
4_y It is the Congress that pioneered the revolution in higher and technical e^ iucation that has now rendered the Indian brain the most highly valued commodity in the world.
It that is th e C oneress V ' of the Congress.
It is the Congress that empowered scheduled established the lITs, the IIMs and the RECs and that established the vast network of research laboratories.
castes, scheduled tribes and other backward classes through reservations and through social welfare It is the Congress that launched liberalization Congress's economic reforms.
and economic development programmes for their policies that made India the world's fourth largest welfare and well-being.
economy by 1998.
Congress, responding Gandhi's Gram Swaraj, Poorna Swaraj promoted grassroots there lire- live* in.iin reasons why the Congress remains unique among all political parties in India.
l irM, the Congress is the only alUndia party in iIh- country, the only national political force with a presence in each and every region of this vast country.
Whether in power or out, the Congress is n visilllc ar"-l tangible political force in villages, towns and cities all across India.
Lok Sahha remains its objective.
Fifth, the Congress has always been a party of youth.
It respects age and seniority Inu youthful energy and dynamism has always been irs hallmark.
In 1989, it was Rajiv (inndlu who reduced the voting age to Ii was Rajiv (> mdhi who declared Swami Viveka nand.i'* birth anniversary on January 12th as National Youth Day.
It was also he who expanded Second, the Congress is the only political party that derives its strength and support from, and appeals to, each and every section oi our variegated society.
It is the only political party that ha?
provided for reservations in it.
* organization lor scheduled castes s c h e d u I e d 11* i b e s, O B C s minorities and women.
Third, the Congress is the onh party whose philosophy o governance is rooted ir democratic values, combining sustainable economic growth with social justice, and marrying economic liberalization to social liberalism.
The Congress way is the way of dialogue, not discord.
the districts of the country.
the network of Nehru Yuvak Kendras to cover all The Congress way is the way of accommodation, not acrimony The Congress has always been more a broad national movement than a mere political Fourth, the Congress is the only party whose party in the conventional sense of the term, philosophy of governance is based on a strong b°r US years, it has provided an unusually centre working purposefully with strong states broad platform for people from diverse social and with empowered local self-government backgrounds to come together in the service institutions.
Rajniti Se Lok Niti, Gram Sahha Se of the country.
The Congress embodies the idc; i "t India like no other party does, sustained assault in the past few years.
For the t 4 lor the Congress, Indian nationalism is all- inclusive and cosmopolitan, a nationalism that respect for aI1 rc,teions.
It means equal draws creatively from every facet of India's rich opportunities for followers of all religions and no Congress, secularism means lull freedom and ^ w -»V/ I IUII17III tilt and variegated heritage, a nationalism that is not discrimination on the grounds of religion.
Most ol all, it means firm opposition tocommunalistn of all kinds.
narrow or bigoted but celebrates the ‘ " contribution made to our composite culture by each of the religions of the land.
It is a nationalism that has an equal and dignified place The misuse of any religion to spread hate and discord in our society is communalism.
The WHY CONGRESS AGAIN?
misuse of religion to incite popular passions to ignite mutual antagonisms is communalism.
Most Indians are religious.
At the same time, most Indians are respectful of other faiths.
Most Indians want to live with all other Indians, whatever their religion, in harmony and goodwill.
But a handful of Indian-' have become self-appointed guardians of their own faiths.
It is they who seek to destroy social peace.
It is they who want us to be prisoners of a distorted past, invented and misinterpreted by them to stoke envy and jealousy and hatred for everything Indian and for each and every Indian.
It is a nationalism that integrates India -- w emotionally.
The BJP's “cultural nationalism" is • .
T VM U 1__I.
*_W • device for dividing Indians emotionally.
The Congress unites the Indian nation through consensus; the BJP divides the Indian nation through confrontation.
betvv een communities.
• • This is the real battleground for secularism It is more than a majority-minority issue.
It i actually a struggle between those who wish t< preserve the essence of all religions and thos who seek to deliberately distort that essence ti undermine our composite nationhood to The Congress is deeply concerned that unacceptable ideological reasons and partisai secularism has come under the most severe and electoral ends.
growth, which characterised the 1992-97 growth lentiv.thclW ed Nl V\ government h; IN years a i perft irmance, • mavsivdv increased unc.npltiyniem by economic ix>ltcitss that have *,'l|mnVn l;,khsof wi>rkers cult ol employment in • iKiMi nny, tin- hatullooms sector, other non-farm i uralemployment and manufacturingnnd mining; ► to ensure the devolution of functions, ► lowered annual average growth over the last five years to much hel( nvsix percent, indeed as low as four percent in two of the five years, accompanied by wild swings in the pendulum ofgn>vvrh; caused acute for kisans and khef mazdoors, leading to an unprecedented number of kisan suicides across the country and growing functionaries and finances to the panchayats and municipalities, thus limiting tlu potc'ntial for employment genu at ion by elected local hehIics; ► caiisceI stagnation of investment and growth in small-scale and cottage industry and agriculture, which are the main sources of employment in the country; ► generated employment reduction schemes in government services and the public sector; THE B M 0 N (J ,\ destitution among kher mazdoors; ► mounted an ideological assault on the public sector, particularly profitable public enterprises which have been the single mostimportant avenue of t >rganized employment since Inde|\*ndence; • weakened national seeurity by not spending huge amounts of money running into thousands of crores of rupees allocated for modernization of our armed forces; • destabilized ;ind lovured growth rates, • damaged social harmony ► ending the steady rise in growth rates year after year, climaxing in nearly seven per cent annual ► by deliberately inciting a communal carnage in Gujarat; by glorifying violence ast against missionaries; fascist ^ enc°uraging viciously communal and organizations like the VHP/Bajrang Dal to government for its comiption and inefficiency and grossly misused theCBI; undermined the independence of our foreign pol school curricula by rewriting marginalisation of the United Nations, by not asserting India's position on world issues effectively spread hate; books autonomy of prestigious intellectual institutions by arul by constant flip-flops in our relations with o 11 loLlLLI Uinrr oit ~ * r . i .
« .
TV 1 • .
ta ngaw ay their professional independence; Pakistan.
destroyed probity in administration by The Prime Minister has displayed a singular lack of /N D A’S TAL FAILURES consistency and clarity on major national issues.
On every major national issue, he has indulged in doublespeak, whether it be Ayodhya and on the preservation of secularism; die carnage in Gujarat; relations widi Pakistan; negotiations with different groups in Jammu and Kashmir; encouraging corruption and fomenting scams in defence, telecom, DDA, allotment of petrol pumps, and links widi the RSS.
stock markets and UTI; denigrated key institutions democracy reports The Deputy Prime Minister and Home Minister took notwithstanding his being arraignec court of law and die Liberhan Commission for his role in the demolirion of the Babri Masjid.
He has presided over shocking security' lapses in the nadon's capital and elsewhere.
Four years ago, he grandly announced diat he would come out with a White Paper on 1SI Activities in India.
V- L - .
• [V » * N • .m- t * • Cl at?
"jw.
>7^ i M r Uqc been in office.
It is this lack of government has U _ klli|rL,,nof lnvebUHciiL v-iwi.- , i. foreign exchange reserves and that has rest, ted in the interest ratesboth factors identified by the Bjr as its “achievements”.
Moreover, low interest rates have benefited borrowers but have enormously hurt [IK -- who haveseen their valuable savings dwindle in value.
depo: The BJP claims that its highway development ^ ^ ^ A III I ___ — « a Home Ministry anc fixed die Deputy Prime Minister keep on chanting dieir firm resolve menace of terrorism at all costs resolve that is completely hollow.
The External Affairs Minister personally escorted three hard-core terrorists to wanton killings of innocent men, MONU Afgha These women and children in J&K.
Recently, former head of Pakistan admitted that die terrorist escorted by Shri Jaswant Singh to Kandahar masterminded attack on The BJP is going to die polls on a so-called 1 (1C L V7 1 # A 1 * This is bogus.
The reality Bihari Vajpayee, the average annual rate of economic growth (NHAI) is unprecedented.
The NHAI Congress government in 1995.
Most of the plans had been finalized before the Congress demitted office.
All that the BJP-led NDA government has done is turn the national highways already built by the express was highways.
Moreover, the new highways being built power.
The rate ofboth public and private investment has declined over die period diat the BJP-led NDA are not free; they can be used only after payment.
Congress j during 1950-90 were all free and anybody could use them.
boycotted by the Opposition for this gross impropriety.
It was during the term of the BJP-led NDA The BJP and its cohorts orchestrated the lunrific government that the stock market and UT1 scams communal carnage in Gujarat after the tragic events took place, as detailed by the Joint Parliamentary Committee that has fixed the eighteen months commencing from the swearing in of the NDA government in October 1999 as the period of the scams.
The scams wiped out the hard-earned savings at Godhra.
The RSS is indicted in most commissions of inquiry' into communal riots.
The Supreme Court has pulled up the Gujarat government refreatedly for its complicity in the communal carnage of2001.
On this count alone, the people of India must reject the BJP /NDAs TAL The BJP has fostered corruption to an unprecedented degree with scams after scams being revealed.
On this coimt too, the people ofhulia must reject the BJP The BJPs economic policies have sharpened the divide between the rich and the poor, between the fortunate feiv and the disadvantaged many, between of crores of middle class families, senor citizens, nfraj caK[ urbcm India, between different regions of 5 and widows.
The epicentre of the scams pensioners lay in cooperative banks based in die constituencies of the PrimeMinisterand the Deputy PnmeMmister.
the coiartry.
On this count also, the people of India must rejecttheBJP.
A video film showed die BJP President and other NDA leaders taking bribes.
The Defence Minister expose • > would not return till his name was cleared rejoined office while the enquiry was on and has been The BJP is using the NDA as a mask.
Hiding behind the faqade of the NDA, the BJP is misleading the hange with Continuity Congress policies have always been anchored in a vision of an economically prosperous, socially jush politically united and culturally harmonious India.
These policies have never been reduced by lote to a mindless doctrine or empty dogma or simplistic mantra.
The Congress has always created space for change.
It has always been pragmatic.
It has always been ready to respond to new challenges.
In consequence, steadfastness to basic principles has never impeded responsiveness to new requirements.
The 1950s needed land reforms, community development, the public sector and the building of agricultural, industrial, irrigation, educational, scientific and other infrastructure.
The Congress ensured that this happened.
The 1960s and 1970s needed a direct attack on poverty, a whole new approach to agricultural The 1980s needed renewed emphasis on science and technology to solve the problems of the people, and the modernization of industry to ready India to meet the new challenges of the 21st century.
It also required India to be ushered into the electronics, computers and telecommunications age in a significant way.
The Congress ensured that this happened.
THE CONG PRIORITI growth and rural employment, the exploration The 1990s needed bolder economic reforms and and exploitation of domestic sources of oil, and liberalization and a much larger role tor the the nationalization of banks to meet the private sector to accelerate growth and promote requirements of not just big business houses but India's integration into a rapidly-changing world also give priority to farmers, weavers, cottage economic system.
A redefinition of the role of industries and small industries and traders, as government in economic development, also to fulfill social needs and aspirations.
The including Constitutionally-sanctioned Congress ensured that all this happened.
Panchayati Raj Institutions and municipalities to function as units ot local self-government was also THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.
THERE needed.
The Congress ensured that happened.
this WILL BE NO COMPROMISE ON THIS.
Six Basics The Congress makes a solemn commitment to the people of India: to restore peace among all of The Congress’s six basics for governance: its peoples, to strengthen the secular order Samaiik Sadbhavna, to ensure social cohesion through emphasis on social harmony, cultural an^ harmony by taking the strictest possible action against those who promote bigotry and PARTY'S PLANS J pluralism and respect for the rule of law, and to ensure a bright and secure economic future for every family in our country.
THE LAW OF THE LAND WILL BE ENFORCED WITHOUT FEAR OR hatred; Yuva Rozgar, to accelerate growth of productive and secure employment opportunities increase by around one crore a year and ensure that each family has at least one job; Grameen Vikas, to improve the income and welfare of kisans and khet mazdoors across the country; Arthik Navotthan to unleash the creative energies of our professionals and entrepreneurs, the cutting edge of our middle class; Mahila Sashaktikaran, to provide for the political empowerment and full educational, economic and legal equality for women; Saman Avsar, to provide for equality of opportunity in every way for dalits, adivasis, OBCs and religious and linguistic minorities.
that social harmony These six priorities constitute the foundation ol AND COHESION IS MAINTAINED all policies of the Congress.
/ L Aadmi Ke Saath I; 3 I The Congress has consistently maintained that liberalisation and globalisation can be meaningful only it they are aimed at locaUevel economic and social transformation that directly benefits the poor in rural and urban India, bringing prosperity to the 6 lakh-odd villages of India and improving the living conditions of the urban poor.
The Congress will broaden and deepen economic reforms.
The overriding objective will be to attain and sustain year after year a 8T0% rate of economic growth and to spread this growth over all sectors, particularly agriculture and industry.
An annual growth rate of less than 4-4.5% in agriculture and 10% in industry is simply unacceptable.
Rozgar The priority requirement for accelerated employment generation is to revive economic growth and sustain it across the country at between 8-10% per year for u'ell over a decade.
This will be the Congress's overall objective.
Faster and broad-based economic growth is an essential pre-requisite for accelerating employment generation.
The Congress will also adopt policies to expand employment in the in the last five years.
Fiscal incentives to promote employment-intensive growth will be introduced.
Continued growth in agriculture will create new employment opportunities.
This is particularly so in the central, eastern and northeastern regions of the country which have still to realize their full agricultural potential.
New jobs will also THE CON PRIORITI be created in other areas of rural development like horticulture, aquaculture, afforestation, dairying and agro-processing.
These need and will be provided new investment, credit, marketing and technology' inputs.
A stable long¬ term export policy for agricultural products and organized sector, which has fallen precipitously commodities will be announced.
The Congress will revamp the functioning ot the textiles, handicrafts, gems and jewelry, leather, Khatli and Village Industries Commission software, engineering and consumer goods will (KV1C) so as to make it a modern, research-based, also significantly boost employment.
The textile technology- driven, c u s t o m e r- to c u s s e d industry will receive special focus in view of the organization.
New programmes for the increased competition in world markets from modernization ot the coir industry, handlooms, January 2005 as mandated by the WTO.
powerlooms, handicrafts, food processing, sericulture, wool development, leather, pottery, RE S S PARTY S ES, PLANS etcM will be launched.
A national Employment Guarantee Act will be enacted immediately.
This will provide a legal guarantee for at least 100 days of employment on asset-creating public works programmes every year at minimum wage, for every rural household.
The concerns of small-scale industry like shortage of working capital, lack of technology and marketing, delayed payments, harassment by inspectors will be addressed expeditiously.
A cluster approach to the development of small- scale industry will be adopted.
Along with vastly expanded credit facilities for self-employment, the services industry will be given all support to fulfill its true employment potential.
This includes not just software and IT-enabled services, not just trade, distribution and transport, not just financial and telecommunications services but also tourism.
al infrastructural facilities for substanti expanding international and domestic tourism will be created.
Reforms of laws and regulations that stand in the way of growth of the services industry will be undertaken.
The Congress will also establish a National Commission to monitor the functioning of A greater thrust on labour-intensive exports of enterprises in the informal sector, the problems they face in access to technology, credit and markets and recommend corrective measures on also expand substantially.
Immediate steps will be¬ taken to ease the burden of debt and high interest an on-going basis.
rates on farm loans.
To enhance the employability of our youth, A time-hound programme for restoring all public systematic efforts will be made to vocationaiise tubewells to good working condition wherever secondary education and to establish at least one required will be started.
The pace of construction industrial training institute in each development of new irrigation wells in the poorer districts of block of the country through creative public- private partnerships.
The employment exchange machinery will be revamped to provide a closer linkage between demand and supply for labour.
As an indicator of how seriously the Congress takes its commitment to employment growth, an annual Rozgar Report to the Nation will be prepared and released on May Kisans and Khet Mazdoors The Congress will pursue an Agriculture First strategy in resource allocation.
Public investment in agriculture will be stepped up substantially with focus in the backward and poor regions.
This will cover irrigation, electrification, godowns, marketing, research and extension.
The entire rural credit system based on cooperatives will be restored to health.
The flow of agricultural credit would be doubled in the next three years and the coverage of small and marginal farmers by institutional lending will the country will be accelerated.
A special technology and extension programme lor dryland farming will be introduced.
An intensive agricultural development programme lor the 100-odd districts in the arid and semi-arid legions of rhe country will be put in place.
Watershed development projects will be promoted on a large-scale and the wasteland development programme lying dormant these past few years will be revived.
The agro-processing industry and other agriculture-related activities like dairying, aquaculture, fisheries, horticulture, sericulture will be encouraged through fresh investment, RE S S PARTY’S ES, PLANS Farmers all over the country will receive (air and remunerative prices and government agencies entrusted with the responsibility for procurement and marketing will pay special attention t<> farmers in poor and backward states and distrii ts.
While farm insurance schemes for both crops and cattle will be implemented, the Congress will als< > ricultural examine the feasibility of an Ag Stabilisation Fund involving a system of direct support or income support to farmers part icularly in the ecologically vulnerable regions of the country.
Controls on the free movement of farm commodities and processing of agricultural products and regulations that depress the incomes of farmers will be systematically removed.
Farmers will be given greater say in the organizations that supply inputs to them.
The Congress will ensure the fullest implementation of minimum wage laws for farm technology and marketing resources.
A renewed labour.
Comprehensive protective legislation will emphasis will be placed on wasteland be enacted tor all agricultural workers.
It will development and afforestation.
redouble its efforts to distribute surplus While the terms of trade will always he maintained in favour of agriculture, simultaneously steps will be taken to ensure that profitability in agriculture is also increased.
productive land to the landless.
It will also modernize the revenue administration at the local level and start a major national programme to record all titles to land and keep them up-to-date.
Like it did tor panchayats, the Congress will bring toward a Constitutional amendment to ensure the democratic, autonomous and professional functioning ot all cooperatives.
Women and Children The Congress pledges to press tor the Constitutional Amendment to reserve one-third of seats in the Lok Sabha and in Vidhan Sabhas for women.
It will launch a movement tor the effective implementation ot social legislation such as tor minimum age at marriage, anti-dowry, curbing atrocities on women, anti-sati, widow welfare, etc.
as well as for minimum w %es ^ ^ women's welfare.
Stern measures will be taken to ensure the elimination ot female foeticide and infanticide.
Marriage registration will be made mandatory.
3Q% cf aH funds flowing into panchayats and nagarpalikas will be earmarked for programmes relating to the development ot women and children and focus on the special needs ot female a<-Ticu'rural labour and women cultivators.
YtUace women and their associations will be health, nutrition, biogas, maintenance of water pumps and borewells and farm forestry.
Complete legal equality for women in all spheres will be made a practical reality, especially by removing discriminatory legislation, by giving them equal share in matrimonial property, by protecting their rights to matrimonial homes and THE CONG PRIORITI AND PRO ’streedhan', by giving them equal rights of ownership of assets like houses and land, etc.
All states will be encouraged to set up family courts at the earliest.
empowered to assume responsibility tor all There will be a major expansion in schemes for development schemes relating to drinking water micro-finance based on self-help groups, supply, sanitation, primary education and especially for tribal women, women belonging to * IIM-Ahmedabad scheduled ca^es, women below the poverty line, 4 • rural women and women in distress, and particularly in the backw sensitive regions and actively encourage the functioning of producer and marketing cooperatives.
Some states of India, particularly in the South, have RESS PARTY S PLANS 1 ecologically mounted in the 150odd districts that still have .x I I must become a movement of civil society as well.
A sharply targeted mobilization effort will be unacceptably high levels of fertility’.
Education and Health The Congress pledges to raise public spending in education to at least 6% of GDP with at least half of this amount being spent in primary and secondary schools.
A cess will be proposed on all central taxes to finance the commitment to universalize access to quality basic education.
A National Commission on Education will be set up to allocate resources and monitor programmes for compliance with national priorities.
The Congress will ensure that all institutions of higher learning in science, technology, social sciences and management will retain the sense of autonomy that they have enjoyed in previous Congress regimes.
Academic excellence and professional competence would be the sole criteria already reached replacement levels of fertility while for a|[ appointments to bodies like the 1CHR, other states will do so over this decade.
But on ICSSR, UGC, NCERT, etc.
present reckoning, four-five states of India will be unable to reach this crucial milestone for decades.
The Congress will take the lead in replicating the those states where uccess of other states in iwth tanning is not just a government program,ne hut The Congress will ensure that nobody is denied education, including in institutions of excellence, because he or she is poor.
Apart from increasing the supply of loan scholarships and refinance through banks, it will also establish a Education Congress Ka Haath Aam Aadmi Ke Saath i • t * I ■j0t: Development Finance Company along the lines of HDFC to provide loans at affordable rates to all those who cannot afford the costs of college and university education in science, engineering and medicine.
Education at all stages would be free in all respects for boys and girls belonging to dalit and adivasi communities.
A national cooked nutritious mid-day meal scheme will be introduced in primary and secondary schools across the country.
The Integrated Child Development Services (1CDS) will be universalized to provide for a functional anganwadi in every settlement and full coverage, especially children below age of six.
The Congress will raise public spending on health to at least 2-3% of GDP, with the focus on primary health care over the next five years and to around 5% of GDP over the next decade.
Some state governments administered by the Congress have introduced innovative health insurance programmes.
A national scheme of health insurance for families living below the poverty line will be proposed.
Linorities Congress believes in affirmative action for all ligious and linguistic minorities.
The Congress ,s provided for reservations tor Muslims in crnla and Karnataka in government nployment and education on the grounds that ev are a socially and educationally backward y . J *.J_ this policy tor socially and educationally backward sections among Muslims and other religious minorities on a national scale.
The The Congress will introduce a new community- Congress also pledges to extend reservations tor anchored health worker scheme and implement the economically deprived persons belonging to it with the involvement of peoples organizations communities that are at present not entitled to and panchayati raj institutions.
such reservations.
r?
The Congress will adopt all possible measures education among women in minority promote maintain communal peace communities particularly.
harmony, especially in sensitive areas.
It will enact a comprehensive law on social • • violence in all its forms and manifestations, providing investigations a central agency, prosecution Special Courts payment of uniform compensation for loss of life, PA RTY' S PLANS honourand property The Congress commits itself to amending the Commission for Constitution to es rablish Minority Educational Institutions that will ■ i .
1 i / f/Ar provide direct affiliation for minority professional insrirutions to central universities.
Special steps will he taken to spread modern and rechmca New middle-level technical institutions will be started in places where for example, weavers and artisans are concentrated.
The National Minorities Development Corporation and State Minorities Development Corporations will be made direct-lending institutions.
On the Ayodhya issue, the Congress's stand has been very clear.
All parties must wait for and abide by the verdict of the courts.
If negotiations are to be held, they must be between the parties to the dispute.
And the Places of Worship (Special Provision) Act, 1992 which freezes the status of all disputed sites other than Ayodhya as of August 1 5, 1947 must be strictly enforced.
Dalits and Adivasis The Congress will create a national consensus on the issue of dalits and adivasis getting a reasonable share of jobs in the private sector.
A dialogue with private industry will be initiated to identify how best Indian industry could fulfill in tangible measure the aspirations of youth, especially those belonging to the weaker sections of society.
Determined efforts will be made to promote a culture of entrepreneurship among the dalits and adivasis by providing businesses run by them with 21 Congress Ka Haath Aam Aadmi Ke • •' .. 33 > ■ ♦.
«• • -.. _ . . . . - f \•*.
*V ' »» • • . . - * ■- , •;: Jr ' -kv >.
* * , - *. . - • .
• *• PI • " 4r-* V t -i t f, • f!
f ‘ preferential treatment government recognized a addressed in an ecologically procurement and by extending bank credit at sustainable manner.
In addition, theie is need to affordable terms.
State governments will be urged to make legislation tor conferring ownership right s in put in place more effective systems of relief and rehabilitation for tribal communities displaces by development projects.
respect of minor forest produce on adivasis Taking note of the growing unrest in tribal areas particularly who work in forests.
in various states, the Congress wi 11 have a fresh All reservation quotas, including those relating to promotions will be fulfilled in a time-bound manner.
Special recruitment drives particularly for Class I and II vacancies will be launched.
A comprehensive national programme for minor irrigation of all lands owned by dal its and adivasis will be introduced.
Landless families will be endowed with some land through the proper implementation of land ceiling and land redistribution legislation.
There is need to reconcile the objectives of faster economic growth and environmental conservation as far as tribal communities dependent on forests are concerned.
The Forest Conservation Act, 1980 has prevented a wholesale loss of forests.
At the same time, concerns have been raised that in its implementation rigidities have developed THE CONG PR10RITI look at development strategies tor tribal areas and work out new designs of sustainable livelihoods.
Income accruing to the government from forest will be earmarked as additional assistance for programmes of tribal development.
depriving tribal communities the benefits of Food and Nutrition Security economic growth.
These concerns have to be Over the past few years, there has been far too I much tampering with the public distribution About 6*8% of our population comprising the system (PDS) that provides the basis for extending most destitute and infirm do not have access to food security to crores of Indians.
Because people the PDS even where the PDS works well.
Special are buying less toodgrain from ration shops, huge schemes to reach foodgrains to this section foodgrain stocks have been built up.
The through panchayats will be launched.
Antyodaya Congress will strengthen the PDS particularly in cards for all households at risk of hunger will be the poorest and backward blocks of the country introduced.
Grain banks in chronically food and also involve women's and ex-servicemen's scarce areas will be established.
P A RT Y’ S PLANS It is a matter of great shame that even today over a third of babies born in India are under-weight reflecting acute malnourishment of the girl child who later becomes a mother.
Nutrition programmes for the girl child particularly will be expanded on a significant scale.
Panchayati Raj Panchayat bodies that got Constitutional sanction a decade ago because of the vision and relentless zeal of Rajiv Gandhi, now need full devolution of funds, functions and functionaries.
Globalisation and economic reforms must be cooperatives in its management at the local level.
based on strong, effective and empowered While the focus of the PDS will be on below-the- institutions of local self-government.
poverty line (BPL) families, surveys to identify The Congress will ensure that all funds for such families will be conducted every two years by poverty alleviation and rural development panchayats Leased on transparent and verifiable ownership, etccu patio n, A _ _ _ A_ - — ^ ^ criteria such as family status, etc.
programmes will be credited directly to panchayat •ill ■• 1 1 • bodies.
The Gram Sabha will be empowered to emerge as the foundation of the panchayati raj Congress Ka Haath Aam Aadmi Ke Saa system.
Appropriate audit systems would be financial ensure soun established administration at the local level.
Informal and Unorganised Sector Almost 93% of the workforce in our country is in this purpose A single, simplified law will be acted set out the obligations of these enterprises to labour and for safety.
Appropriate social security measures will be devised to protect I _ . ZN .
I 4* A the workers in the unorganized sector against the risks of ill-health, unemployment and old age.
While The Congress will create legal space in the cities must and will be taken to expand the proportion of employment in the organized sector, the Congress will ensure the well-being and welfare of all workers in the unorganized sector.
Some Congress state governments have already taken significant steps in this area but a renewed national effort is now needed with focus on social insurance and health support.
Special social security schemes started by earlier Congress governments for workers in the unorganized like weavers, handloom workers, sector fishermen and fisherwomen, toddy tappers, leather workers, plantation labour, beedi workers, etc., will be expanded.
CONG and towns for hawkers, vendors, food'Sellers and The Congress will establish a National n , .
f . ’ . . fhnt me uuiisic all such informal sector service activities tnai Commission to examine problems facing uu^u iiuuilllcll bCLlUL bCLVLCC ^ — enrich urban life, so that they are spared the risk enterprises operating in the unorganized sector.
The Commission will be asked to make appropriate recommendations to provide ot extortion, eviction, confiscation anL harassment.
technical, marketing and credit support to these Social and Physical Infrastructure enterprises.
A National Fund will be created for Public-private partnerships will form the bash ot infrastructure expansion.
Among other things, this could take the form of public expenditure and private management.
Subsidies in the provision of infrastructure will be made explicit and provided through the budget of the central and state governments.
The railways have suffered immensely over the PARTY’S PLANS potential.
By 2020, the presently known irrigation potential must be harnessed, tor which long-term commitments caf funds will be made.
But even after this, two-fifths cat cultivated area will still be rain-fed, particularly in central India with the bulk of India's tribal population.
The Congress and its partners will prepare and implement, on a much larger scale, plans tor these regions.
The Congress will launch a special programme % so as to ensure each household will have full access to reliable power in the next three to five years.
The Congress will use India's foreign exchange reserves creatively to significantly expand the existing public investment programme in power generation so as to add at least 6000-8000 MW of generating capacity every year.
The public sector has a crucial role to play in power generation even as the private sector takes on an increased role in power distribution.
past few years with rail safety being a prime casualty.
The Congress will move purposefully to In order to supplement water availability' economic and social dimensions of the resources, a local community-based twork and recharge the country's groundwater railways in mind.
nae Congress will vastly accelerate the '< velopment and use of the country s miration National Rainwater Harvesting Programme will be launched to capture at least an additional 1% of India's rain resources every year.
The Congress commits itself to work out a comprehensive programme of urban renewal one-rank, one-pension will once again he re- examined and the satisfactory solution arrived at based on public-private partnerships.
This will lay expeditiously.
particular emphasis on the modernization of urban transport, water supply and sanitation and control of pollution.
Municipal administration will be revived and made financially self- sustaining.
Social housing schemes will be launched to meet the needs of the urban poor and to deal with the proliferation of slums.
Technologies to promote low-cost housing will be deployed on a large scale.
Defence, National Security and Foreign Policy The Congress will ensure that all delays in the modernization of our armed forces are eliminated and that funds budgeted for modernization are, in fact, spent to the fullest.
The Congress is committed to maintaining a credible nuclear weapons programme while at the same time it will evolve demonstrable and verifiable confidence-building measures with its nuclear neighbours.
The welfare of ex-servicemen The Congress will make the National Security Council a professional and effective institution It will immediately have a discussion in Parliament on the Subrahmanyam Committee THE CONG PRIORIT!
report on hargil and move resolutely to implement its recommendations to strengthen will occupy urgent attention and plans will be our intelligence networks.
expeditiously prepared for involving them in crucial nation-building tasks.
A new Department The Congress has been consistent, unlike the BJP, on the issue of dialogue with Pakistan on all • i • of Ex-Servicemen's Welfare will be set up in the issues including Jammu and Kashmir.
It has Ministry of Defence.
The long-pending issue of always advocated formal and informal talks on ifA < 4 % 99>—as the basis of the historic Shimla Agreement of major regional projects in areas like energy and 197 ^ At the same time, the Congress is firm in its water that will bring benefits to all countries of view that Pakistan’s sponsorship of cross-border our region.
terrorism must end completely once and for all.
If Regional Development ii continues, then the Indian state has the responsibility to protect its citizens.
The Congress will expand trade and investment As always, the Congress will work for balanced regional development.
India's northeast demands and will receive special treatment with particular emphasis on roads, power, tourism, communication and handicrafts.
Without the restoration of law and order and a firm approach to combating militancy, no development can be sustained in the northeast.
The northeast will emerge as a gateway to East Asia with which India is building new economic relationships.
The Congress also takes note of growing inter-state disparities that have led to some important states like UP and Bihar to fall behind in social development and economic growth.
While state governments have the final responsibility for governance, the central government has still an relations with t 'hina and with countries of East Asia.
important role in ensuring that the lagging states West Asia improve their performance through fiscal and and ot her non-aligned countries.
It will reaffir m out other policies.
it,klui(,na| bonds with countries like Russia, Japan In view of the importance of state-level reforms, and the European l Jnion.
It will engage the United nes in scientific, technological, strategic and 1 tniiiert ial cooperation It will take the dership to .strengthen SAARC and launch the Congress will set up a Systems Reforms Commission to work out, in cooperation with state governments, the details of state-level reforms that are needed to accelerate growth and impiove the 1111111117 of basic social services.
A operation soon.
Protection sti uctured and transparent approach to alleviate the burden of debt on states .so as to enable them to increase social sector investments will be adopted.
Administrative, Police, Judicial and Electoral Reforms An Administrative Reforms Commission will be established to prepare a detailed blueprint for revamping the public administration system completely so as to make it more performance' oriented and accountable.
While b asic governance is the priority, e-governance will be promoted on a massive scale in areas of concern to the common man particularly, like land records, tax administration, etc.
All government agencies but particularly those that deal with citizens on a day-to-day basis must operate in a responsive and accountable manner.
extended to all “whistleblowers” through statutory means, if necessary, The police force will function in an impartial, professional, effective and humane manner.
The special needs of police families, especially i in education and housing, will be taken care of in THE CON PRIORJTI The Right to Information Act at the centre will be adequate measure.
More women will encouraged made more progressive, meaningful and useful to to join the police force.
4- * * 1 .
■ / v 1 XV 4 — — -A I 1 i ^ the public.
The monitoring and implementation of the Act will be made more participatory and the penalty clauses regarding delays, illegal denials and other inadequacies relating to the supply of information to the public will be Immediate measures will be taken to drastically CL|t delays in courts, particularly in the High Courts and in lower levels of the judiciary.
Legal aid services will be aided.
Alternative dispute settlement mechan isms wi 11 be strengthened- A >-* - .. v. H..- * new system of nyaya panchayats will be instituted.
fulfilled their social purpose, transparency in The Congress is deeply committed to electoral reforms.
It was the first party to set up a committee to review its system of financing to ensure maximum transparency.
The report of that committee is in the public domain and the party financing and state funding of elections will help.
Even so, the Congress is conscious of the havoc that corruption at all levels adds to the harassment of the common man and is determined to rid the cou n try of th is sc<>u rge.
Congress is on the path of its implementation.
It Industry PARTY’S PLANS Revival of industrial growth is of paramount importance.
Incentives for boosting private investment will be introduced.
The system of approvals of foreign direct investment will be made more transparent.
Indian industry will he encouraged in every manner to enhance its global presence.
Competition, both domestic and external, will be deepened across industry with professionally-run regulatory institutions in place to ensure that the competition is free and fair.
These regulatory institutions will protect the interests of consumers.
was the only party to welcome last year's Supreme The Congress will strengthen the public Court order on disclosure by candidates that was sector in key, strategic areas, including opposed by the BJP and it allies.
The Congress will tackle the root causes of corruption and the generation of black money.
To a large extent, deregulation, removal of laws Tat have outlived their utility or have not infrastructure.
It will help public sector companies in these areas to emerge as global companies.
There is still an important role for the public sector as a venture capitalist in new and emerging areas.
Public sector .
‘A V companies that can be revived through new management will be identified.
The great advantage of the public sector still lies in starting new projects, while e great me lustry that is the lifeline of many towns an d cities across the country will h m o d e r n i z e d and given greater technological, investment and marketing , 1 advantage private sector lies in support running them commercially.
Public-private synergies will be fostered.
The Congress will approach privatization selectively.
Disinvestment will not b resorted to merely to raise revenue to meet short-term targets, as the NDA has been doing.
Disinvestment revenues will be used for designated social development programmes.
The Congress will ensure that disinvestment increases competition and consumer welfare.
The Congress will establish a National Manufacturing Competitiveness Council to provide a continuing forum for policy interactions to energise and sustain the growth of the manufacturing industry like food processing, textiles, engineering, consumer goods, pharmaceuticals, leather, capital goods, industrial machinery and IT hardware.
A massive push will be given to the applications of IT particularly.
Household and artisanal manufacturing The Congress is committed to a modern, world-class financial sector that also fulfills THE CONG PRIORITI social objectives.
Competition in the financial sector will be expanded.
Public sector banks will be given full managerial autonomy.
Banks will be encouraged in every way to expand lending, particularly to agriculture, agro-industry, value-added agriculture, small-scale industry and infrastructure.
Interest rates must be such so as to stimulate not just investments but also provide adequate returns to savers.
Fiscal Policy The Congress reiterates its fi 1 r m commitment to eliminating the revenue tax reforms to sign i fi can tly expand the base of taxpayers, to substantially increase tax compliance and to make the tax administration more citizen-friendly.
Without increasing tax rates, the Congress believes that the present deficit of the central government in five Tax:GDP ratio of 14-15 % must be PARTY’S PLANS years time so as to release more resources investments in soci and physical infrastructure.
detailed roadmap for accomplishing this will be unveiled within M days of coming to power so that national consensus is also created.
ongress wi ill undertake major raised to at least 18% by the end of the decade.
VAT will be introduced in close cooperation and consultation with trade and industry.
This will enhance the competitiveness of Indian industry and also check tax evasion.
Implementation of Manifesto Within 100 days of receiving the mandate of the people of our country, the Congress will release a detailed action plan with milestones for governance based largely on the promises and commitments made in this manifesto.
Every year on October 2nd, the Congress pledges to present to the people of India a Jan Dastavejh on the progress of implementation of the manifesto. . . .
I conscious of its accomplishments and f Incii India diversities many unities anu .. c .Lp steady hand of experience A vote for the Congress is a vote for th ‘ for convicti< UI LWI loioiA^n^y --c?
governance and administration nd A vote for the Congress is a vote for a vision of India that has an equal and dignified place for each and every °^e ° C _ in which there is equality of opportunity tor all to fulfi t eir aspirations.
The Congress is asking the people of India to vote tor it on its concerns and its charter.
The Congress has received the support and trust of the people of India for decades.
It has always tried to fulfill that trust in substantial measure.
For economic growth with social harmony, vote Congress.
For economic growth that benefits all sections of our society, and fulfills the aspirations of all Indians, vote Congress.
For economic growth that brines c- , r b I.u 1 lugs prosperity first and foremost to rural India, vote Congress 1 or clarity, conviction, compassion and consistency m governance and admini i nistration, vote Congress.
Vole Congress, Jui Hind