TOWARDS A NEW POLITY ELECTION MANIFESTO LOK SABHA ELECTION-1984     Indian polity today stands at a critical crossroad of history.
The state of the nation is examplified by the breakdown of law and order, an absence of purpose and direction in governance, deep divisions within society marked by deliberately engineered communal and castesist passions, and a serious erosion of institutions.
Near about half our citizens continue to groan under the dehumanising yoke of abject poverty aggravated by spiraling prices.
Urban chaos and rural neglect have degraded the quality of our citizens’ life.
The shocking assassination of the late Prime Minister and subsequent occurrences are the most horrifying and telling symptoms of erosion of moral authority and a total decay of the ruling party.
At such a critical juncture a new direction and a fresh political initiative was expected from the successor government.
Betraying all hopes, the government of the day, mired in immobility, a prisoner of the old caucus, continues cynically to repeat yesterday’s irrelevancies.
When decisive action is called for, it merely mouths platitudes and attempts to transfer responsibility by accusing others.
National integrity, unity, and cohesion are the paramount need of the hour; the reestablishment of national consensus a primary task.
Today’s challenge cannot be met by yesterday’s government.
The need of the hour is a new polity, a new government, a new leadership.
In the new polity we stand committed to value-based politics, to democracy, to positive secularism, and to Gandhian economics.
India needs a new government which is clean, effective purposeful and representative of the rich diversity of our land.
Such a government must restore the moral authority of the State, commit itself afresh to the integrity of the nation and guarantee the security of every single citizen of the country.
This Republic of   3 elan no longer be left a Prisoner of the corrupt and criminal.
To fulfill this task the Bharatiya Janata Party offers to the nation the following programme.
   National Politics National Unity And Positive Secularism BJP is pledged to defend the unity and integrity or India it believes that India, from Kashmir to Kanya Kumari, is one country, and all Indians, irrespective of language, caste or creed, are one people.
Unity in diversity has been the hallmark of Indian culture, which is a unique multi-heud synthesis of the cultural contributions made over the centuries by different peoples and religions.
In Indian tradition, since times immemorial, the State has always been a civil institution, which makes no distinction between one citizen and another on grounds of his religion.
The very idea of a theocratic state is alien to Indian political history.
So, when India became independent in 1947, we very naturally declared ourselves a secular state, unconcerned that Pakistan had opted for theocracy.
It is this positive concept of secularism to which BJP is committed.
Secularism should not be allowed to become a euphemism for appeasement, alternately of this community, or that, or a sordid political device to garner bloc-votes.
Ours is a democratic federal Constitution.
It envisages strong States, with a strong Centre.
Indeed the whole cannot be strong unless the constituent parts are strong too.
But over the years the States have been increasingly reduced to glorified municipalities.
The BJP will restore the balance between the Centre and the States as visualised by our constitution makers.
And to that end, it will: Support and strengthen state Governments and not destabilize and topple them; Appoint State Governors in consultation with State Governments;   3 .
Enact an anti-Defection Law; Limit the number of ministers to 10 per cent of legislators; as per the Report of the Committee on Defections; Give the states a fairer share of Central revenues and increase the financial powers of the States; Delete the temporary Article 370 of the Constitution; Constitute an Inter-State Council under Article 263 to settle all Inter-State and State-Centre disputes; Guarantee to all minorities, linguistic and religious, peace and security, and full opportunities for progress and development.
Fair Elections The BJP believes in the primacy of elections.
It is convinced that elections must be held regularly and very fairly.
They must honestly reflect the public mind.
And the parties fighting these elections must also function democratically—and cleanly.
Four evils threaten to subvert the freedom and fairness of elections—money-power, ministerial-power, media-power and muscle-power.
The BJP is resolved to contain and curb all these evils.
The party will give high priority to electoral reform.
More specifically, BJP will— Give the right of vote to all those above eighteen; Introduce Identity Cards for voters; Use electronic voting machines, and to this end, make necessary changes in the election law; As recommended by the Parliamentary Joint Committee on Amendments to Election Law, examine the feasibility of introducing the List system of elections; Give the right of Postal Ballot to Indian citizens living abroad; Hold State and Central elections simultaneously every five years; Make the Election Commission a multi-member body; strengthen its independence by making expenditure incurred on the Commission expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of India, as is provided in the case of Comptroller and Auditor General and Supreme Court and   High Court judges, and by providing the Commission with an independent, minimal infrastructure; Extend the jurisdiction of the Election Commission to local body elections, and to ensure that elections to local bodies are held regularly; Arrange for public funding of elections, as is the case in Germany, Japan and most other democratic countries; Have party accounts publicly audited; To prevent abuse of governmental power by the ruling party, give legal teeth to the Code of Conduct framed by Election Commission; violation of the code shall be made a corrupt practice under the law.
Corruption In the last 4 years or so corruption has not only become way of life but has in fact been institutionalized and legitimized.
An unholy nexus has developed between the corrupt politician, the corrupt bureaucrat and the corrupt businessman.
The volume of black-money has grown phenomenally and is now estimated at around 50 per cent of the total money in circulation.
The BJP holds that the roots of all corruption lie in political and electoral corruption.
While measures to cleanse elections have been dealt with earlier, with regard to political corruption in general, the BJP will, inter alia, take the following steps: It will enact a law, and create an Ombudsman-Lokpal and Lokayaukta-as recommended by the Administrative Reform’s Commission; and Stramline procedures and rules relating to purchases awarding of contracts etc.
in Government and public sector undertakings and regulate discretionary powers of political authorities; political interference and intervention in day-to-day End Government departments and public sector functioning of actions, dealing with purchases and award of contracts etc.
; Rationalise and streamline the tax structure, providing sufficient incentives to savings and avoiding harassment to honest tax-payers and to avoid generation of black money; Require all Ministers to make an annual declaration of assets.
4 North East All our North Eastern States suffer from unsatisfactory, economic development, insufficient recognition of local diversity, inadequate participation in National tasks, unchecked illegal immigration resulting in demographic imbalances and serious social destablisation.
The BJP believes that a resolution of all these problems has to be undertaken jointly and keeping in mind the peculiarities of the region.
In this endeavor the Brahmaputra Valley and the State of Assam play a crucial role.
No integrated development of the region is possible if Assam continues to remain unstable.
The BJP will, therefore, give high priority to the solution of the many problems afflicting Assam.
It will work purposefully and expeditiously for their early resolution.
Whilst cooperating with the efforts of the Chief Election Commissioner, to carry out a detailed enumeration, leading to a proper revision and publication of electoral rolls, the party will simultaneously continue to emphasise the need for adequate safeguards so that the scrutiny of enumeration lists becomes meaningful.
Mindful of the national commitment of bonafide refugees in the region, the BJP will work continuously to protect their interests.
In addition, the BJP will take all effective steps to prevent further illegal immigration.
For this purpose it will work towards joint, cooperative effort by all the concerned adjoining states like Tripura, West Bengal and Bihar.
At the heart of the continued impasse in Assam is the alienation of a whole section of our countrymen, resulting in the citizens of that state being deprived of their right to participate in current elections.
The BJP will immediately resume the process of negotiation and reconciliation so that the many problems of the region can be tackled with the wholehearted participation of the citizens.
Punjab ‘The BJP shares the agony of Punjab with the Punjabis.
It congratulates the people of Punjab on maintaining the peace in the Punjab in the face of grave provocation.
The BJP holds the Congress (1) squarely responsible for   encouraging separatist and terrorist elements in the Punjab.
As a result, for four long agonising years, the State has been subject to an orgy of murder and mayhem.
The tragic murder of Prime Minister Mrs Gandhi, and the bastial carnage which followed in its wake, also, are poison-fruits of Government’s Punjab policy.
The BJP wishes to declare unequivocally that the nation shall not allow another assault on the country’s integrity, and that there can be no compromise with those who talk of Khalistan.
At the same time, the BJP will not suffer any harm being done to innocent people, Hindu or Sikh.
The Punjab problem is basically political and we will solve it politically; Separatism and terrorism will be sternly dealt with; We will adequately compensate the sufferers of violence during the last three years; The BJP will refer territorial claims and counterclaims river waters and other outstanding issues, to the Chief Justice of India, for arbitration within one year.
Law & Order The BJP views with alarm the rise of social violence in the country.
This includes communal violence, atrocities on Harijans and tribals, and criminal assaults on women.
It is committed to the security of life, limb, property and honour of all citizens.
Whenever there is a serious eruption of violence There must be a judicial inquiry; The inquiry report must be published; The Report recommendations must be implemented; Men guilty of incitement to violence or dereliction of duty will be punished; All riot sufferers must be suitably and adequately compensated and rehabilitated; We will conduct in-depth socio-economic studies of prone areas to take effective steps for riot-prevention.
The Police & The People The Police is a vital organ of the State.
Over the years, the gulf between the people and the Police has grown very wide.
The people complain of Police Zulum; and the Police complains of political   4 and of bad living and working conditions.
The BJP will Implement the Police Commission’s recommendations particularly with regard to the emoluments and service conditions of police personnel; Modernise the Police Force and convert it into an efficient and impartial instrument or law and order: Set up a machinery for redressal of Police, People’s grievances; Stop political meddling in police work; Set up local committees of respected citizens to bridge the gap between the People and the Police.
Justice The BJP attaches the greatest importance to Justice—Justice that will be quick, inexpensive and just.
It notes with regret that over the years there has been an all all-round deterioration in this respect.
The Independence of the Judiciary has been seriously eroded.
BJP will take corrective steps to restore the independence, integrity and efficiency of the judicial system.
We will Simplify the legal procedures and increase the number of judges, so that no case lingers on beyond one year; Appoint Chief Justices strictly in order of seniority; Not harass judges with politically inspired transfers; Offer better emoluments to judges to attract more talent to the Bench; Raise the retirement age of judges to 65, give them full pensions equal to their salary, and give them quasi-judicial work after retirement without extra cash payment.
Human Rights Commission BJP will widen the scope of the present ineffectivc Minorities Commission and convert it into a Human Rights Commission to take care of the just rights of all individuals, groups and communities.
   National Economy The National Economy is in bad shape.
While production is moving up at snail’s pace, prices are galloping away.
More people are unemployed today than at the time of Independence.
The rich are getting richer while the poor stay poor.
Village industries are dying.
Many of our industries are working at only 40 per cent of capacity.
More and more millions are falling below the Poverty Line everywhere.
Last year alone the Public Sector lost ₹ 6,000 crores (Rupees Six thousand crores) only.
The BJP will reverse all these ugly trend, and give the country a humane economy.
It will take all steps necessary to achieve full employment, maximise production, stabilise prices and pull more and more millions above the Poverty Line, until nobody is left poor in the country.
Agriculture Agriculture is our biggest industry.
It is the backbone of the economy.
BJP will encourage it in every way.
In particular, we will: Implement the land laws; quickly complete on-going big irrigation projects; start thousands of small irrigation works; subsidies inputs; give remunerative prices; establish a parity of agricultural and industrial prices; Specially encourage pulses, oil seeds, fruits, nuts and, vegetables cultivation, and also production of cash crops; Increase milk supply and effect a White Revolution; Attain food self-sufficiency and never again need to import food-grains.
BJP will encourage and improve industry all-round.
We will:   4 .
Make the public sector productive and profitable; Demarcate the spheres of multinational corporations, other foreign companies, big industry, small-scale industry and cottage industry; Cut down on the plathora of controls which presently exist, and which breed corruption and dampen enterprise; and maintain only such of these restrictions as are necessary for social justice.
Foster the Swadeshi spirit; Reserve more and more consumer items to small-scale and cottage sectors; Make credit more cheaply available to small-scale industry; Modernise industrial plants; Promote agro-based industries; Encourage Research and Development; Require businessmen to act as trustees of the public good; Publicly honour excellence in industry and commerce.
Finance The BJP will handle public funds with the same care and caution as one would handle one’s own funds.
We will not impose any new taxes; We will reduce some taxes.
To begin with, the income tax exemption will be raised to ₹ 30,000; We will abolish octroi duty-and require the State Government to make good the loss of municipalities; We will abolish Sales Tax and require the Centre to make good the loss of State Governments, by matching increases in excise duties; We will rationalise and simplify the entire tax structure.
The highest rate of income tax shall be 49 per cent; All savings and investments in approved organisations (including non-government institutions.)
will be exempted from wealth tax and Estate duty; Corporation tax revenues will be shared with the States; Smugglers and other economic offenders will be severely dealt with; A strict watch will be kept on the operations of foreign   banks, We will encourage the growth of small local banks, duty supervised and guaranteed by the Reserve Bank of India.
Prices BJP will maintain price stability by efficient management of production and supplies, and by rooting out corruption.
Any rise in prices will be fully and promptly neutralised by increased DA in both private and public sectors and in private and Government service, including central, State and local government.
We will open more Fair Price Shops in towns and villages; existing arrangements will be streamlined.
Make not only grains, sugar and kerosene, but also pulses, cooking oil and soap and such sundry articles of every day use available at these shops.
Labour BJP believes in healthy trade unionism.
It will: Rationalise and simplify Labour Laws; Recognise unions on the basis of secret ballot; Introduce worker participation from the Shop Floor to the Board Room in all public sector projects, public limited companies and foreign companies operating in India; Insulate workers against inflation (specific measures spelt out in next chapter).
Full Employment BJP recognises the citizen’s Fundamental Right to work.
All our economic policies whether it is small dams or cottage industry, house construction or road building will boost employment.
In addition we will: Introduce Employment Guarantee Scheme on the Maharashtra pattern, throughout the country; There will be pensions for the aged poor: There will be ‘Antyodaya’ for the poorest of the poor.
4 There is a serious energy crisis throughout the world.
The crisis is particularly acute in India with heavy oil imports, serious power-shortages and high power prices.
This Situation will have to be tackled on a war-footing.
BJP will: Intensify efforts to find more oil, coal and natural gas reserves; Improve the working of power plants which are now functioning at less than 50 per cent of capacity; Stop the massive theft of electric power; Introduce power-efficient energy-saving devices in homes and factories; Increase forest cover from the present 19 per cent of land to the desired 33 per cent; Encourage wind, water, biogas and solar power generation.
Pay special attention to the development of nuclear energy.
   The People People, whether in the villages or in towns and cities, have had a raw deal all these years.
BJP will make life more bearable for them.
Villagers Since a majority of the people live in villages, a major portion of development funds will be invested in the villages; Drinking water will be made available to all the remaining about 1.5 lakh waterless villages during the next five years; Cow slaughter will be banned; In the first stage all villages with a population of 1,000 will be connected by pucca road; Likewise, all villages with a population of 1,000 will be given electric connection; Village artisans will be trained and their techniques modernised.
For example, smiths will become mechanics, carpenters will make furniture, washermen will become dry-cleaners etc; Local people will be given preference in the matter of local jobs; Panchayats will be reorganised in the true spirit of Panchayati Raj; Mobile courts will decide minor disputes locally.
Townsmen House construction by individuals, trusts, commercial establishments and cooperatives will be encouraged to   4 more houses available at reasonable rents; City water, power and sewage services will be improved; All applicants on the waiting list will be given telephone connections; The menace of goondas will be ended; All urban centres will be progressively made into garden cities.
Salariat The BJP fully appreciates the problems of the salaried class, now crushed between ‘fixed incomes and rising prices.
It will: Link salaries in private services also to cost of living index; Encourage employers to build houses for staff; Progressively introduce pension schemes in private service, private sector and public sector; Lower Life Insurance premia; Increase the return on Provident Fund deposits; Abolish Compulsory Deposit Scheme; Ensure payment of pension and GPF dues within one month of retirement; Ask all establishments to build Holiday Homes and organize cooperative stores, for their staff.
Government Employees Central Government employees suffer from all the problems of the salariat; additionally, their salaries are lower than those in private service.
Indeed, fourteen State Governments are paying higher salaries than the Central Government.
BJP will move fast in the matter.
It will: Ask the Fourth Pay Commission to submit a quick interim report, doing urgent justice to the employees; Order full and prompt neutralisation of all increases in the cost of living index; Immediately pay all arrears of DA instalments that have become due; Provide residential accommodation to all Government employees.
Pensioners The pensioners are the most hard-pressed in the fixed income group.
BJP will: Replace the 1871 Pension Act by a new law, more in tune with the changed social security concepts; Have a National Pensions Policy to secure social and economic justice to all citizens; Constitute a separate Pension Commission to examine the special problems of pensioners; Grant pensioners DA relief on the same scale as to serving employees; exempt pensioners from payment of income tax; Re-fix pensions as and when pay scales are revised; Grant travel concessions to pensioners.
Ex-servicemen The welfare of ex-servicemen is inextricably linked with the morale of serving personnel because we believe that today’s soldier, sail or airman is tomorrow’s ex-serviceman.
The BJP holds that insufficient attention has been paid to their welfare, pensions, re-employment and other allied matters, The BJP would work towards a purposeful resolution of all these problems.
We believe that the last Supreme Court judgement has given grounds for a great deal of disaffection.
We would, therefore, take steps to ensure that: Standard pension rate is kept at not less than 50 per cent of the total emoluments last drawn; Introduce one rank-one pension system.
This would include all old pensioners irrespective of their date of retirement; Introduce a proper system for taking into account the cost of living and corresponding adjustments in pensions.
Take steps to restore the commuted value of pension or, completion of the period of commutation; Widows of pensioners who retired prior to 1.1.1964 to be given the same pension as is applicable in the case of family pensioners or reservists; Strengthen Zilla and District Sainik Boards; Enlarge the terms of reference of the Fourth Central Pay Commission so as to include the question of pensions.
4 Castes & Scheduled Tribes The BJP takes note of the fact that during the last few years, oppression of Harijans and tribals has increased manifold.
The party is resolved to exert its full strength in defence of these underprivileged sections.
It will: Enforce laws against untouchability very stringently; Give preference to Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes; In the allotment of surplus land to agricultural labour, and housing sites to the homeless; Take steps towards employing mechanical means of handling refuse, and thus to do away with the degrading practice of carrying night soil on the head; Evolve a new forest policy based on a partnership between the forest tribals and the forest authorities; Frame policies which protect tribals from exploitation, land-alienation and indebtedness, and enable them to grow in accordance with their own genius.
Women Though women are described as the better half, they continue to be treated worse.
BJP will redress this Unbalance.
We will: Implement the Report of the Committee on the Status of Women (December 1974); Build hostels for single women working in the cities; Provide smokeless Chulas at concessional rates to village women; Make registration of marriages compulsory—like births and deaths—to prevent child marriages; Make the wife equal co-sharer in the husband’s wealth and income; Treat bride burning injuries as attempt to murder and dowry deaths as murder wider section 302.
I.P.C.
Children BJP looks upon Children as the greatest wealth of the nation.
We will give them: Good Schools; Good health care specially against gastro-enteritis; Good milk to drink; Good play-grounds.
   Quality Of Life Man does not live by bread alone.
He must also have health and housing, education and sports, and above all a happy environment.
Health Health is wealth.
BJP considers hygiene, sanitation and nutrition as more important than medicines and hospitals.
We will: Along with Allopathy, recognise and promote Ayurveda and Siddha, Unani and Homeopathy, Chromopathy and Nature Cure and, in general, encourage holistic healing; Supply free milk to needy children in primary schools; Give every child an annual physical check-up; Improve the present district Civil hospitals and set up similar hospitals at taluka level; Give every village a Health Care Centre, to take particular care of expectant mothers; Have a Mobile Dispensary in each taluka; Build more and better public latrines particularly for women in villages; Organise Eye Camps, and camps for other serious ailments in various areas; Implement Hathi Committee Report on Pharmaceuticals to break the stranglehold of drug companies, and make basic drugs available cheap to the people.
Education Knowledge is power.
BJP views education as the key to allround development of personality, and the progress and prosperity of the masses.
We will:   4 .
Implement Article 45 of the Constitution to give free education to all children in the 6-14 age group; Launch an Adult Literacy Programme; Give education a vocational and technical content; Make some school texts common throughout the country for national integration; consciously promote among school children feelings of patriotism and commitment to the nation; Raise the emoluments and status of teachers; Introduce compulsory moral instruction, that will be nondenominational but character-building; Ensure academic freedom and the autonomy of universities; Provide the universities with communication channels to carry their knowledge resources down to the village level; Eliminate political interference from educational institutions; Delink jobs from degrees.
Science & Technology BJP views science and technology as handmaids of human welfare.
It will: Foster a scientific temper among the people; Use Science and Technology for increasing productivity and generating employment; Put new life in National Laboratories; Direct these laboratories to evolve Appropriate Technology for Indian industrial needs; Specially develop biochemistry, cybernetics, avionics, electronics, nuclear technology and technocracy; Create the right working conditions, for our best brains to remain here and serve the country and not migrate to other lands.
Housing BJP regards it as the basic right of a family to own a house.
It will: Give housing sites to the rural poor; Give them interest-free loans to build pucca houses;   Encourage house construction with local materials; Convert city slums into housing colonies and meanwhile extend to them all civic amenities; Rationalise Housing and Rent Control Laws; Encourage all establishments to build houses for their own stall—as also help employees to build their own houses; Double the number of houses now built annually by various State Housing Boards; Encourage Cooperative Housing Societies; Build new townships round an industry in the countryside.
Family Welfare BJP believes in the sanctity of life.
It appreciates small happy families.
It is committed to family planning as a means of individual and national development.
Make Family Planning information and facilities available to the people; Perform Vasectomy and Tubectomy operations free; Help childless couples with medical assistance to have a child.
Environment We look upon India as a holy land.
Our land, air and waters, our hills, forests, flora and fauna are all sacred to us.
We all keep them neat, clean and intact.
We will: Require anti-pollution devices to be installed to process and clean up industrial and municipal effluents before the same are discharged into our rivers; Keep a strict watch on chemical fertilizers and insecticides, for any poisoning of the soil; Improve auto exhausts, to prevent the fouling of the air; Curb the aggression of noise in the cities; Plant 20 crore trees every year; While protecting the traditional rights of Vanavasis, we will require the planting of three trees for every single  tree that is cut by anybody for any reason.
4 The BJP reaffirms its commitment to the freedom of thought and expression.
We will: Make freedom of the Press an explicit Fundamental Right, and not just an implied one derived from the citizen’s right to Freedom of Expression; Encourage the growth of the Press by abolishing the duty on newsprint and the tax on newspaper advertising; Revive the Prasar Bharati Bill of 1979, which sought to convert AIR and Doordarshan into an autonomous corporation sui generis.
This Corporation would have greater autonomy than that enjoyed by BBC today; Review the Official Secrets Act in so far as it obstructs the Right to Know and enact a Freedom of Information law on the US lines, Implement the P.C.
Joshi Report on T.V.
software, to improve the quality of T.V.
programmes.
Films BJP recognises the “real role of cinema in entertainment education and national integration.
It is also conscious of the damage that is being caused to the moral and social fibre of the people by their exposure to violence and vulgarity in films.
The censors can play only a negative role.
What is needed is conscious promotion and development of good cinema.
The BJP will: Have, in addition to A and U Films, ‘Q’, that is Quality films, which will be exempt from entertainment taxes; Have special theatres in metropolitan centres to screen art films and other Quality films.
Implement the recommendations of the Karanth Committee on National Film Policy.
Arts Art is the essence of life.
BJP will encourage all art forms.
It will make the various arts, part of Education, Production and Life.
To promote theatre, BJP will, as a rule, exempt all theatrical performances from entertainment tax.
Sports Government has set up a Sports Ministry; but it has issued a Policy Directives.
And it has few resources, BJP will that and put India on the Olympic map of the world, We will: Move Sports from the State List to the Concurrent List; Enunciate a National Sports Policy; Require Government to provide playgrounds for all schools; Have a National Sports Council to develop stadium playing in fields gymnasia, swimming pools, indoor stadia all over the country; Take care of the nutrition of promising sportsmen; Eliminate political interference from the Nation, Sports Federations and the National Olympic Council; Charge NSF and NOC with the task of coaching and guiding of athletes; Meanwhile concentrate on events in which we can make a mark and forget the events in which we arc nowhere in the picture, to avoid humiliation and demoralization.
   4 Security National security is a primary responsibility.
The BJP would work towards fulfilling this national duty with a sense of high purpose.
Security of the nation is an integrated whole: an amalgam of the internal, the economic, the social, the political, the military and the diplomatic.
Internal cohesiveness, and a united and determined national will is the foundation of a nation’s defence preparedness.
The BJP will, therefore, resolve the social and political turmoil in strategically sensitive border states like J & K, Punjab, North East and Assam.
Indian diplomacy can assist in the protection of our national interests only if it is guided by a purposeful foreign policy.
Foreign Policy The BJP will continue to follow an independent foreign policy committed to world peace, disarmament and a new international economic order.
We believe that the task of freeing the world from economic exploitation, external influences, domination, and colonialism in all its new forms is yet to be completed.
For this a continued strengthening of the non-aligned movement is the foundation of our policy plank.
BJP will: Work towards re-imparting dynamism to the non-aligned movement; Reject the domination of super-power Interests in South Asia and the Indian Ocean; Pursue a poilcy of peace, friendship and cooperation with its neighbouring countries; Re-establish India’s Asian identity with emphasis on a policy of constructive cooperation in South and South East Asia; Strengthen South Asian Regional Conference and work   towards the formation of closer economic ties leading to the establishment of a regional common market; Initiate fresh endeavours for the withdrawal of foreign forces from Afghanistan, a political solution of the Afghan problem, free from outside intervention or interference so that Afghanistan and its identity as an independent, non-aligned nation could be re-established; Work for the establishment of a new international economic order; take initiative for trade and monetary reform; North- South dialogue with emphasis on enhanced South-South co-operation; Work towards Non-aligned initiatives for a resolution of the Iran-Iraq war; the problem in Lebanon and the Arab- Israel dispute; Continued efforts for the freedom of Namibia, and a worldwide rejection of apartheid; and Continuously work towards the solution of problems of people of Indian origin living abroad, more particularly the plight of Tamils in Sri Lanka.
Defence The Bhartiya Janata Party will exert for: Optimum defence preparedness; Diversification of sources of supply of defence hardware; continued emphasis on maximizing indigenous production; self-reliance and Defence Research and Development; Greater public accountabiiity of defence expenditure; Enhancement of Indian Navy’s capability; Identification, and elimination of foreign lobbies associated with defence weapons procurement and contracts; and Improve service conditions in the Armed Forces so as to make careers in the Army, Navy, and Air Force more attractive to the best talent in the country.
Here above is a proud and patriotic programme that the BJP pledges to implement.
And it has the will, the ability and the integrity to implement it well.
Its disciplined cadres are the envy of other parties.
And its collective leadership, headed by the inimitable Atal Bihari Vajpayee is the best and the brightest in the land.
4 BJP commits itself to addressing all religious, linguistic and ethnic groups and work purposefully for a just and speedy redressal of their due grievances and issues that alienate.
It reaffirms its faith in all Indians being co-sharers in the continuing task of nation-building and invites all to work shoulder to shoulder with the rest of their brethren.
This process of heating and reconciliation cannot be undertaken by that very government which earlier caused the dismemberment of our national consensus.
The BJP commits itself afresh to the betterment of the Harijan, the Girijan, the backward, the downtrodden, the working class, the unemployed, the artisan and the women of India.
The betterment of the kisan, the upliftment of the rural landless and the amelioration of the lot of the poorest of the poor is our firm commitment.
To the youth of India we make a special appeal.
You are the future destiny of our land.
Come, join us in our endeavour, to build a new India.
The BJP accepts the challenge of the day, pledges itself to meeting the need of the hour, invites all citizen’s to share these concerns and aspirations, and to join with us in our quest for a new value-based polity.